<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Luca Barbareschi<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (born <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>July 28, 1956<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Montevideo<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>) is an <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Italian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>- <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Uruguayan<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> actor, television presenter and politician, member of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Italian Chamber of Deputies<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
He was one of four actors whom the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Italian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> police believed had been murdered in the making of the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1980<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> horror film <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Cannibal Holocaust<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. So realistic was the film that shortly after it was released its director <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ruggero Deodato<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was arrested for murder. The actors had signed contracts to stay out of the media for a year in order to fuel rumours that the film was a snuff movie. The court was only convinced that they were alive when the contracts were cancelled and the actors appeared on a television show as proof.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2008<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> he was elected as Member of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Italian Parliament<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Chamber of Deputies<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Silvio Berlusconi<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s centre-right party <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>People of Freedom<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2010<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> he joined, with other 32 deputies and 10 senators, the <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Gianfranco Fini<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s new party "<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Future and Freedom for Italy<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>".
