<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Yakov Mikhaylovich Sverdlov<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Russian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>:); known under pseudonyms "<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Andrei<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>", "<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mikhalych<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>", "<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Max<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>", "<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Smirnov<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>", "<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Permyakov<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>" <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>3 June<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> [O.S. <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>22 May<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>] 1885  <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>16 March 1919<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) was a <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Bolshevik party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> leader and an official of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Russian Soviet Republic<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
He was born in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Nizhny Novgorod<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> to <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Jewish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> parents. His father was an engraver. He was adopted by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Maxim Gorky<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. He joined the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Russian Social Democratic Labour Party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1902<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, and then the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Bolshevik<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> faction, supporting <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Vladimir Lenin<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. He was involved in the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1905<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> revolution.
After his arrest in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>June 1906<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, for most of the time until <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1917<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> he was either imprisoned or exiled. During the period <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1914<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>-<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1916<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> he was in internal exile in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Turukhansk<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Siberia<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, along with <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Joseph Stalin<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.
After the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1917 February<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Revolution<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> he returned to <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Petrograd<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> from exile and was re-elected to the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Central Committee<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. He played an important role in planning the October <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Revolution<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. Research in 1990 by the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Moscow<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> playwright and historian Edvard Radzinsky uncovered <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sverdlov<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s role in the murder of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Tsar Nicholas II<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and his family. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sverdlov<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> ordered their execution on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>July 16, 1918<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, which took place in the city of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Yekaterinburg<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.
A close ally of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Vladimir Lenin<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sverdlov<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> played an important role in persuading leading <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Bolsheviks<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> to accept the controversial decisions to close down the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Constituent Assembly<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and to sign the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Treaty of Brest-Litovsk<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. It was claimed that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lenin<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> provided the theories and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sverdlov<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> made sure they worked. Later their relationship suffered as <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lenin<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> appeared to be too theoretical for practical <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sverdlov<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, who at that time was the chief architect of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Red Terror<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
He is sometimes referred to as the first head of state of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Soviet Union<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> but this is not correct since the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Soviet Union<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> came into existence in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1922<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, three years after <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sverdlov<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s death. However, as chairman of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>All-Russian Central Executive Committee<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>VTsIK<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>) he was the de jure head of state of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Russian SFSR<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> from shortly after the October <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Revolution<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> until the time of his death.
An official version is that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sverdlov<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> died of influenza in Oryol during the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1918<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> flu pandemic, while returning to <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Moscow<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> from <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Kharkiv<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. He is buried in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Kremlin Wall Necropolis<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Moscow<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. Another version is that he died of tuberculosis. According to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Paganuzzi<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>March 16, 1919<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he visited <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Morozov<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s factory in <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Moscow<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> where a worker hit him on his head with a heavy object at around four in the afternoon.. Historian <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Arkadi Waksberg<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> claimed that there were reliable rumours that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sverdlov<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was beaten to death by workers in Oryol, due to his <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Jewish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> origin and the whole affair was covered up to prevent anti-semitic outburst. Another speculation is that he was eliminated due to his involvement in an attempt to.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1924<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Yekaterinburg<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> was renamed <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sverdlov<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>sk in his honor. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1991<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Boris Yeltsin<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> began reverting pre-Soviet names in Russia, and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sverdlov<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>sk was changed back to <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Yekaterinburg<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.
His son <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Andrei<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> had a long career as an officer for the Soviet security organs (NKVD, OGPU). His niece Ida married <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>NKVD<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> chief <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Genrikh Yagoda<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
The Imperial <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Russian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> Navy destroyer leader <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Novik<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (commissioned in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1913<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) was renamed Yakov <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sverdlov<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1923<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. The first ship of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sverdlov<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> class cruisers was also named after him.
