<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Dimitrie Pompeiu<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Romanian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> pronunciation:&#160; ; <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>4 October 1873<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> [O.S. <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>22 September<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>], <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Broscǎuţi<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Botoşani County<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Romania<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> – <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>8 October 1954<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Bucharest<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>) was a well-known <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Romanian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> mathematician.
After studying in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Dorohoi<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Bucharest<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, he went to <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>France<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, where he studied mathematics at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Paris<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Sorbonne<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>). He obtained a Ph.D. degree in mathematics in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1905<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> with a thesis, On the continuity of complex variable functions, written under the direction of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Henri Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. After returning to <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Romania<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, he was named Professor of Mechanics at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Iaşi<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1912<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he assumed a chair at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Bucharest<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1934<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he was elected member of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Romanian Academy<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
His contributions were mainly in the field of mathematical analysis, complex functions theory, and rational mechanics. In an article published in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1929<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he posed a challenging conjecture in integral geometry, now widely known as the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Pompeiu problem<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. Among his contributions to real analysis there is the construction, dated <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1906<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, of non-constant, everywhere differentiable functions, with derivative vanishing on a dense set. Such derivatives are now called <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Pompeiu derivatives<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Adrian Năstase<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; · .
