<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ali Babacan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Turkish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> pronunciation:&#160; ; born <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>4 April 1967<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Ankara<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Turkey<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>) is a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Turkish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> politician and the current Deputy Prime Minister of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Turkey<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> responsible for the Economy. He was previously Minister of Economy in the 58th cabinet from the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Justice and Development Party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>AK Party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>). On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>August 29, 2007<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he was named Minister of Foreign Affairs of in the cabinet of re-elected Prime Minister <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Recep Tayyip Erdoğan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Babacan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> succeeded <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Abdullah Gül<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, who became President.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Babacan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> graduated from the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>TED Ankara College<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> ranking first among the class of <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1985<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. He attended the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Middle East Technical University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Ankara<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1989<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> was awarded a BSc in Industrial Engineering with the highest marks. He went to the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>U.S<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. on a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Fulbright Scholarship<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> to do postgraduate studies and in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1992<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> received an MBA from the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Kellogg School of Management<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> at <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Northwestern University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Evanston<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Illinois<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, with majors in marketing, organizational behavior and international business.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Babacan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> worked then for two years as an associate at <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>QRM, Inc.<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Chicago<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Illinois<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, a company doing financial consulting to the top executives of major banks in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>United States<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. He returned to <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Turkey<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1994<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and, served as chief advisor to the mayor of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Ankara<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> the same year. He was the chairman of his family owned textile company between <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1994<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2002<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
He entered politics in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2001<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> as a co-founder and a Board member of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Justice and Development Party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and was elected to parliament as deputy for <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Ankara<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>November 3, 2002<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. He was appointed Minister of Economy on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>November 18, 2002<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and became the youngest member of the cabinet, then at the age of 35.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Babacan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> had the duty to steer a painful economic reform program, which was backed by multi-billion-dollar <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>IMF<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> loans; with its help <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Turkish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> economy achieved a remarkable recovery after two severe crises. He stayed always away from the rough-and-tumble of the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Turkish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> political arena and focused solely on the economic reform, acting rather as a technocrat without indulging into populism.
On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>May 24, 2005<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, Prime Minister <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Recep Tayyip Erdoğan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> announced his appointment as chief negotiator in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Turkey<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s accession talks with the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>European Union<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, which started on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>October 3, 2005<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
As government minister <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Babacan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> has attended several international meetings including the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>World Economic Forum<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Davos<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Switzerland<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, and the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Bilderberg Group<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>May 1, 2009<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Babacan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was appointed as minister responsible for the economy by Prime Minister <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Erdoğan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, and with additional responsibility for the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Treasury<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
 .
