<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Tille Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>November 11, 1922<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>  <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>October 23, 2011<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) was a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Canadian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> judge who was known for being <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Saskatchewan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s first female magistrate. She also was an advocate for social justice in areas such as poverty, women's rights and prison reform, and in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1972<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> she was named the first chair of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Saskatchewan Human Rights Commission<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
She was born <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Tillie Goldenberg<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>J. M.<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sarah Goldenberg<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1922<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>J. M.<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was a <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Saskatoon<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> lawyer. She received her Bachelor of Arts degree from the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Saskatchewan<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1941<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. Later, after having married and after her two children were born, she returned to studies and obtained her LLB in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1956<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. She was the only woman in her class.
She met her husband <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>George Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> while both were volunteering in the in the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1930<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>s; her parents initially disapproved because <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>George<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and his family were communists. They married in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1941<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>George<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> completed his law degree while <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Tillie<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> supported him working as a secretary. He went on to become a well-respected labour lawyer, and for part of his career worked in <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Tillie<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s father's firm. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>George<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Tillie<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> continued to be involved in politics, supporting the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Co-operative Commonwealth Federation<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (later, the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>New Democratic Party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>).
After law school, she worked in the<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/> Saskatoon Land Titles Office<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, as deputy registrar. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1960<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> she became the first woman to be appointed as a provincial magistrate in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Saskatchewan<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. She might also have been the first <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Jewish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> person to be named magistrate, but that is less clear. Presiding over misdemeanours, she became more aware of the association between crime and poverty, and began to push for reforms, through such organizations as the John Howard Society, the Medical Care Insurance Commission of Saskatchewan, and the Provincial Commission of Inquiry into Legal Aid. Collaborating with Roger Carter, the law school dean at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Saskatchewan<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, she helped to build opportunities for <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Aboriginal<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> people to enter the field of law.
When the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Saskatchewan Human Rights Commission<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> was created in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1972<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, she was named its first chair. There was criticism that she had named abortion as a human right, but neither she nor the commission as a whole gave in to the pressure to remove it. In 1976 she was elected as a director on the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Canadian Research Institute for the Advancement of Women<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. From <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1977<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1987<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, she served on the board of governors of the Canadian Council on Social Development.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> suffered a severe stroke in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1995<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, but recovered much of her lost speech and mobility, despite a poor prognosis initially. She died at the age of 88, on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>October 23, 2011<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
