<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Iulia Antoanella Motoc<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>is a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Romanian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>international law professor and international expert, now Member of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>United Nations Human Rights Committee<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mococ<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>is a professor at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Bucharest<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, where she holds courses on International law, <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Human rights<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>European law<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. She has also lectured at several Universities, including <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>NYU<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Yale University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>European University Institute<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Florence<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>UN University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Tokyo<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. According to "<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Pladoyer pour les droits de l'homme<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>" she was the youngest <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>UN<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>Special Rapporteur. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Iulia Motoc<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>was appointed judge at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Constitutional Court of Romania<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2010<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
Born in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Timi_oara<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, she graduated from the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>School of law<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Bucharest<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Iulia Antoanella Motoc<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>holds a master degree from the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Paul Cýzanne University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>School of Law<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Aix-Marseille<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, a doctorate in international law from <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Paul Cýzanne University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Aix-Marseille<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>(summa cum laude), an habilitation in law from <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Jean Monnet Department University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/><tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Paris Sud<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>and doctorate in ethics from the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Bucharest<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>,<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Department of Philosophy<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Iulia Antoanella Motoc<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>was former member and President of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>UN Sub commission on the promotion and protection of Human Rights<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. She was also <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>UN<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>Special Rapporteur for human rights situation in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Democratic Republic of the Congo<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>and the youngest <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>human Rights<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>United Nations<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>(according to "<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Plaidoyer pour les droits de l'homme<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>"). It this quality she paid special attention to violence against women and children. She visited <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>NYU School of law<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>as a Fulbright scholar co-teaching courses in <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>International Law<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Yale Law School<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>as Senior Schell Fellow. She was prized for her academic achievements and elected in the several prestigious academic Boards, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>ESIL<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>International Board of Academics<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Practitioners Melbourne University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>TMC Asser<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/><tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Netherlands<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>EMA Director<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>EIUC<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/><tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Venice<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. She is a <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>UN<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>Special Rapporteur on <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Human Genome<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>and <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Human Rights<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, Member of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Human Rights Committee<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>and Member of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Advisory Committee for the Framework Convention on the Protection on Minorities<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Council of Europe<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Iulia Antoanella Motoc<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>is an arbiter and conciliator with <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>ICSID<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Washington<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.
<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Iulia Antoanella Motoc<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>is married with the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Romanian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>Ambassador to <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>EU<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/><tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mihnea Motoc<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>and they have a son, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Luca-mihnea<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
