<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Dame Elizabeth Rosemond "Liz" Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>DBE<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (February 27, 1932&#160; –&#160; March 23, 2011) was a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>British<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>-<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>American<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> actress. From her early years as a child star with <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>MGM<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, she became one of the great screen actresses of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Hollywood<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>'s <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Golden Age<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. As one of the world's most famous film stars, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was recognized for her acting ability and for her glamorous lifestyle, beauty and distinctive violet eyes.
<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>National Velvet<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (1944) was <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s first success, and she starred in <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Father of the Bride<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (1950), <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>A Place in the Sun<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (1951), <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Giant<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (1956), <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Cat on a Hot Tin Roof<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (1958), and <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Suddenly, Last Summer<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (1959). She won the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Academy Award<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> for Best Actress for <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>BUtterfield 8<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (1960), played the title role in <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Cleopatra<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (1963), and married her co-star <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Richard Burton<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. They appeared together in 11 films, including <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Who's Afraid of Virginia Woolf?<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (1966), for which <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> won a second <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Academy Award<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. From the mid-1970s, she appeared less frequently in film, and made occasional appearances in television and theatre.
Her much publicized personal life included eight marriages and several life-threatening illnesses. From the mid-1980s, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> championed <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>HIV<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> and <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>AIDS<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> programs; she co-founded the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>American Foundation<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> for <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>AIDS<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> Research in 1985, and the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Elizabeth Taylor AIDS Foundation<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in 1993. She received the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Presidential Citizens Medal<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Legion of Honour<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Jean Hersholt Humanitarian Award<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> and a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Life Achievement Award<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> from the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>American Film Institute<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, who named her seventh on their list of the "<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Greatest American Screen Legends<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>". <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> died of congestive heart failure at the age of 79.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Elizabeth Rosemond Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was born at <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Heathwood<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, her parents' home at <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>8 Wildwood Road<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Hampstead Garden Suburb<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, a northwestern suburb of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>London<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>; the younger of two children of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Francis Lenn Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (1897–1968) and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sara Viola Warmbrodt<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (1895–1994), who were <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Americans<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> residing in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>England<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s older brother, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Howard Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, was born in 1929. Her parents were originally from <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Arkansas City<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Kansas<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Francis Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was an art dealer, and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sara<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was a former actress whose stage name was "<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sara Sothern<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>". <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sothern<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> retired from the stage in 1926 when she married <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Francis<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>New York City<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s two first names are in honor of her paternal grandmother, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Elizabeth Mary<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Rosemond<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>) <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
Colonel <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Victor Cazalet<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, one of their closest friends, had an important influence on the family. He was a rich, well-connected bachelor, a Member of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Parliament<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and close friend of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Winston Churchill<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Cazalet<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> loved both art and theater and was passionate when encouraging the <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> family to think of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>England<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> as their permanent home. Additionally, as a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Christian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> Scientist and lay preacher, his links with the family were spiritual. He also became <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Elizabeth<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s godfather. In one instance, when she was suffering with a severe infection as a child, she was kept in her bed for weeks. She "begged" for his company: "Mother, please call <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Victor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and ask him to come and sit with me.":14.
Biographer <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Alexander Walker<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> suggests that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Elizabeth<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s conversion to <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Judaism<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> at the age of 27 and her life-long support for <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, may have been influenced by views she heard at home. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Walker<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> notes that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Cazalet<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> actively campaigned for a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Jewish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> homeland, and her mother also worked in various charities, which included sponsoring fundraisers for <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Zionism<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. Her mother recalls the influence that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Cazalet<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> had on <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Elizabeth<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>:.
A dual citizen of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>United Kingdom<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>United States<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, she was born <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>British<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, through her birth on <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>British<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> soil and an <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>American<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> citizen through her parents. She reportedly sought, in 1965, to renounce her <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>United States<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> citizenship, to wit: "Though never accepted by the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>State Department<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Elizabeth<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> renounced in 1965. Attempting to shield much of her <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>European<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> income from <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>U.S.<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> taxes, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Elizabeth<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> wished to become solely a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>British<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> citizen. According to news reports at the time, officials denied her request when she failed to complete the renunciation oath, refusing to say that she renounced "all allegiance to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>United States of America<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.".
At the age of three, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> began taking ballet lessons. Shortly before the beginning of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>World War II<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, her parents decided to return to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>United States<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> to avoid hostilities. Her mother took the children first, arriving in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>New York<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in April 1939, while her father remained in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>London<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> to wrap up matters in his art business, arriving in November. They settled in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Los Angeles<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>California<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, where her father established a new art gallery, which included many paintings he shipped from <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>England<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. The gallery would soon attract numerous <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Hollywood<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> celebrities who appreciated its modern <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>European<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> paintings. According to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Walker<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, the gallery "opened many doors for the <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>s, leading them directly into the society of money and prestige" within <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Hollywood<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>'s movie colony.:27.
Soon after settling in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Los Angeles<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s mother discovered that <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Hollywood<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> people "habitually saw a movie future for every pretty face." Some of her mother's friends, and even total strangers, urged her to have <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> screen tested for the role of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bonnie Blue<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Scarlett<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s child in <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Gone with the Wind<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, then being filmed. Her mother refused the idea, as a child actress in film was alien to her. And in any regard, they would return to <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>England<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> after the war.:28.
<tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Hollywood<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> columnist <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hedda Hopper<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> introduced the <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylors<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Andrea Berens<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, the fiancée of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>John Cheever Cowdin<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, chairman and major stockholder of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Universal Pictures<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Berens<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> insisted that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sara<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> take <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> to see <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Cowden<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> who, she assured, would be dazzled by her breathtaking beauty. <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>also became interested in <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>MGM<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> head<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/> Louis B. Mayer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> reportedly told his producer, "Sign her up, sign her up! What are you waiting for?" As a result, she soon had both <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Universal<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>MGM<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> willing to place her under contract. When <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Universal<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> learned that <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>MGM<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> was equally interested, however, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Cowden<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> telephoned <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Universal<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> from <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>New York<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>: "Sign her up, he ordered, don't even wait for the screen test." <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Universal<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> then gave her a seven-year contract.:31.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> appeared in her first motion picture at the age of nine in <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>There's One Born Every Minute<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (1942), her only film for <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Universal<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. After less than a year, however, the studio fired <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> for unknown reasons. Some speculate that she did not live up to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Cowden<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s promise. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Walker<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> believes that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s intuition told her "she wasn't really welcome at <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Universal<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>." She learned, for instance, that her casting director complained, "The kid has nothing, " after a test. Even her beautiful eyes—they were a deep blue that appeared violet and stunned those who met her in person, with a mutation that gave <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> double eyelashes—did not impress him: "Her eyes are too old, she doesn't have the face of a child, " he said.:32 But <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Walker<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> admits that "this was not so far off the mark as it may appear now." He explains:.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> herself remembers that when she was a child in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>England<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, adults used to describe her as having an "old soul, " because, as she says, "I was totally direct." She also recognized similar traits in her baby daughter:.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s father served as an air raid warden with <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>MGM<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> producer <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sam Marx<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, and learned that the studio was searching for an <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>English<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> actress for a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Lassie<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> film. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> received the role and was offered a long-term contract at the beginning of 1943. She chose <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>MGM<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> because "the people there had been nicer to her when she went to audition, " <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> recalled.:32 <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>MGM<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s production chief, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Benny Thau<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, was to remain the "only <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>MGM<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> executive" she fully trusted during subsequent years, because, writes <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Walker<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, "he had, out of kindly habit, made the gesture that showed her she was loved.":32 <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Thau<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> remembered her as a "little dark-haired beauty...[with] those strange and lovely eyes that gave the face its central focus, oddly powerful in someone so young.":34 <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>MGM<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, in addition, was considered a "glamorous studio, " boasting that it had "more stars than there are in heaven." Before <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s mother would sign the contract, however, she sought certainty that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> had a "<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>God<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>-given talent" to become an actress. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Walker<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> describes how they came to a decision:.
<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>MGM<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> cast <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> in <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Lassie Come Home<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (1943) with child star <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Roddy McDowall<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, with whom she would share a lifelong friendship. He later recalled regarding her beauty, "who has double eyelashes except a girl who was absolutely born to be on the big screen?" The film received favorable attention for both actors, and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>MGM<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> signed <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> to a conventional seven-year contract starting at $100 a week and with regular raises. Her first assignment under her new contract was a loan-out to <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>20th Century Fox<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> for the character of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Helen Burns<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> in a film version of the <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Charlotte Brontë<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> novel <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Jane Eyre<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (1944). <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> returned to <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>England<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> to appear in another <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McDowall<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> picture for <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>MGM<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>The White Cliffs of Dover<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (1944).
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s persistence in seeking the role of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Velvet<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> Brown in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>MGM<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>National Velvet<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> made her a star at the age of 12. Her character is a young girl who trains her beloved horse to win the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Grand National<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Velvet<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, which costarred fellow young actor <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mickey Rooney<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>English<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> newcomer <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Angela Lansbury<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, became a great success upon its release in December 1944. Many years later <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> called it "the most exciting film" she had ever made, although the film caused many of her later back problems due to her falling off a horse during filming.
Viewers and critics "fell in love with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Elizabeth Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> when they saw her in it." <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Walker<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> explains why the film was popular:.
<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Velvet<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> grossed over US$4&#160; million and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>MGM<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> signed <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> to a new long-term contract. Because of the movie's success she was cast in another animal film, <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Courage of Lassie<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (1946), in which <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bill<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> the dog outsmarts the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Nazis<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. The film's success led to another contract for <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> paying her $750 per week. Her roles as <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mary Skinner<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> in a loan-out to <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Warner Brothers' Life With Father<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (1947), <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Cynthia Bishop<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> in <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Cynthia<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (1947), <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Carol Pringle<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> in <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>A Date with Judy<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (1948), and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Susan Prackett<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> in <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Julia Misbehaves<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (1948) were all successful. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> received a reputation as a consistently successful adolescent actress, with a nickname of "One-Shot Liz" (referring to her ability to shoot a scene in one take) and a promising career. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s portrayal of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Amy<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> in the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>American<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> classic <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Little Women<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (1949) was her last adolescent role.
The teenage <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was reluctant to continue making films. Her stage mother forced <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> to relentlessly practice until she could cry on cue and watched her during filming, signaling to change her delivery or a mistake. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> met few others her age on movie sets, and was so poorly educated that she needed to use her fingers to do basic arithmetic. When at age 16 <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> told her parents that she wanted to quit acting for a normal childhood, however, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sara<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/><tag name="PERSON" value="start"/> Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> told her that she was ungrateful: "You have a responsibility, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Elizabeth<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. Not just to this family, but to the country now, the whole world".
In October 1948, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> sailed aboard the RMS&#160; <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Queen Mary<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> to <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>England<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> to begin filming <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Conspirator<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. Unlike some other child actors, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> made an easy transition to adult roles. Before <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Conspirators<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> 1949 release, a TIME cover article called her "a jewel of great price, a true star sapphire", and the leader among <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Hollywood<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>'s next generation of stars such as <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Montgomery Clift<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Kirk Douglas<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ava Gardner<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. The petite <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> had the figure of a mature woman, with a 19" waist. <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Conspirator<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> failed at the box office, but 16-year-old <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s portrayal of a 21-year-old debutante who unknowingly marries a communist spy played by 38-year-old <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Robert Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, was praised by critics for her first adult lead in a film. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s first picture under her new salary of $2, 000 per week was <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>The Big Hangover<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (1950), both a critical and box office failure, that paired her with screen idol <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Van Johnson<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. The picture also failed to present <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> with an opportunity to exhibit her newly realized sensuality.
Her first box office success in an adult role came as <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Kay Banks<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> in the romantic comedy <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Father of the Bride<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (1950), alongside <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Spencer Tracy<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Joan Bennett<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. The film spawned a sequel, <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Father's Little Dividend<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (1951), which <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s costar <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Spencer Tracy<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> summarized with "boring… boring… boring". The film did well at the box office but it would be <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s next picture that would set the course for her career as a dramatic actress.
In late 1949, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> had begun filming <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>George Stevens<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>' <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>A Place in the Sun<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. Upon its release in 1951, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was hailed for her performance as <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Angela Vickers<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, a spoiled socialite who comes between <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>George Eastman<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Clift<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>) and his poor, pregnant factory-working girlfriend <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Alice Tripp<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Shelley Winters<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>). The film, based on <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Theodore Dreiser<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s novel, <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>An American Tragedy<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, was an indictment of "the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>American dream<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>" and its corrupting influences, notes biographer <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Kitty Kelley<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
Although <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, then only 17, was unaware of the psychological implications of the story and its powerful nuances, it became the pivotal performance of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s career. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Kelley<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> explains that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Stevens<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, its director, knew that with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Elizabeth Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> as the young and beautiful star, the "audience would understand why <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>George Eastman<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Clift<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>) would kill for a place in the sun with her." <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Hollywood<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> columnist <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hedda Hopper<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, allowed on the set to watch the filming, became "wide-eyed watching the little girl from <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>National Velvet<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> seduce <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Montgomery Clift<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> in front of the camera, " writes <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Kelley<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. When the scene was over, Hopper went to her, "<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Elizabeth<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, where on earth did you ever learn how to make love like that?".
Critics acclaimed the film as a classic, a reputation it sustained throughout the next 50 years of cinema history. <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>The New York Times<tag name="MISC" value="end"/><tag name="PERSON" value="start"/> A.H. Weiler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> wrote, "<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Elizabeth<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s delineation of the rich and beauteous Angela is the top effort of her career", and the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Boxoffice<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> reviewer unequivocally stated "Miss <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> deserves an <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Academy Award<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>".
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> became increasingly unsatisfied with the roles being offered to her at the time. While she wanted to play the lead roles in The Barefoot Contessa and I'll Cry Tomorrow, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>MGM<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> continued to restrict her to mindless and somewhat forgettable films such as: a cameo as herself in Callaway Went Thataway (1951), Love Is Better Than Ever (1952), Ivanhoe (1952), The Girl Who Had Everything (1953) and Beau Brummel (1954). She had wanted to play the role of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lady Rowena in Ivanhoe<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, but the part was given to Joan Fontaine. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was given the role of Rebecca. When <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> became pregnant with her first child, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>MGM<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> forced her through The Girl Who Had Everything (even adding two hours to her daily work schedule) so as to get one more film out of her before she became too heavily pregnant. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> lamented that she needed the money, as she had just bought a new house with second husband <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Michael Wilding<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and with a child on the way things would be pretty tight. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> had been forced by her pregnancy to turn down Elephant Walk (1954), though the role had been designed for her. Vivien Leigh, almost two decades <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s senior, but to whom <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> bore a striking resemblance, got the part and went to Ceylon to shoot on location. Leigh suffered a nervous breakdown during filming, and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> reclaimed the role after the birth of her child <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Michael Wilding<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, Jr. in January 1953.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s next screen endeavor, <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Rhapsody<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (1954), another tedious romantic drama, proved equally frustrating. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> portrayed <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Louise Durant<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, a beautiful rich girl in love with a temperamental violinist (<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Vittorio Gassman<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>) and an earnest young pianist (<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>John Ericson<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>). A film critic for the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>New York<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/><tag name="PERSON" value="start"/> Herald Tribune<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> wrote: "There is beauty in the picture all right, with Miss <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> glowing into the camera from every angle… but the dramatic pretenses are weak, despite the lofty sentences and handsome manikin poses.".
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s fourth period picture, Beau Brummell, made just after Elephant Walk and <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Rhapsody<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, cast her as the elaborately costumed Lady Patricia, which many felt was only a screen prop—a ravishing beauty whose sole purpose was to lend romantic support to the film's title star, Stewart Granger. The Last Time I Saw Paris (1954) fared only slightly better than her previous pictures, with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> being reunited with <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>The Big Hangover<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> costar <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Van Johnson<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. The role of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Helen Ellsworth Willis<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was based on that of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Zelda Fitzgerald<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and, although pregnant with her second child, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> went ahead with the film, her fourth in 12 months. Although proving somewhat successful at the box office, she still yearned for more substantial roles.
Following a more substantial role opposite <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Rock Hudson<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>James Dean<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> in <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>George Stevens<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>' epic <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Giant<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (1956), <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was nominated for an <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Academy Award<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> for Best Actress four years in a row for <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Raintree County<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (1957) opposite <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Montgomery Clift<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>; <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Cat on a Hot Tin Roof<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (1958) opposite<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/> Paul Newman<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>; <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Suddenly, Last Summer<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (1959) with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Montgomery Clift<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Katharine Hepburn<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mercedes McCambridge<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>; and finally winning for <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>BUtterfield 8<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (1960). The film co-starred then husband <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Eddie Fisher<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and ended her contract, which <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> said had made her an "<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>MGM<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> chattel" for 18 years.
<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Suddenly, Last Summer<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>'s success made <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> among the top ten most successful actors at the box office, and she remained in the top ten almost every year for the next decade. In 1960, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> became the highest paid actress up to that time when she signed a $1&#160; million dollar contract to play the title role in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>20th Century Fox<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s lavish production of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Cleopatra<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, which was released in 1963. During the filming, she began a romance with her future husband <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Richard Burton<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, who played Mark Antony in the film. The romance received much attention from the tabloid press, as both were married to other spouses at the time. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> ultimately received $7&#160; million for her role.
Her second <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Academy Award<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, also for Best Actress in a Leading Role, was for her performance as <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Martha<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> in <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Who's Afraid of Virginia Woolf?<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (1966), playing opposite then husband <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Richard Burton<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Burton<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> would appear together in six other films during the decade, among them The V.I.P.s (1963), The <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Sandpiper<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (1965), and <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>The Taming of the Shrew<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (1967). By 1967 their films had earned $200&#160; million at the box office. When <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Burton<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> considered not working for three months, the possibility caused alarm in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Hollywood<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> as "nearly half of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>U.S.<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> film industry's income" came from movies starring one or both of them. Their next films <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Doctor Faustus<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (1967), <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>The Comedians<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (1967) and <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Boom!<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (1968), however, all failed at the box office.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> appeared in John Huston's Reflections in a Golden Eye (1967) opposite Marlon Brando (replacing <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Clift<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, who died before production began) and Secret Ceremony (1968) opposite Mia Farrow. By the end of the decade her box-office drawing power had considerably diminished, as evidenced by the failure of The Only Game in Town (1970), with Warren Beatty.
Although limited by a "thin and inflexible voice", <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> continued to star in numerous theatrical films throughout the 1970s, such as Zee and Co. (1972) with Michael Caine, Ash Wednesday (1973), The Blue Bird (1976) with Jane Fonda and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ava Gardner<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, and A&#160; Little Night Music (1977). With then-husband <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Richard Burton<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, she co-starred in the 1972 films Under Milk Wood and Hammersmith Is Out, and the 1973 made-for-TV movie Divorce His, Divorce Hers.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> starred in the 1980 mystery film The Mirror Crack'd, based on an Agatha Christie novel. In 1985, she played movie gossip columnist Louella Parsons in the TV film Malice in Wonderland opposite Jane Alexander, who played <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hedda Hopper<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> appeared in the miniseries North and South. Her last theatrical film was 1994's The Flintstones. In 2001, she played an agent in the TV film These Old Broads. She appeared on a number of television series, including the soap operas General Hospital and All My Children, as well as the animated series The Simpsons—once as herself, and once as the voice of Maggie Simpson, uttering one word, "Daddy".
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> also acted on the stage, making her Broadway and West End debuts in 1982 with a revival of Lillian Hellman's The Little Foxes. She was then in a production of Noël Coward's Private Lives (1983), in which she starred with her former husband, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Richard Burton<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. The student-run <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Burton<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/><tag name="PERSON" value="start"/> Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> Theatre in Oxford was named for the famous couple after <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Burton<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> appeared as <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Doctor Faustus<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> in the Oxford University Dramatic Society (OUDS) production of the Marlowe play. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> played the ghostly, wordless Helen of Troy, who is entreated by Faustus to "make [him] immortal with a kiss".
In the early 1980s, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> moved to Bel Air, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Los Angeles<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, which was her residence until her death. She also owned homes in Palm Springs, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>London<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and Hawaii.
In March 2003, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> declined to attend the 75th Annual <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Academy Award<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>s, due to her opposition to the Iraq War. She publicly condemned then President George W. Bush for calling on Saddam Hussein to leave Iraq, and said she feared the conflict would lead to "<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>World War II<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>I".
The February 2007 issue of Interview magazine was devoted entirely to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. It celebrated her life, career and her upcoming 75th birthday.
On December 1, 2007, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> acted on-stage again, appearing opposite <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>James Earl Jones<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> in a benefit performance of the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>A. R. Gurney play Love Letters<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. The event's goal was to raise $1&#160; million for <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>AIDS<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> foundation. Tickets for the show were priced at $2, 500, and more than 500 people attended. The event happened to coincide with the 2007 Writers Guild of America strike and, rather than cross the picket line, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> requested a "one night dispensation." The Writers Guild agreed not to picket the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Paramount Pictures<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> lot that night to allow for the performance.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was married eight times to seven husbands. When asked why she married so often, she replied, "I don't know, honey. It sure beats the hell out of me, " but also said that, "I was taught by my parents that if you fall in love, if you want to have a love affair, you get married. I guess I'm very old-fashioned." <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s husbands were:.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> had many romances outside her marriages. Before marrying <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hilton<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> she was engaged to both Heisman Trophy winner <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Glenn Davis<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>—who did not know until the relationship ended that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s mother had encouraged it to build publicity for her daughter—and the son of William D. Pawley, the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>United States<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> Ambassador to <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Brazil<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Howard Hughes<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> promised <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s parents that if they would encourage her to marry him, the enormously wealthy industrialist and film producer would finance a movie studio for her; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sara<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/><tag name="PERSON" value="start"/> Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> agreed, but <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> refused. After she left <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hilton<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/><tag name="PERSON" value="start"/> Hughes<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> returned, proposing to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> by suddenly landing a helicopter nearby and sprinkling diamonds on her. Other dates included <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Frank Sinatra<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Henry Kissinger<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Malcolm Forbes<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. In 2007, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> denied rumors of a ninth marriage to her partner <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Jason Winters<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, but referred to him as "one of the most wonderful men I've ever known.".
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> had two sons, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Michael Howard<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (born January 6, 1953) and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Christopher Edward<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (born February 27, 1955), with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Michael Wilding<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. She had a daughter, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Elizabeth Frances "Liza"<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (born August 6, 1957), with<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/> Michael Todd<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. During her marriage to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Eddie Fisher<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> started proceedings to adopt a two-year-old girl from <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Germany<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Maria<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (born August 1, 1961); the adoption process was finalized in 1964 following their divorce. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Richard Burton<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> later adopted <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s daughters Liza and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Maria<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
In 1971, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> became a grandmother at the age of 39. At the time of her death, she was survived by her four children, ten grandchildren, and four great-grandchildren.
In 1959, at age 27, after nine months of study, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> converted from <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Christian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> Science to <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Judaism<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, taking the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Hebrew<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> name <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Elisheba Rachel<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. She stated that her conversion was something she had long considered and was not related to her marriages. After <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mike Todd<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s death, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> said that she "felt a desperate need for a formalized religion, " and explained that neither <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Catholicism<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> nor <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Christian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> Science were able to address many of the "questions she had about life and death.":175.
Biographer <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Randy Taraborrelli<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> notes that after studying the philosophy of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Judaism<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> for nine months, "she felt an immediate connection to the faith.":176 Although <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> rarely attended synagogue, she stated, "I'm one of those people who think you can be close to <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>God<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> anywhere, not just in a place designed for worship... ":176 At the conversion ceremony, with her parents present as witnesses and in full support of her decision, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> repeated the words of Ruth:.
... for whither thou goest, I will go; and where thou lodgest, I will lodge; thy people shall be my people and thy <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>God<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> my <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>God<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>.:176.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was a follower of Kabbalah and a member of the Kabbalah Centre.
During an interview when she was 55, she describes how her inner sense of identity, when a child actress, kept her from giving in to many of the studio's demands, especially with regard to altering her appearance to fit in:.
She adds that she began to recognize her "inner being" during her adulthood:.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> had a passion for jewelry, stating that "You can't cry on a diamond's shoulder, and diamonds won't keep you warm at night, but they're sure fun when the sun shines". At her death, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s jewelry collection was reportedly worth $150&#160; million. She was a client of jewelry designer Shlomo Moussaieff. Over the years she owned a number of well-known pieces, two of the most famous being the 33.19-carat (6.64&#160; g) Krupp Diamond, which <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> wore daily, and the 69.42-carat (13.88&#160; g) pear-shaped <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>-<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Burton<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> Diamond; both were among many gifts from husband <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Richard Burton<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> also owned the 50-carat (10&#160; g) La Peregrina Pearl, purchased by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Burton<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> as a Valentine's Day present in 1969. The pearl was formerly owned by Mary I of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>England<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Burton<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> sought a portrait of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Queen Mary<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> wearing the pearl. Upon the purchase of such a painting, the <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Burton<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>s discovered that the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>British<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> National Portrait Gallery did not have an original painting of Mary, so they donated the painting to the Gallery. Her enduring collection of jewelry has been documented in her book <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>My Love Affair with Jewelry<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (2002) with photographs by the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>New York<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> photographer John Bigelow <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
At her death <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> left an estate estimated at $600&#160; million to $1&#160; billion; beyond the $150&#160; million in jewelry, she owned $130&#160; million in real estate. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was a pioneer in marketing a celebrity merchandise brand, and despite her years as an actress, most of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s wealth came from her business ventures. She designed fine jewelry for The <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Elizabeth<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> Collection, and launched three perfumes, "White Diamonds", "Passion", and "Passion for Men", which together had an estimated US$69&#160; million in 2010 sales.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was a fashion icon during her years as an active film star. In addition to her own purchases, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>MGM<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> costumers <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Edith Head<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Helen Rose<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> helped <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> choose clothes that emphasized her face, chest, and waist. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> helped popularize <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Valentino<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Halston<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s designs, and in the 1980s <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Schering-Plough<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> developed violet contact lenses, citing <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s eyes as inspiration.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> devoted consistent and generous humanitarian time, advocacy efforts, and funding to <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>HIV<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> and <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>AIDS<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>-related projects and charities, helping to raise more than $270&#160; million for the cause. She was one of the first celebrities and public personalities to do so at a time when few acknowledged the disease, organizing and hosting the first <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>AIDS<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> fundraiser in 1984, to benefit <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>AIDS<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> Project <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Los Angeles<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was cofounder of the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>American<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> Foundation for <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>AIDS<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> Research (amfAR) with Dr. Michael Gottlieb and Dr. Mathilde Krim in 1985. Her longtime friend and former co-star <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Rock Hudson<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> had disclosed having <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>AIDS<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> and died of it that year. She also founded the <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Elizabeth<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/><tag name="PERSON" value="start"/> Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/><tag name="MISC" value="start"/> AIDS<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> Foundation (ETAF) in 1993, created to provide critically needed support services for people with <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>HIV<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>/<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>AIDS<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. For example, in 2006 <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> commissioned a 37-foot (11&#160; m) "Care Van" equipped with examination tables and xray equipment, the New Orleans donation made by her <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Elizabeth<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/><tag name="PERSON" value="start"/> Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/><tag name="MISC" value="start"/> AIDS<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> Foundation and Macy's. That year, in the wake of Hurricane Katrina, she also donated US$40, 000 to the NO/<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>AIDS<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> Task Force, a non-profit organization serving the community of those affected by <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>HIV<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>/<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>AIDS<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> in and around New Orleans.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was honored with a special <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Academy Award<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Jean Hersholt Humanitarian Award<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, in 1992 for her <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>HIV<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>/<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>AIDS<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> humanitarian work. Speaking of that work, former President <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bill<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/><tag name="PERSON" value="start"/> Clinton<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> said at her death, "<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Elizabeth<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s legacy will live on in many people around the world whose lives will be longer and better because of her work and the ongoing efforts of those she inspired.".
After her conversion to <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Judaism<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> worked for <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Jewish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> causes throughout her life. In 1959, her large-scale purchase of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Israeli Bonds<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> caused <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Arab<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> boycotts of her films. In 1962, she was barred from entering <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> to complete <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Cleopatra<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>; its government announced that "that Miss <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> will not be allowed to come to <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> because she has adopted the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Jewish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> faith and 'supports <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Israeli<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> causes.'" In 1974, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Richard Burton<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> considered marrying in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, but could not because <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Burton<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was not <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Jewish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> helped to raise money for organizations such as the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Jewish National Fund<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>; advocated for the right of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Soviet<tag name="MISC" value="end"/><tag name="MISC" value="start"/> Jews<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> to emigate to <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and canceled a visit to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>USSR<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> because of its condemnation of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> due to the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Six-Day War<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>; signed a letter protesting the United Nations General Assembly Resolution 3379 of 1975; and offered herself as a replacement hostage during the 1976 Entebbe skyjacking.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> struggled with health problems much of her life; starting with her divorce from <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hilton<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> experienced serious medical issues whenever she faced problems in her personal life. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was hospitalized more than 70 times and had at least 20 major operations. Many times newspaper headlines erroneously announced that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was close to death; she herself only claimed to have almost died on four occasions.
At 5'4", <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> constantly gained and lost significant amounts of weight, reaching both 119 pounds and 180 pounds in the 1980s. She smoked cigarettes into her mid-fifties, and feared she had lung cancer in October 1975 after an X-ray showed spots on her lungs, but was later found not to have the disease. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> broke her back five times, had both her hips replaced, had a hysterectomy, suffered from dysentery and phlebitis, punctured her esophagus, survived a benign brain tumor operation in 1997 and skin cancer, and faced life-threatening bouts with pneumonia twice, one in 1961 requiring an emergency tracheotomy. In 1983 she admitted to having been addicted to sleeping pills and painkillers for 35 years. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was treated for alcoholism and prescription drug addiction at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Betty Ford Clinic<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> for seven weeks from December 1983 to January 1984, and again from the autumn of 1988 until early 1989.
On May 30, 2006, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> appeared on Larry King Live to refute the claims that she had been ill, and denied the allegations that she was suffering from Alzheimer's disease and was close to death. Near the end of her life, however, she was reclusive and sometimes failed to make scheduled appearances due to illness or other personal reasons. She used a wheelchair and when asked about it stated that she had osteoporosis and was born with scoliosis.
The mutation that gave <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> her striking double eyelashes may also have contributed to her history of heart trouble. In November 2004, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> announced a diagnosis of congestive heart failure, a progressive condition in which the heart is too weak to pump sufficient blood throughout the body, particularly to the lower extremities such as the ankles and feet. In 2009 she underwent cardiac surgery to replace a leaky valve. In February 2011, new symptoms related to heart failure caused her to be admitted into Cedars-Sinai Medical Center in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Los Angeles<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> for treatment, where she remained until her death at age 79 on March 23, 2011, surrounded by her four children.
She was buried in a private <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Jewish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> ceremony, presided over by Rabbi Jerry Cutler, the day after she died, at Forest Lawn Memorial Park in Glendale, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>California<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> is entombed in the Great Mausoleum, where public access to her tomb is restricted. At her request, the funeral began 15 minutes after it was scheduled to begin; as her representative told the media "She even wanted to be late for her own funeral.".
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> has been called the "greatest movie star of all, " writes biographer William J. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mann<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.:2 A child star at the age of 12, she soon after launched into public awareness by <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>MGM<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and a string of successful films, many of which are today considered "classics." Her resulting celebrity made her into a <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Hollywood<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> icon, as she set the "gold standard" for <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Hollywood<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> fame, and "created the model for stardom, " adds <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mann<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.:3.
Other observers, such as social critic <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Camille Paglia<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, similarly describe <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> as "the greatest actress in film history, " partly as a result of the "liquid realm of emotion" she expressed on screen. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Paglia<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> describes the effect <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> had in some of her films:.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> had a major role in sparking the sexual revolution of the 1960s, as she pushed the envelope on sexuality: She was one of the first major stars to pose (mostly) nude in <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Playboy<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, and among the first to remove her clothes onscreen.:5 In <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>A Place in the Sun<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, filmed when she was 17, her surprising maturity shocked <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Hollywood<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> columnist <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hedda Hopper<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, who wrote of her precocious sexuality. Film historian <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Andrew Sarris<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> describes her love scenes in the film with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Montgomery Clift<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> as "unnerving—sybaritic—like gorging on chocolate sundaes.":6.
In real life, she was considered "a star without airs, " notes <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mann<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. Writer <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Gloria Steinem<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> likewise described her as a "movie queen with no ego... expert at what she does, uncatty in her work relationships with other actresses.":7 <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mike Nichols<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, who directed her in <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Who's Afraid of Virginia Woolf?<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (1966), said that of all the actors he’s worked with, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> had the "most democratic soul." <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mann<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> adds that she treated electricians and studio crew the "same way she would a Rothschild at a charity gala.":6 Director <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>George Cukor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> told <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> that she possessed "that rarest of virtues—simple kindness.":7.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> won two <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Academy Award<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>s for Best Actress for her performance in <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>BUtterfield 8<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> in 1960, and for <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Who's Afraid of Virginia Woolf?<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> in 1966. Additionally, she received the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Jean Herscholt Humanitarian Academy Award<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> in 1992 for her work fighting <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>AIDS<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>.
In 1997, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was honored by the Screen Actors Guild (SAG) with the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Life Achievement Award<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. As <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> could not be in attendance, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Gregory Peck<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> read the following statement on her behalf:.
As we all know, ours was one of the first industries to be directly and dramatically affected by the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>AIDS<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> epidemic. And it’s heartening to me that this community has risen to the challenge. And the foundation of the Screen Actors Guild, of which I’m so proud to be a member, is no exception having made a very generous donation to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Elizabeth Taylor AIDS Foundation<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. Thank you all for honoring me tonight.
Love, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Elizabeth<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> received the French <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Legion of Honour<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> in 1987, and in 2000 was named a Dame Commander of the Order of the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>British<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> Empire. In 2001, she received a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Presidential Citizens Medal<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> for her humanitarian work, most notably for helping to raise more than $200&#160; million for <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>AIDS<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> research and bringing international attention and resources to addressing the epidemic. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was inducted into the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>California<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> Hall of Fame in 2007.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was the subject of at least 53 books as of 2006; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Kitty Kelley<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> wrote the first unauthorized biography of the actress in 1981, which <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> denounced. She never wrote a comprehensive autobiography due to her desire for privacy, but did publish several books besides <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>My Love Affair with Jewelry<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s first, <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Nibbles and Me<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (1946), discussed the child star's "adventures with her pet chipmunk". Reviewers criticized another, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Elizabeth Taylor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (1964), for being uninteresting and lacking in new information. She received a $750, 000 advance payment for <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Elizabeth Takes Off: On Weight Gain, Weight Loss, Self-Image and Self-Esteem<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (1988).
&#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; .
&#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; .
Y. Frank Freeman (1956)&#160; · .
 .
 .
&#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; .
&#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; .
&#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; .
&#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; .
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>John Ford<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (1973)&#160; · .
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Charlie Chaplin<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (1972)&#160; · .
 .
 .
