<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Peter Bercovitch<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>September 17, 1879<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>  <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>December 26, 1942<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) was a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Canadian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> provincial and federal politician.
Born in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Montreal<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Quebec<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, the son of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hyam Bercovitch<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Fannie Goldberg<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, he received a Bachelor of Civil Law from <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>McGill University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and a Master of Laws from the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Université de Montréal<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. He was called to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Quebec Bar in<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1901<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and was created a <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>King's Counsel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1911<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. He pracised law in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Montreal<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and became a senior partner of the law firm <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Bercovitch<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Cohen<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and Spector.
He was elected to the<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/> Legislative Assembly of Quebec<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> representing the riding of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Montréal-Saint-Louis<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1916<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Quebec<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> election. A Liberal, he was re-elected in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1919<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> (by acclamation), <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1923<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1927<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1931<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1935<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> (by acclamation), and <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1936<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. He resigned in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1938<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and was acclaimed to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Canadian House of Commons<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> representing the riding of Cartier in a <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1938<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> by-election. A Liberal, he was re-elected in the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1940<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> federal election. He died in office in late <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1942<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
