<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lech Aleksander KaczyDski<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>(<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Polish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>pronunciation:&#160; &#160; ; <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>18 June 1949<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>  <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>10 April 2010<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) was the President of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Poland<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2005<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> until his sudden death in 2010, and a politician of the party <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Prawo i Sprawiedliwo[<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>(<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Law and Justice<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>PiS<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>). <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>KaczyDski<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>served as Mayor of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Warsaw<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>from 2002 until 22 December 2005, the day before his presidential inauguration. He was the identical twin brother of the former Prime Minister of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Poland<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>and current Chairman of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Law and Justice party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>JarosBaw KaczyDski<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. On 10 April 2010, he died in the crash of a <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Polish Air Force<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/><tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Tu-154<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>while attempting to land at <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Smolensk-North airport<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Russia<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lech KaczyDski<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>was a graduate of law and administration of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Warsaw University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. In 1980 he was awarded his PhD by <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>GdaDsk University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. In 1990 he completed his habilitation in labour and employment law. He later assumed professorial positions at <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>GdaDsk University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Cardinal Stefan WyszyDski University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Warsaw<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.
In the 1970s <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>KaczyDski<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>was an activist in the pro-democratic anti-<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Communist<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>movement in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Poland<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Workers' Defence Committee<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, as well as the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Independent Trade Union<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>movement. In August 1980, he became an adviser to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Inter-Enterprise Strike Committee<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>in the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>GdaDsk Shipyard<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>and the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Solidarity<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>movement. After the communists imposed martial law in December 1981, he was interned as an anti-socialist element. After his release, he returned to trade union activities, becoming a member of the underground <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Solidarity<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
When <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Solidarity<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>was legalized again in the late 1980s, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>KaczyDski<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>was an active adviser to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lech WaBsa<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>and his <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Komitet Obywatelski Solidarno[<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>in 1988. From February to April 1989, he participated in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Round Table<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>talks.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>KaczyDski<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>was elected senator in the elections of June 1989, and became the vice-chairman of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Solidarity<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>trade union. In the 1991 parliamentary election, he was elected to the parliament as a non-party member. He was, however, supported by the electoral committee <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Center Civic Alliance<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, closely related but not identical to the political party <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Centre Agreement<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>(<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Porozumienie Centrum<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>) led by his brother. He was also the main adviser and supporter of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lech WaBsa<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>when the latter was elected President of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Poland<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>in December 1990. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>WaBsa<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>nominated <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>KaczyDski<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>to be the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Security Minister<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Presidential Chancellery<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>but fired him in 1992 during to a conflict concerning <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Jan Olszewski<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s government.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>KaczyDski<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>was the President of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Supreme Chamber of Control<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>(<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Najwy|sza Izba Kontroli<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>NIK<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>) from February 1992 to May 1995 and later <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Minister of Justice<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Attorney General<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>in <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Jerzy Buzek<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s government from June 2000 until his dismissal in July 2001. During this time he was very popular because of his strong stance against corruption.
In 2001 he founded the political party <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Law and Justice<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>(<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Prawo i Sprawiedliwo[<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>PiS<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>), usually labelled 'conservative' by media, with his brother <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>JarosBaw<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lech KaczyDski<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>was the president of the party between 2001 and 2003. His brother <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Jaroslaw<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>is its current chairman.
In 2002, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>KaczyDski<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>was elected mayor of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Warsaw<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>in a landslide victory. He started his term in office by declaring a war on corruption. He strongly supported the construction of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Museum of the Warsaw Uprising<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>and in 2004 appointed a historical panel to estimate material losses that were inflicted upon the city by the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Germans<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>in the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Second World War<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>(an estimated 85% of the city was destroyed in the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Warsaw Uprising<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>) as a direct response to heightened claims coming from <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>German<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>expellees from <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Poland<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. The panel estimated the losses to be at least 45.3&#160; billion euros ($54&#160; billion) in current value. He also promoted construction of the museum of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Polish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/><tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Jews<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Warsaw<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>by donating city land to the project.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>KaczyDski<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>twice banned the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Warsaw<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>gay pride parade in 2004 and again in 2005, locally known as the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Parada Rýwno[ci<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>(the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Equality Parade<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>), stating that the application of the parade organizers had not been properly filed, also saying that he did not respect homosexuals' right to demonstrate stating "I respect your right to demonstrate as citizens. But not as homosexuals. Additionally, he feared the parade would promote a "homosexual lifestyle" and complained that police did not use enough force in breaking it up by stating Why was force not used to break up an illegal demonstration?. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Kaczynski<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> referred to the organizers of the gay pride parades as "perverts". In 2004 his opponents called his actions unconstitutional and he was repeatedly criticised by the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Mazowieckie Voivodeship<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> administration, which officially supervises the Mayor of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Warsaw<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. In 2005, he allowed a counter-demonstration, the "<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Parade of Normality<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.".
In 2007, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Poland<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, represented by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>KaczyDski<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, was found guilty by the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>European Court of Human Rights<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>of violating the principle of freedom of assembly under Article 11 of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>European Convention on Human Rights<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
On 19 March 2005, he formally declared his intention to run for president in the October 2005 election. Elected President of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Republic of Poland<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>in defeating the runner up <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Donald Tusk<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, by polling 54.04 percent of the vote, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>KaczyDski<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>assumed office on 23 December 2005 by taking an oath before the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>National Assembly<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
In his first public speech as president-elect, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>KaczyDski<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>said that his presidency would pursue the task of ameliorating the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Republic<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, a process which he said would consist of "purging various pathologies from our life, most prominently crime (...), particularly criminal corruption  that entire, great rush to obtain unjust enrichment, a rush that is poisoning society, [and preventing the state from ensuring] elementary social security, health security, basic conditions for the development of the family [and] the security of commerce and the basic conditions for economic development.
During his inauguration he stated several goals he would pursue during his presidency. Among those concerning internal affairs were: increasing social solidarity in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Poland<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, bringing justice to those who were responsible for, or were affected by communist crimes in the People's <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Republic of Poland<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, fighting corruption, providing security in economy, and safety for development of family. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>KaczyDski<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>also stated that he would seek to abolish economic inequalities between various regions of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Poland<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. In his speech he also emphasized combining modernisation with tradition and remembering the teachings of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Pope John Paul II<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
On 21 December 2008, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>KaczyDski<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>became the first <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Polish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>head of state to visit a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Polish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>synagogue and to attend religious services held there. His attendance coincided with the first night of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Hanukkah<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>KaczyDski<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>memorialized many of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Poland<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>s national heroes known as cursed soldiers who perished at the hands of the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Polish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>secret police, the Soviet NKVD, the SMERSH, and other repressive organs of communist rule. Such national heroes as Witold Pilecki, August Fieldorf, and many others, were posthumously rehabilitated and bestowed with Polands highest decorations for valor.
From 20052007, in accordance article 133 of the Constitution of the Republic of Poland, KaczyDski pardoned 77 people and declined to pardon 550.
In foreign affairs, KaczyDski noted that many of Poland's problems were related to the lack of energy security and this issue would have to be resolved in order to protect Polish interests. Strengthening ties with the United States while continuing to develop relations within the European Union are two main goals of Polish foreign affairs, as well as improving relations with France and Germany despite several problems in relations with the latter. Aside from those issues, his immediate goals were to develop tangible strategic partnership with Ukraine and greater cooperation with the Baltic states and Georgia. He was greatly admired in Israel, because he promoted educating Polish youth about the Holocaust. There was widespread grief in Israel over his death.
Defense Minister RadosBaw Sikorski compared the planned Russia to Germany gas pipeline to the Ribbentrop-Molotov Pact and Foreign Minister Anna Fotyga stated that the pipeline was a threat to Poland's energy security.
In November 2006 in Helsinki, at a European UnionRussia meeting, Poland vetoed the launch of EU-Russia partnership talks due to a Russian ban on Polish meat and plant products imports.
As a reaction to claims by a German exile group Preussische Treuhand, which represents post-1945 German expellees from Eastern Europe, the Polish Foreign Minister Fotyga mistakenly threatened to reopen a 1990 Treaty fixing the Oder and Neisse rivers as the border between the two countries instead of the Neighborhood Treaty signed in the same year.
Following the military conflict between Russia and Georgia in 2008, KaczyDski provided the website of the President of Poland for dissemination of information for blocked by the Russian Federation Georgian internet portals.
During a state visit to Serbia in 2009, KaczyDski said that the Polish government, on the basis of its constitutional competences, decided to recognize Kosovo and emphasized that he, as the President of the state, did not agree with that.
KaczyDski married economist Maria KaczyDska in 1978. They had one daughter, Marta KaczyDska-Dubieniecka, and two granddaughters named Ewa and Martyna. His brother is JarosBaw KaczyDski, the former Prime Minister of Poland.
On 10 April 2010, a Tupolev Tu-154M plane was carrying Lech KaczyDski, his wife Maria KaczyDska, and other members of a Polish delegation (top public and military figures of Polish state) from Warsaw to commemorate the Katyn massacre. The plane crashed while approaching Smolensk Air Base in Russia. The governor of Smolensk Oblast confirmed to Russia 24 news channel that there were no survivors of the crash. 96 people were killed in the crash, including many of Poland's highest military and civilian leaders.
Russian President Dmitry Medvedev ordered a government commission to investigate the crash. Russia's Prime Minister, Vladimir Putin, was placed in charge of the investigation.
On 11 April 2010, President Kaczynski's body was returned to Poland, where he and his wife lay in state at the Presidential Palace in Warsaw. The state funeral was held in Krakýw on 18 April 2010. After a Roman Catholic mass at St. Mary's Basilica, the presidential couple were laid to rest in a sarcophagus, placed in the antechamber to Jýzef PiBsudski's crypt beneath the Wawel Cathedral, the resting place of several Polish kings and national heroes. A significant number of foreign dignitaries were unable to attend the funeral, after initially planning to come, as a result of the widespread cancellation of air travel in Europe following the eruption of the volcano Eyjafjallajýkull in Iceland.
First Polish Republic.
Ignacy Wyssogota Zakrzewski&#160; | Jýzef MichaB Aukasiewicz&#160; | Andrzej RafaBowicz&#160; | Ignacy Wyssogota Zakrzewski&#160; | Jýzef MichaB Aukasiewicz and Andrzej RafaBowicz.
Prussian Occupation.
Franz Schimmelpfennig von der Ove&#160; | Friedrich Georg Tilly.
Duchy of Warsaw.
Joachim MoszyDski&#160; | PaweB BieliDski&#160; | StanisBaw Wgrzecki.
Congress Poland.
Karol Woyda&#160; | StanisBaw Wgrzecki&#160; | Jakub Ignacy AaszczyDski&#160; | Aleksander Graybner&#160; | Teodor Andrault de Langeron&#160; | Kazimierz Woyda&#160; | Zygmunt Wielopolski&#160; | Kalikst Witkowski&#160; | Sokrates Starynkiewicz&#160; | MikoBaj Bibikow&#160; | Wiktor LitwiDski&#160; | Aleksander Miller.
World War I.
ZdzisBaw Lubomirski&#160; | Piotr Drzewiecki.
Second Polish Republic.
StanisBaw Nowodworski&#160; | WBadysBaw JabBoDski&#160; | Zygmunt SBomiDski&#160; | Marian Zyndram-Ko[ciaBkowski&#160; | Stefan StarzyDski.
General Government.
Julian Kulski&#160; | Marceli Porowski&#160; | Helmut Otto&#160; | Oskar Rudolf Dengel&#160; | Ludwig Leist.
People's Republic of Poland.
Marian Spychalski&#160; | StanisBaw ToBwiDski&#160; | Jerzy Albrecht&#160; | Janusz Zarzycki&#160; | Zygmunt Dworakowski&#160; | Janusz Zarzycki.
Jerzy Majewski&#160; | MieczysBaw Dbicki&#160; | Jerzy BolesBawski.
Third Polish Republic.
StanisBaw Wyganowski&#160; | MieczysBaw Bareja&#160; | Marcin Zwicicki&#160; | PaweB Piskorski&#160; | Wojciech Kozak&#160; | Lech KaczyDski&#160; | MirosBaw Kochalski (acting)&#160; | Kazimierz Marcinkiewicz (acting)&#160; | Hanna Gronkiewicz-Waltz.
