<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Michel Loève<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>January 22, 1907<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> – <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>February 17, 1979<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) was a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>French<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>American<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> probabilist and a mathematical statistician, of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Palestinian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Jewish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> origin. His name is known to probabilists and statisticians because of the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Karhunen–Loève theorem<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> and <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Karhunen–Loève transform<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Michel Loève<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was born in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Jaffa<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Palestine<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1907<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, during the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Ottoman<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> domination there, in a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Jewish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> family. Passed most of the childhood's years in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and received there his primary and secondary education in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>French<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> schools. Later, after achieving the grades of B.L. in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1931<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and A.B. in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1936<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he studied mathematics at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Université de Paris<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> under <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Paul Lévy<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. and received his Docteur ès Sciences (Mathématiques) in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1941<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1936<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> was employed as actuaire of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Lyon<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
Because of his <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Jewish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> origin, he was arrested during the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>German<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> occupation of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>France<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and sent to <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Drancy internment camp<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. Having survived the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Holocaust<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, after the liberation became between <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1944<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>–<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1946<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> chief of researches at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Institut Henri Poincaré<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> at <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Paris University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, then until <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1948<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> worked at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of London<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
After one term as a visiting professor at <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Columbia University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> he accepted the position of Professor of Mathematics at <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Berkeley<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1955<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> adding the title Professor of Statistics.
He is the author of one of the best known textbooks on measure-theoretic probability theory. He is memorialized via the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Loève Prize <tag name="MISC" value="end"/>created by his widow Line.
