<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lê éc Anh<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (born <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1 December 1920<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) is <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Vietnamese<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> general and politician. He was president from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1992<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> until <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1997<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> after leading the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Vietnamese<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> forces in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Cambodia<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> throughout the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1980<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>s. He was regarded as a conservative who advocated maintaining tight party control over domestic policies. He was born in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Phú LÙc District<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Thëa Thiên-Hu¿ Province<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Anh<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> led <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Vietcong combat<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> units during the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Vietnam War<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>.
As a general <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Anh<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was the commander of the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Vietnamese<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> forces in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>People's Republic of Kampuchea<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1980<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>s. He formulated five key points for the defence of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Cambodia<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> against <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Khmer Rouge<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> re-infiltration and was the architect of the unpopular K5 Plan.
Later he entered politics and he held a succession of government posts. During his time as Defence Minister General he was already a major conservative voice in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Vietnam<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s political system. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1989<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, after the collapse of communism in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Eastern Europe<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, he warned about the threat of the West undermining <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Vietnam's Communist Party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, arguing for more army involvement in politics "at a time when <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Vietnamese<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> socialism was under attack".
From <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1991<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> (to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1993<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Anh<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> controlled <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Vietnamese<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> policy towards <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Cambodia<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>China<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> at the expense of foreign minister <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>NguyÅn C¡ Th¡ch<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and therefore was involved in the normalisation of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Vietnam<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s relations with <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>China<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>November 1991<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. He was the first <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Vietnamese<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> president to visit <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Beijing<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in 38 years since an official visit in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>November 1993<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to discuss economic relations and territorial disputes in the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>South China Sea<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>; however, consensus was achieved only on the former issue.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>September 1992<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> he was elected to the new post of state president, replacing a collective presidency. Although a mostly symbolic position, the presidency became much more important during his tenure.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Anh<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> is considered by many to have been (ideologically) the most conservative among the three political leaders during his tenure. Prime Minister <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Võ Vn KiÇt<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was associated with the reform camp and therefore often disagreed with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Anh<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. Secretary-General of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Communist Party of Vietnam<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>× M°Ýi<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was ideologically more flexible and effectively came to be seen as representing the middle ground between <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Anh<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>KiÇt<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, but seems to have tended towards conservative positions.
His opposition to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>KiÇt<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s reform ambitions are part of a long-lasting rivalry. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1991<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Anh<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> joined <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>× M°Ýi<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> to support him in his candidacy for party leadership against <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Võ Vn KiÇt<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. The <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>KiÇt<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> camp later spread rumours about wrongdoings <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Anh<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was said to be involved in in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Cambodia<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.
In mid-<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>November 1996<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he was hospitalized after a major stroke. This was at a time when the reform camp that he opposed was in decline and for some time his illness seemed to change the dynamics within the political leadership, weakening the conservative camp and reinvigorating the reform camp. However, Party leader <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>× M°Ýi<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> led a counter-attack against the reform camp, warning of the dangers of the 'current market economy'. The conservative camp gained further momentum when <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Anh<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> surprisingly recovered in April 1997. He stepped down as president in September 1997 after the Communist Party Congress and was replaced by Tr§n éc L°¡ng. He was an Advisor of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Party's Central Committee<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>December 1997<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>-<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2001<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
.
