<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ian MacIntosh Black<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (born <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>27 June 1941<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) is a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Scottish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> former swimmer. He was <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>BBC Sports Personality of the Year<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1958<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> at the age of only seventeen and is still to this date the youngest winner of the award. He achieved this phenomenal feat by winning gold medals in three separate events at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>European Championships<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Budapest<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, competing as an adult.
In the same year he also won gold and silver medals for <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Scotland<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> at the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1958<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>British Empire and Commonwealth Games<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Cardiff<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>; gold in the 220 yards butterfly, silver in the 440 yards freestyle and silver in the 4×220 yards freestyle relay.
He holds certain age-related <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>British<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> records to this day.
When competing for <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Great Britain<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, he would proudly display his <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Scottish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> identity by wearing a <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>MacGregor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> tartan dressing gown poolside. As well as excelling in the water, he was also a formidable rugby union player.
He is a member of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Scottish Sports Hall of Fame<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
In the late <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>70<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>s he became Headteacher of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Seafield Primary School<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Elgin<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. He taught in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Canada<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and he became headmaster of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>St Christopher's prep school<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Bahrain<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. In the early <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1980<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>s he was headmaster of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Sek Kong Primary School<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Kong Kong<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> before moving to <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Aberlour House school<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1987<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>-<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>89<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. He later returned to his former school, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Robert Gordon's College<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Aberdeen<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, as headmaster of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Junior School<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, and retired in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2004<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
He is notable for his extreme modesty concerning his sporting accomplishments. He is married and he has four children. He is a member of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Church of Scotland<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. His uncle served in the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Great War<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> and was killed on the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Western Front<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. His ancestors lived in the very north of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Scotland<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> near <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>John O'Groats<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. They changed their name to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Black<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> for their hair colour because their previous surname <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>MacGregor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was associated with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Rob Roy MacGregor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ian Black<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> attended <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Aberdeen University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> where he was awarded an M.A. and a Certificate in Education.
.
