<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Stanisław Zaremba<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>October 3, 1863<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> – <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>November 23, 1942<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) was a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Polish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> mathematician. His research in differential equations, applied mathematics, classical analysis, particularly on harmonic analysis, was widely recognized. He was a mathematician who contributed to the success of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Polish School of Mathematics<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> through his teaching and organizational skills as well as through his research. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Zaremba<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> wrote a number of university textbooks and monographies.
He was a professor of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Jagiellonian University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (since <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1900<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>), member of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Academy of Learning<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (since <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1903<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>), co-founder and president of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Polish Mathematical Society<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1919<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>).
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Zaremba<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was born on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>October 3, 1863<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Romanówka<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Ukraine<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and was first educated as an engineer. He went to <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Paris<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> for graduate school and received his degree from the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Sorbonne<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1889<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. He stayed in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>France<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> until <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1900<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, when he joined the faculty at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Jagiellonian University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Kraków<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. His years in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>France<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> enabled him to establish a strong bridge between <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Polish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> mathematicians and those in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>France<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.
He died on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>November 23, 1942<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Kraków<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, during the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>German<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> occupation of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Poland<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
.
