<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Wilhelm Conrad Röntgen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>German<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> pronunciation: ; <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>27 March 1845<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>&#160; – <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>10 February 1923<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) was a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>German<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> physicist, who, on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>8 November 1895<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, produced and detected electromagnetic radiation in a wavelength range today known as X-rays or <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Röntgen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> rays, an achievement that earned him the first <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Nobel Prize<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> in Physics in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1901<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.:1.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Röntgen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was born in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Lennep<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Germany<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> as the only child of a merchant and manufacturer of cloth. His mother was <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Charlotte Constanze Frowein<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Amsterdam<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>March 1848<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, the family moved to <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Apeldoorn<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Wilhelm<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was raised in the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Netherlands<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. He received his early education at the boarding school, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Institute of Martinus Herman van Doorn<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Apeldoorn<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. From <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1861<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1863<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he attended the ambachtsschool in Utrecht. He was expelled for refusing to reveal the identity of a classmate guilty of drawing an unflattering portrait of one of the school's teachers. Not only was he expelled, he subsequently found that he could not gain admittance into any other <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Dutch<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> or <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>German<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> gymnasium.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1865<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he tried to attend the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Utrecht<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> without having the necessary credentials required for a regular student. Upon hearing that he could enter the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Federal Polytechnic Institute<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Zurich<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> (today known as the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>ETH Zurich<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>), he passed its examinations, and began studies there as a student of mechanical engineering. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1869<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he graduated with a Ph.D. from the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Zurich<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>; once there, he became a favorite student of Professor <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>August Kundt<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, whom he followed to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Strassburg<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1873<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1874<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Röntgen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> became a lecturer at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Strassburg<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1875<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> he became a professor at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Academy of Agriculture<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> at <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Hohenheim<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Württemberg<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. He returned to <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Strassburg<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> as a professor of physics in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1876<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, and in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1879<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he was appointed to the chair of physics at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Giessen<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1888<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he obtained the physics chair at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Würzburg<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, and in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1900<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Munich<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, by special request of the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Bavarian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> government. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Röntgen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> had family in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Iowa<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>United States<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and at one time planned to emigrate. Although he accepted an appointment at <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Columbia University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>New York City<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and had actually purchased transatlantic tickets, the outbreak of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>World War I<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> changed his plans and he remained in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Munich<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> for the rest of his career.
.
During <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1895<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Röntgen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was investigating the external effects from the various types of vacuum tube equipment — apparatuses from <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Heinrich Hertz<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Johann Hittorf<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>William Crookes<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Nikola Tesla<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Philipp von Lenard<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> — when an electrical discharge is passed through them.[7] In early <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>November<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he was repeating an experiment with one of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lenard<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s tubes in which a thin aluminium window had been added to permit the cathode rays to exit the tube but a cardboard covering was added to protect the aluminium from damage by the strong electrostatic field that is necessary to produce the cathode rays. He knew the cardboard covering prevented light from escaping, yet <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Röntgen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> observed that the invisible cathode rays caused a fluorescent effect on a small cardboard screen painted with barium platinocyanide when it was placed close to the aluminium window. It occurred to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Röntgen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> that the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Hittorf-Crookes tube<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, which had a much thicker glass wall than the <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lenard<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> tube, might also cause this fluorescent effect.
In the late afternoon of <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>8 November 1895<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Röntgen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> determined to test his idea. He carefully constructed a black cardboard covering similar to the one he had used on the <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lenard<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> tube. He covered the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Hittorf-Crookes tube<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> with the cardboard and attached electrodes to a <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ruhmkorff<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> coil to generate an electrostatic charge. Before setting up the barium platinocyanide screen to test his idea, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Röntgen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> darkened the room to test the opacity of his cardboard cover. As he passed the <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ruhmkorff<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> coil charge through the tube, he determined that the cover was light-tight and turned to prepare the next step of the experiment. It was at this point that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Röntgen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> noticed a faint shimmering from a bench a meter away from the tube. To be sure, he tried several more discharges and saw the same shimmering each time. Striking a match, he discovered the shimmering had come from the location of the barium platinocyanide screen he had been intending to use next.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Röntgen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> speculated that a new kind of ray might be responsible. <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>8 November<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> was a Friday, so he took advantage of the weekend to repeat his experiments and make his first notes. In the following weeks he ate and slept in his laboratory as he investigated many properties of the new rays he temporarily termed "X-rays", using the mathematical designation for something unknown. Although the new rays would eventually come to bear his name in many languages as "<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Röntgen Rays<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>" (and the associated X-ray radiograms as "<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Röntgenograms<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>"), he always preferred the term X-rays ("X-ray" overtook "<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Röntgenogram<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>" in popular usage by the year <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1980<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.).
Nearly two weeks after his discovery, he took the very first picture using x-rays of his wife's hand, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Anna Bertha<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. When she saw her skeleton she exclaimed "I have seen my death!".
The idea that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Röntgen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> noticed the shimmering of the barium platinocyanide screen simply through good fortune misrepresents his investigative powers; he had planned to use the screen in the next step of his experiment and would therefore have made the discovery a few moments later regardless.
At one point while he was investigating the ability of various materials to stop the rays, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Röntgen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> brought a small piece of lead into position while a discharge was occurring. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Röntgen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> thus saw the first radiographic image, his own flickering ghostly skeleton on the barium platinocyanide screen. He later reported that it was at this point that he determined to continue his experiments in secrecy, because he feared for his professional reputation if his observations were in error.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Röntgen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s original paper, "<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>On A New Kind Of Rays<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>" (<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Über eine neue Art von Strahlen<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>), was published 50 days later on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>28 December 1895<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>5 January 1896<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, an <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Austrian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> newspaper reported <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Röntgen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s discovery of a new type of radiation. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Röntgen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was awarded an honorary Doctor of Medicine degree from the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Würzburg<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> after his discovery. He published a total of three papers on X-rays between <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1895<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1897<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. Today, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Röntgen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> is considered the father of diagnostic radiology, the medical specialty which uses imaging to diagnose disease.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Röntgen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was married to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Anna Bertha Ludwig<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (m. <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1872<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, d. <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1919<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) and had one child, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Josephine Bertha Ludwig<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. Adopted at age 6, in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1887<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, she was the daughter of Anna's brother. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Röntgen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> died on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>10 February 1923<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> from carcinoma of the intestine. It is not believed his carcinoma was a result of his work with ionizing radiation because of the brief time he spent on those investigations, and because he was one of the few pioneers in the field who used protective lead shields routinely. In keeping with his will, all his personal and scientific correspondence were destroyed upon his death.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1901<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Röntgen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was awarded the very first <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Nobel Prize<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> in Physics. The award was officially "in recognition of the extraordinary services he has rendered by the discovery of the remarkable rays subsequently named after him". <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Röntgen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> donated the monetary reward from his <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Nobel Prize<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> to his university. Like <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Pierre Curie<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Röntgen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> refused to take out patents related to his discovery, as he wanted mankind as a whole to benefit from practical applications of the same (personal statement). He did not even want the rays to be named after him.
Today, in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Remscheid-Lennep<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, 40 kilometers east of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Düsseldorf<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, the house in which <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Roentgen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was born in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1845<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> is the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Deutsches Röntgen-Museum<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
In many languages, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Röntgen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s name (or a local linguistic derivative) is used to refer to radiology and its products instead of the term "x-ray", which <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Röntgen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> himself coined. Some examples are the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Japanese<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> "rentogen", the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Lithuanian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> "rentgeno", the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Hebrew<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> "rentgen", the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Croatian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> "rentgen", <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Turkish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> "röntgen" and many others.
The <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Philips<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> Medical System diagnostic radiography research and development division in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Hamburg DE<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> is on <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Röntgen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>strasse (<tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Röntgen Street<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>).
.
