<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>David Arnold Croll, PC, QC<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (born <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Davud Avrum Croll<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>March 12, 1900<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> – <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>June 11, 1991<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) was a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Canadian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> politician.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Croll<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was born in a shtetl in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Russia<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s Pale of Settlement and was brought to <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Canada<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> with his family as a young boy, at which point his name was anglicized. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Croll<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> became a lawyer as a young man and then entered politics serving as mayor of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Windsor<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Ontario<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1931<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1934<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> during the worst days of the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Great Depression<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. He made his reputation as a social reformer when he insisted the city go into deficit in order to provide relief programs for the unemployed and destitute.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Croll<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> won a seat in the<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/> Legislative Assembly<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Ontario<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> as a Liberal Member of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Legislative Assembly<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (MLA) for <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Windsor<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1934<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> election that brought the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Liberals<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> to power under the leadership of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mitchell Hepburn<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Croll<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> became <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Canada<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s first <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Jewish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> cabinet minister when he became Minister of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Public Welfare<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. He later also added the portfolios of Minister of Municipal Affairs and Minister of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Labour<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. He and Attorney-General <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Arthur Roebuck<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> broke with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hepburn<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> over the Premier's opposition to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>United Auto Workers<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> strike against <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>General Motors<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Oshawa<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1937<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, and resigned from cabinet saying "I would rather walk with the workers than ride with <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>General Motors<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>." He served in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Canadian Army<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> during the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Second World War<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, enlisting as a Private in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Essex Scottish Regiment<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and rising in rank to lieutenant-colonel. He remained a provincial Liberal backbencher until <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1943<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, as well as serving again as Mayor of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Windsor<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.
He was recruited by the Liberal Party of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Canada<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> to contest the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Toronto<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> riding of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Spadina<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1945<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> federal election. The <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Liberals<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> feared that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Tim Buck<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, leader of the communist <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Labour Progressive Party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> was poised to win the riding. The popular <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Croll<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was seen as the only Liberal who could defeat him. After <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Croll<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was nominated, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Buck<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> instead ran in a neighbouring riding, leaving <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sam Carr<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> to be the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>LPP<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s candidate. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Croll<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> handily won a seat in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Canadian House of Commons<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> becoming <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Spadina<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>'s Member of Parliament (MP) and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Tory Toronto<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s sole Liberal MP. He was re-elected in the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1949<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1953<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> elections.
Despite being regarded as one of the most talented Liberal MPs and, until <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1950<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, the only Liberal MP from <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Toronto<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Croll<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was never summoned to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Canadian Cabinet<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> where he would have become the first <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Jewish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> federal cabinet minister. Louis St. Laurent admitted to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Croll<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> that this was due to anti-Semitism in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Quebec<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and within quarters of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Liberal Party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. Instead, he was appointed to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Canadian Senate<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1955<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, becoming <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Canada<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s first <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Jewish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> senator.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Croll<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was the author of the influential <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1971<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> "Report of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Special Senate Committee<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> on Poverty" which began with the words "the poor do not choose poverty. It is at once their affliction and our national shame. The children of the poor (and there are many) are the most helpless victims of all, and find even less hope in a society where welfare systems from the very beginning destroys their chances of a better life." The report moved the <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Trudeau<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> government to triple family allowances in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1973<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and institute the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Child Tax Credit<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1978<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. Aside from his work on poverty, he was also responsible for Senate reports on aging. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1990<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> in recognition of his contributions, he was sworn into the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Queen's Privy Council<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> for <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Canada<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, an honour usually given only to federal cabinet ministers.
He remained a senator until his death in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1991<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
The Senator David A. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Croll<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> Apartments is a seniors' residence in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Toronto<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in the building formerly occupied by <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Rochdale College<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
.
