<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>David McPherson Broome CBE<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (born <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1 March 1940<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) is a retired <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Welsh<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> show jumping champion.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Broome<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was born in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Wales<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, attended <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Monmouth School<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and still maintains his stables at <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Mount Ballan Manor<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Crick<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, near <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Chepstow<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Monmouthshire<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. He won the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>European<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> championships in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1961<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1967<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, and <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1969<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, individual <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Olympic bronze medals<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1960<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1968<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, the latter on his best-known horse <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Mr Softee<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, on which he was only two fences (8 faults) behind the<tag name="MISC" value="start"/> Gold medal position<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1960<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> he was also voted <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>BBC Sports Personality of the Year<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. He won the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>World individual championship<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1970<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, and in the same year was <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Western Mail Welsh Sports Personality of the year<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1978<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> he was part of the world championship winning <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>British<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> team. He turned professional in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1973<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>David Broome<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> has won the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>King George V Gold Cup<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> a record six times on six different horses between <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1960<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>–<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1991<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, a record yet to be equalled. He has enjoyed most of his success on <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Irish Sport Horses<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> and he has said his favourite horse of all was Sportsman.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Broome<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> is still active in the administration of the sport.
