<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Louis Rasminsky, CC, CBE<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>February 1, 1908<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, - <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>September 15, 1998<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Ottawa<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>) was the third Governor of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Bank of Canada<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1961<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1973<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, succeeding <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>James Coyne<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. He was succeeded by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Gerald Bouey<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
Born in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Montreal<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, he was raised in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Toronto<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, graduated at <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Harbord Collegiate Institute<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, educated at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Toronto<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>London School of Economics<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1930<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he started at the<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/> League of Nations<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> as a specialist in monetary and banking issues. He joined the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Bank of Canada<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1940<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, becoming executive assistant to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Governors of the Bank<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1943<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1954<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Deputy Governor<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1955<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1968<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he was made a Companion of the Order of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Canada<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Canada<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s highest civilian honour, "for his services to <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Canada<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and a life-long career in the fields of international economic affairs and central banking". In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1968<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he was awarded the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Outstanding Achievement Award<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, the highest honour in the Public Service of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Canada<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. He was the first <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Canadian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> to receive an honorary degree from <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Yeshiva University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. He also received honorary degrees from <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Carleton University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Trent University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, and the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of British Columbia<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
His daughter, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lola Rasminsky<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, currently is Founder and Director of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Avenue Road Arts School<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Toronto<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. His son, Dr. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Michael Rasminsky<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, practices neurology at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Montreal General Hospital<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
