<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Graham Eric Stringer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (born <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>17 February 1950<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) is a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>British<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Labour Party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> politician who is the current Member of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Parliament<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (MP) for <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Blackley<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Broughton<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> having previously represented <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Manchester Blackley<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1997<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2010<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Stringer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> attended <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Christ Church Primary School<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Beswick<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Manchester<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and then went to <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Moston Brook High School for Boys<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (closed in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>August 2000<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) on <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Northampton Road<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Harpurhey<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>/<tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Monsall<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.
After graduating with a BSc (Hons) in Chemistry from the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Sheffield<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1971<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Stringer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> worked as an analytical chemist.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Stringer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> became a local councillor in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Manchester<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1979<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, and was <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Manchester City Council<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> leader from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1984<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1996<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. He was also chair of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Manchester Airport<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> plc from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1996<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1997<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Stringer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was first elected in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1997<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> taking over the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Blackley<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> seat of the retired <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Kenneth Eastham<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. He is only the third MP in the constituency since 1964, which has been a "safe" Labour seat since Paul Rose defeated Eric Johnson that year.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Stringer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s first role in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Labour government<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> was as a member of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Environment, Transport and Regions Select Committee<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> until <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1999<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. He then served as Parliamentary Secretary to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Cabinet Office<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> until <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2001<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. After a spell on the back benches and as a government whip, he spent the last six years of the Labour Government as a member of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Transport Committee<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. Although he was on the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Transport Committee<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> he campaigned against a proposed Congestion Charge in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Greater Manchester<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Stringer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> gained some notoriety when he became the first MP to publicly call for <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Gordon Brown<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> to resign as Prime Minister. Following boundary changes which abolished the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Manchester Blackley<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> constituency, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Stringer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> successfully contested the successor seats of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Blackley<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Broughton<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> at the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2010<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> general election.
On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>7 January 1999<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> he married <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Kathryn Carr<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>New Orleans<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>; the couple have one son.
In a <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2009<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> online column, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Stringer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> denied the existence of dyslexia, calling it "a cruel fiction" invented by "the education establishment" to divert blame for illiteracy from "their eclectic and incomplete methods for instruction". The charities <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Dyslexia Action<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> and the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>British Dyslexia Association<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> criticised <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Stringer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s claims.
