<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>William Brymner, CMG<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>December 14, 1855<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> – <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>June 18, 1925<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) was a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Canadian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> art teacher and a figure and landscape painter.
Born in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Greenock<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Scotland<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, the son of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Douglas Brymner<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> the first <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Dominion Archivist<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Jean Thomson<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, he moved with his family to <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Melbourne<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Lower Canada<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1857<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1864<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, his family moved to <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Montreal<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. Following architectural studies in enrolled at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Académie Julian<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Paris<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1878<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> where his instructors were <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>William-Adolphe Bouguereau<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Tony Robert-Fleury<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. Both of his teachers, in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Paris<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, were famous exponents of 'Grand manner' naturalism. During this period at the Salon he became interested in the work of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Jean-Louis Ernest Meissonier<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> who was already popular with the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>French<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> public.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Brymner<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> specialized in domestic figure scenes and avoided large historical subjects. <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Two Girls Reading of<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1898<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> displays a "careful treatment of light and an understanding of the force of a simple emphatic composition". In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1886<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> he settled in Montreal after staying in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Paris<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> "on and off for almost seven years". Two years prior to leaving <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Paris<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, at <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Runswick Bay<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Yorkshire<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, he completed A Wreath of Flowers.
Many members of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Beaver Hall Group<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> studied under <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>William Brymner<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, a prominent <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Canadian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> artist who encouraged them to explore new modernistic approaches to painting.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1883<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he was made an associate of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Royal Canadian Academy of Arts<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>RCA<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>). He was elected vice-president of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>RCA<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1907<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and president in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1909<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1916<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he was made a Companion of the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Order of St Michael and St George<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>.
