<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Georges Jean Marie Valiron<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>7 September 1884<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>  <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>March 1955<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) was a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>French<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> mathematician, notable for his contributions to analysis, in particular, the asymptotic behaviour of and <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Tauberian theorems<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Valiron<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> obtained his Ph.D. from the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Paris<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1914<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, under supervision of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Émile Borel<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. Since <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1922<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> he held a professorship at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Strasbourg<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, and since <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1931<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> a chair at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Paris<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. He held a plenary speech at the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1932<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> International <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Congress of Mathematicians<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Zürich<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.
He was awarded the title Commander of the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Legion of Honour<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1954<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. One of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Valiron<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s doctoral students, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Laurent Schwartz<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, went on to receive a <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Fields Medal<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1950<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
.
