<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ozias Leduc<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>October 8, 1864<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> - <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>June 16, 1955<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) is one of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Quebec<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>'s early painters. He was born in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Saint-Hilaire-de-Rouville<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Leduc<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> produced many portraits, still lives and landscapes, as well as religious works.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Leduc<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was mainly self-taught. Around <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1880<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he worked with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Luigi Cappello<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, an <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Italian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> painter, on church decorations. Around <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1881<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he was employed at Carli, a manufacturer of statues in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Montreal. Around<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1883<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he worked with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Adolphe Rho<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, decorating another church, this time in <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Yamachiche<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. After that, he started working on his own on church decorations. Leduc made a brief trip to Paris and <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>London<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1897<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> with <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>Suzor-Coté<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, where he was influenced by some impressionists.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Leduc<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> received an Honorary doctorate from the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Université de Montréal<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1938<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. His legacy includes teaching <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Paul-Émile Borduas<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. He is best known for his work decorating the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Notre-Dame-de-la-Présentation church<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> in <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Shawinigan South<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, a project which took him thirteen years to complete. <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Notre-Dame-de-la-Présentation<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> church was designated of National Historic Significance of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Canada<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>2004<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and it was plaqued in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2005<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Leduc<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> lived a very solitary life in his home town and was dubbed "the sage of St-Hilaire".
He died in Saint-Hyacinthe in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1955<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
.
