<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Muhammad Hosni Sayyid Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Arabic<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>: , <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/><tag name="MISC" value="start"/> Arabic<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> pronunciation:&#160; , ; born <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>4 May 1928<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) is a former <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> politician and military commander. He served as the fourth President of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1981<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2011<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was appointed Vice President of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1975<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, and assumed the presidency on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>14 October 1981<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, following the assassination of President <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Anwar El Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. The length of his presidency made him <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s longest-serving ruler since <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Muhammad Ali Pasha<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. Before he entered politics, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was a career officer in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egyptian Air Force<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, serving as its commander from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1972<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1975<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and rising to the rank of air chief marshal.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was ousted after 18 days of demonstrations during the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2011<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> revolution when, on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>11 February<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, Vice President <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Omar Suleiman<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> announced that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> had resigned as president and transferred authority to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Supreme Council of the Armed Forces<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>13 April<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, a prosecutor[which?] ordered <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and both his sons to be detained for 15 days of questioning about allegations of corruption and abuse of power. He was then ordered to stand trial on charges of premeditated murder of peaceful protestors during the revolution. These trials officially began on the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>3 August 2011<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>’s military prosecutors then also proclaimed that it is investigating <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s role in the assassination of his predecessor <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Anwar Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was born on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>4 May 1928<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Kafr El-Meselha<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Monufia Governorate<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. He is married to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Suzanne Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, and has two sons: <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Alaa<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Gamal<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
Upon completion of high school, he joined the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egyptian Military Academy<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, where he received a Bachelor's degree in Military Sciences in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1949<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2 February 1949<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> left the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Military Academy<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and joined the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Air Force Academy<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, gaining his commission as a pilot officer on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>13 March 1950<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and eventually receiving a Bachelor's Degree in Aviation Sciences.
As an <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egyptian Air Force<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> officer, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> served in various formations and units, including two years when he served in a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Spitfire<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> fighter squadron. Some time in the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1950<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>s, he returned to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Air Force Academy<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, this time as an instructor, remaining there until early <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1959<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. From <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>February 1959<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>June 1961<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> undertook further training in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Soviet Union<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, attending a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Soviet<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> pilot training school in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Moscow<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and another at <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Kant Air Base<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, near <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Bishkek<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Kyrgyzstan<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> (then a <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Soviet republic<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>), an airfield that is today home to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Russian 5th Air Army<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>999th Air Base<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> undertook training on the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Ilyushin Il-28<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> and <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Tupolev Tu-16<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> jet bomber, and then joined the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Frunze Military Academy<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1964<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. On his return to <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> served in wing and then base commander appointments, taking up command of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Cairo West Air Base<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>October 1966<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> before briefly commanding the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Beni Suef Air Base<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>November 1967<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> became the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Air Force Academy<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s commander when he was credited with doubling the number of pilots and navigators in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Air Force<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> during the pre-<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>October War<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> years. Two years later he became <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Chief of Staff<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> for the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egyptian Air Force<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> became Commander of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Air Force<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egyptian Deputy Minister of Defence<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1972<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. In the following year his military career reached its pinnacle when he was promoted to <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Air Chief Marshal<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> in recognition of service during the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>October War<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> of <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1973<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> has been credited in some publications for <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s initial strong performance in the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1973<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> war against <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. The <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> analyst <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mohamed Hassanein Heikal<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> gave a different evaluation of the role of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Air Force<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1973<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> from that of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and his supporters. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Heikal<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> argued that the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Air Force<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> played a mostly psychological role in the war, providing an inspirational sight for the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> ground troops that carried out the crossing of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Suez Canal<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, rather than for any military necessity. The role of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was further disputed by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Shahdan El-Shazli<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> the daughter of the former <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> military <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Chief of Staff<tag name="MISC" value="end"/><tag name="PERSON" value="start"/> Saad el-Shazly<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. She alleged that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> altered the representation of a number of events pertaining to the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1973<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> war to show a magnified role for himself. In an interview with the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> independent newspaper <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Almasry Alyoum<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>26 Feb 2011<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>), <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>El-Shazli<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> claimed that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> altered documents to take credit for the initial success of the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> forces in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1973<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> from her father. She alleged that even photographs pertaining to the discussions in the military command room were altered, so that the pictures of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Saad El-Shazli<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> were erased and replaced by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. She stated that she intends to take a legal action with this regard.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>April 1975<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was appointed by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> as Vice President of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. In this position, he loyally served <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s policies. He took part in government consultations that dealt with the future disengagement of forces agreement with <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
As part of his support for <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s policies, he went in early <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>September 1975<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> on a mission to <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Riyadh<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, and <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Damascus<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> to convince the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Saudi Arabian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, and <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Syrian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> governments to accept the disengagement agreement signed with the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israeli government<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> ("<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Sinai II<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>"), but was refused a meeting by the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Syrian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> President, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hafez Al-Assad<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
In addition, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was sent by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> to numerous meetings with foreign leaders. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s political significance as Vice-President can be seen from the fact that at a conversation held on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>23 June 1975<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> between Foreign Minister <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Fahmy<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>US<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Ambassador<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hermann Eilts<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Fahmy<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> said to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Eilts<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> that "<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mobarek<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> [sic] is, for the time being at least, likely to be a regular participant in all sensitive meetings" and he advised the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Ambassador<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> not to antagonize <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, as he was <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s personal choice.
Following the assassination of President <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>October 1981<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> by a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Jihad<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> cell in the military led by Lieutenant <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Khalid Islambouli<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hosni Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> became the fourth President of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, and the Chairman of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>National Democratic Party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>NDP<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>). He was the longest serving President of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, his term lasting 29 years.
Until <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Libya<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s suspension from the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Arab League<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> at the beginning of the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2011<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Libyan<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> civil war, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> was the only state in the history of the organisation to have had its membership suspended, due to President <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s peace treaty with <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. However, in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1989<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, eight years after , <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> was re-admitted as a full member, and the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>League<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s headquarters were relocated to their original location in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Cairo<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.
<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> was a member of the allied coalition in the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1991<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Gulf War<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, and <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> infantry were some of the first to land in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Saudi Arabia<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> to evict <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Iraqi<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> forces from <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Kuwait<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s involvement in the coalition was deemed by the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>US<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> government as crucial in garnering wider <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Arab<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> support for the liberation of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Kuwait<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
In addition to further solidifying <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s central role in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Arab World<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, the participation of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> forces brought financial benefits for the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> government. Reports that sums as large as $500, 000 per soldier were paid or debt forgiven were published in the news media. According to <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>The Economist<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>:.
According to the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>BBC<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> has survived six assassination attempts. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>June 1995<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> there was an alleged assassination attempt involving noxious gases and <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/><tag name="MISC" value="start"/> Islamic<tag name="MISC" value="end"/><tag name="MISC" value="start"/> Jihad<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> while he was in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Ethiopia<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> for a conference of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Organization of African Unity<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. Upon return <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> is said to have authorized bombings on <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Al-Gama'a al-Islamiyya<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, which by <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1999<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> saw 20, 000 persons placed in detention related to the revolutionary <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Islamic<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> organizations. He was also reportedly injured by a knife-wielding assailant in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Port Said<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>September 1999<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
In his early years in power, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> greatly expanded the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egyptian State Security Investigations Service<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Mabahith Amn ad-Dawla<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>) and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Central Security Forces<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (anti-riot and containment forces). According to author <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Tarek Osman<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, the experience of seeing his predecessor assassinated "right in front of him" and his much longer military career than Presidents <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Nasser<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> or <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> may have instilled in him more focus and absorption with security than seemed the case with either of those heads of the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> state. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> sought advice and confidence not in "leading ministers, " "senior advisors" or "leading intellectuals", but from his security chiefs -- various "interior ministers, army commanders, and the heads of the ultra-influential intelligence services." .
President <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> spoke out against the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2003<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Iraq War<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, arguing that the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Israeli-Palestinian conflict<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> should have been resolved first. He also claimed that the war would cause "100 <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bin Ladens<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>." However, as President he did not support an immediate <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>US<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> pull out from <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Iraq<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> as he believes it will lead to probable chaos.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>July 2004<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> accepted the resignation of Prime Minister <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Atef Ebeid<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and most of the cabinet. He then appointed <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ahmed Nazif<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> as the new Prime Minister. The new cabinet was generally viewed with optimism. Economic conditions were starting to improve considerably after a period of stagnation. The new cabinet headed by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ahmed Nazif<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> had some success in overcoming the grim economic situation. The <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> stock market had the greatest percentage increase of all emerging markets for the fiscal year <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2004<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>/<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2005<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. However, unemployment persisted and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> came under criticism for favoring big business and privatization as opposed to workers' rights. All this was a consequence of the wide use of privatization policy, by selling shares in most public sector companies, but it was widely believed that this reserve of previously nationalized capitals would end soon, leaving <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Nazif<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s government broke.
President <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> has been re-elected by majority votes in a referendum for successive terms on four occasions: in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1987<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1993<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, and <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1999<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. The referendum in itself and its results are of questionable validity[who?]. No one could run against the President due to a restriction in the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> constitution in which the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>People's Assembly<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> played the main role in electing the President of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Republic<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
After increased domestic and international pressure for democratic reform in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> asked the parliament on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>26 February 2005<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to amend the constitution to allow multi-candidate presidential elections by <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>September 2005<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. Previously, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> secured his position by having himself nominated by parliament, then confirmed without opposition in a referendum.
The <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>September 2005<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> ballot was, therefore, a multiple candidate election rather than a referendum, but the electoral institutions, and security apparatus remain under the control of the President. The official state media, including the three government newspapers and state television also express views identical to the official line taken by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. In the last few years however, the cabinet headed by Prime Minister <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ahmed Nazif<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> has been somewhat successful in turning things around. According to the List of countries by <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Human Development Index<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/><tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/> Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> ranks 111th out of 177 countries, and rates 0.702 on the index.
On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>28 July 2005<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> announced his candidacy, as he had been widely expected to do. The election which was scheduled for <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>7 September 2005<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> involved mass rigging activities, according to civil organizations that observed the elections. Reports have shown that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s party used government vehicles to take public employees to vote for him. Votes were bought for <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> in poor suburbs and rural areas. It was also reported that thousands of illegal votes were allowed for <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> from citizens who were not registered to vote. On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>8 September 2005<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ayman Nour<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, a dissident and candidate for the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>El-Ghad Party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> ("<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Tomorrow party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>"), contested the election results, and demanded a repeat of the election.
In a move widely seen as political persecution, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Nour<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was convicted of forgery and sentenced to five years at hard labor on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>24 December 2005<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. On the day of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Nour<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s guilty verdict and sentencing, the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>White House Press Secretary<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> released the following statement denouncing the government's action:.
"The <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>United States<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> is deeply troubled by the conviction today of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> politician <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ayman Nour<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> by an <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> court. The conviction of Dr. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Nour<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, the runner-up in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2005<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> presidential elections, calls into question <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s commitment to democracy, freedom and the rule of law. We are also disturbed by reports that Mr. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Nour<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s health has seriously declined due to the hunger strike on which he has embarked in protest of the conditions of his trial and detention. The <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>United States<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> calls upon the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> government to act under the laws of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in the spirit of its professed desire for increased political openness and dialogue within <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> society, and out of humanitarian concern, to release Mr. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Nour<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> from detention.".
According to <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Reporters Without Borders<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>; <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> media ranks 133 out of 168 in freedom of the press, showing an improvement of 10 places from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2005<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
While in office, political corruption in the <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> administration's Ministry of Interior rose dramatically, due to the increased power over the institutional system that is necessary to secure the prolonged presidency.[clarification needed] Such corruption has led to the imprisonment of political figures and young activists without trials, illegal undocumented hidden detention facilities, and rejecting universities, mosques, newspapers staff members based on political inclination. On a personnel level, [clarification needed] each individual officer is allowed to violate citizens' privacy in his area using unconditioned arrests due to the emergency law.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2005<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Freedom House<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, a non-governmental organization that conducts research into democracy, reported that the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> governments, under <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> expanded bureaucratic regulations, registration requirements, and other controls that feed corruption. Whenever <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>s face such controls, money is what ultimately triggers the requisite signature or relevant approval. Compounding the normal bureaucratic culture is the state ownership of many or most of the primary economic levers – banking and financial institutions, tourism, oil, the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Suez Canal<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, manufacturing, the media, and so on. Furthermore, government employees receive insufficient pay, while a decreasing minority of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptians<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> achieve increasingly vast wealth, thus creating a growing income gap between the classes and causing the supposed middle class to be squeezed to the smallest minority between the rich and the poor. <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Freedom House<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> claimed that "corruption remained a significant problem under <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, who promised to do much, but in fact neither did anything significant to tackle it effectively.".
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2010<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Transparency International<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Corruption Perceptions Index<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> report assessed <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> with a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>CPI<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> score of 3.1, based on perceptions of the degree of corruption from business people and country analysts, with 10 being very clean and 0 being highly corrupt. <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> ranked 98th out of the 178 countries included in the report.
<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> is a semi-presidential republic under <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Emergency Law<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Law No. 162 of 1958<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>) and has been since <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1967<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, except for an 18-month break in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1980<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>s (which ended with the assassination of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Anwar Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>). Under the law, police powers are extended, constitutional rights suspended and censorship is legalized. The law sharply circumscribes any non-governmental political activity: street demonstrations, non-approved political organizations, and unregistered financial donations are formally banned. Some 17, 000 people are detained under the law, and estimates of political prisoners run as high as 30, 000. Under that "state of emergency", the government has the right to imprison individuals for any period of time, and for virtually no reason, thus keeping them in prisons without trials for any period. The government continues the claim that opposition groups like the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Muslim Brotherhood<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> could come into power in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> if the current government did not forgo parliamentary elections, confiscate the group's main financiers' possessions, and detain group figureheads, actions which are virtually impossible without emergency law and judicial-system independence prevention. Pro-democracy advocates in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> argue that this goes against the principles of democracy, which include a citizen's right to a fair trial and their right to vote for whichever candidate and/or party they deem fit to run their country.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2009<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>US<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/><tag name="MISC" value="start"/> Ambassador<tag name="MISC" value="end"/><tag name="PERSON" value="start"/> Margaret Scobey<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> reported uncertainty regarding presidential succession, stating "Despite incessant whispered discussions, no one in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> has any certainty about who will eventually succeed <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> nor under what circumstances." She listed likely candidates, saying, "The most likely contender is presidential son <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Gamal Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (whose profile was ever-increasing at the ruling party, until that party collapsed during The <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian Revolution<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> of <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2011<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>); some suggest that intelligence chief <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Omar Suleiman<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> might seek the office, or dark horse <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Arab League<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> Secretary-General <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Amr Moussa<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> might run. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s ideal of a strong but fair leader would seem to discount <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Gamal Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> to some degree, given <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Gamal<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s lack of military experience, and may explain <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s hands off approach to the succession question." President <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and his son denied this, "saying [that] a multi-candidate electoral system has made the political process more transparent." <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Nigerian Tribune<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> journalist <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Abiodun Awolaja<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> described a would-be succession by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Gamal Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> as a "hereditary pseudo-monarchy". <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Ambassador<tag name="MISC" value="end"/><tag name="PERSON" value="start"/> Scobey<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> summarised <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s vision of the presidential succession, stating, "Indeed, he seems to be trusting to <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>God<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> and the ubiquitous military and civilian security services to ensure an orderly transition." The <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>National Democratic Party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> continued to state that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hosni Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was to be the party's only candidate to the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2011<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> Presedential Elections. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> declared on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1 February 2011<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> that he had no intention to run in the presidential race at the end of <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2011<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. When this declaration failed to ease the protests, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s vice president stated that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Gamal Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, the son, will not run for president. With the escalation of the demonstration and the fall of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, a former influential figure in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>National Democratic Party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hamdy El-Sayed<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, claimed that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Gamal Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> intended to forcibly take over his father's position, assisted in that by the then Interior Minister, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Habib El-Adly<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hosni Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> is generally supportive of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. As he has been involved intensely in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Arab League<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, he has supported <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Arab<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> efforts to achieve a lasting peace in the region. The current position of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>League<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> is that which was endorsed at the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Beirut Summit<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>28 March 2002<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. At the summit the league adopted the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Arab Peace Initiative<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Saudi<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>-inspired peace plan for the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Arab–Israeli conflict<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. The initiative offered full normalization of the relations with <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. In exchange, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> was demanded to withdraw from all occupied territories, including the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Golan Heights<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, to recognize an independent <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Palestinian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> state in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>West Bank<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Gaza Strip<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> with <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>East Jerusalem<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> as its capital, as well as a "just solution" for the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Palestinian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> refugees. The <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Peace Initiative<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> was again endorsed at <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2007<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> in the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Riyadh Summit<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>July 2007<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Arab League<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> sent a mission, consisting of the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Jordanian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> and <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> foreign ministers, to <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> to promote the initiative.
On 19 June 2008, the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>-brokered "lull" or pause in hostilities between <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Hamas<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> went into effect. The term "lull" is a translation of the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Arabic<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> term <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Tahdia<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. According to The <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>New York Times<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, neither side fully respected the terms of the cease-fire.
The agreement required <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Hamas<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> to end rocket attacks on <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and to enforce the lull throughout <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Gaza<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. In exchange, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Hamas<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> expected the blockade to end, commerce in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Gaza<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> to resume, and truck shipments to be restored to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2005<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> levels, which was between 500 and 600 trucks per day. <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> tied easing of the blockade to a reduction in rocket fire and gradually re-opened supply lines and permitted around 90 daily truck shipments to enter <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Gaza<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, up from around 70 per day. <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Hamas<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> criticized <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> for its continued blockade while <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> accused <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Hamas<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> of continued weapons smuggling via tunnels to <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and pointed to continued rocket attacks.
However, when conflict again ensued during the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Gaza War<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s foreign minister stated that <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Hamas<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> had brought it upon itself.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2009<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s government banned the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Cairo Anti-war Conference<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, which has criticised his lack of action against <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
Mass protests against <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and his regime erupted in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Cairo<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and other <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> cities on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>25 January 2011<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1 February<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> announced he would not contest the presidential election due in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>September<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. He also promised constitutional reform. This did not satisfy the majority of protesters as they expected <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> to depart immediately. The demonstrations continued and on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2 February<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, violent clashes occurred between pro-<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and anti-<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> protestors.
On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>10 February<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, contrary to rumours, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> asserted that he would not resign until the September election, though he would be delegating responsibilities to Vice President <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Omar Suleiman<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. The next day, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Suleiman<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> announced that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> had resigned. The announcement sparked cheers, flag-waving, and celebrations from protesters in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> after <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s announcement of resignation. Discussions began about the nation's future direction. It had been suggested that <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> be put in the hands of a caretaker government. A few hours prior to the resignation announcement, reports surfaced suggesting the ousted president and his immediate family had left <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Cairo<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> for <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Sharm el-Sheikh<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.
On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>25 January 2011<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, protests against <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and his government erupted in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Cairo<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and around <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> calling for <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s resignation. The group protesting in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Cairo<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>'s <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Tahrir Square<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> was so large that they could be seen from space as they rallied <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s resignation, chanting anti-<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> slogans. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> stated in a speech that he would not leave, and would die on <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> soil. Opposition leader <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mohamed ElBaradei<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> paid no attention to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s remarks and labeled it as a trick designed to help <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> to stay in power. In a state televised broadcast on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1 February 2011<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> announced that he would not seek re-election in September but would like to finish his current term and promised constitutional reform. This compromise was not acceptable for the protestors and violent demonstrations occurred in front of the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Presidential Palace<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> where pro- and anti-<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> protestors clashed. On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>11 February<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, Vice President <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Omar Suleiman<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> announced <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarek<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> had resigned and that power would be turned over to the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> military.
Two and a half hours after <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s resignation, an <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> military member came on air and thanked him for "putting the interests of the country first." The statement, which said "The <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Supreme Council<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> is currently studying the situation, " never provided what the council will do next.
Following his resignation, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> did not make any media appearances. With the exception of family and a close circle of aides, he reportedly refused to talk to anyone, even his supporters. His health was speculated to be rapidly deteriorating with some reports even alleging him to be in a coma. Most sources claim that he is no longer interested in performing any duties and wants to "die in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Sharm El-Sheikh<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.".
On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>28 February 2011<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, the General Prosecutor of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> issued an order prohibiting <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and his family from leaving <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. It was reported that the former president was in contact with his lawyer in case of possible criminal charges against him. As a result, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and his family had been under house arrest at a presidential palace in the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Red Sea<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> resort of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Sharm el-Sheikh<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>13 April<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, a prosecutor originally appointed by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> ordered the former president and both his sons to be detained for 15 days of questioning about allegations of corruption and abuse of power amidst growing suspicion that the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> military was more aligned with the <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>s than with the revolution. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Gamal<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Alaa<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> were jailed in <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Tora Prison<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, while state television reported that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was in police custody in a hospital near his residence following a heart attack. Former <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>i Cabinet minister <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Benjamin Ben Eliezer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> told <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Israeli Radio<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> that he had offered <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> refuge in the southern <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Israeli<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> city of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Eilat<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.
On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>24 May 2011<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was ordered to stand trial on charges of premeditated murder of peaceful protestors during the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2011<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian revolution<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> and, if convicted, could face the death penalty. The decision to try <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was made days before a scheduled protest in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Tahir Square<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. The full list of charges released by the public prosecutor was "intentional murder, attempted killing of some demonstrators...misuse of influence and deliberately wasting public funds and unlawfully making private financial gains and profits.".
On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>28 May 2011<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, a <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Cairo<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> administrative court found him guilty of damaging the national economy during the protests by shutting down the Internet and telephone services. He was fined LE200 million (about <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>US<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>$33.6 million), which the court ordered he must pay from his personal assets. This was the first court ruling against <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, who will next have to answer to the murder charges.
The trial of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hosni Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and his two sons <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ala'a<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Gamal<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, along with former interior minister <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Habib el-Adly<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and six former top police officials began on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>3 August 2011<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> at a temporary criminal court at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Police Academy<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in north <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Cairo<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. The charges are corruption and the premediated killing of peaceful protestors during the mass movement to oust him, the latter of which carries the death penalty. The trial was broadcast on <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> television, with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> making a surprise first appearance since his resignation, brought in on a hospital bed and held in a cage for the session. Upon reading out the charges to him, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> pleaded not guilty, denying responsibility for the charges against him. Judge <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ahmed Refaat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> adjourned the court, ruling that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> be transferred under continued arrest to the military hospital on the outskirts of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Cairo<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, with the second session scheduled for <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>15 August<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>15 August<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> the trial was resumed. It lasted three hours, at the conclusion of which Judge <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Rifaat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> determined that the third session would take place on 5 September and that the remainder of the proceedings would be off-limits to television cameras.
In the summer of <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2010<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, the media speculated "<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> is on the cusp of dramatic change", because <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was thought to be afflicted by cancer, and because of the scheduled <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2011<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> presidential election. While intelligence sources suggested that he suffered from esophageal cancer, stomach or pancreatic cancer, it was denied by <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> authorities. Speculation about his ill health flared up with his resignation on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>11 February 2011<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. According to <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> media, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s condition worsened after he went into exile in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Sharm el-Sheikh<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was reportedly depressed, refused to take medications, and was slipping in and out of consciousness. According to the source, an unnamed <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> security official, "<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> wants to be left alone and die in his homeland". The source also denied that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was writing his memoirs, stating that he was in a state of almost complete unconsciousness. After his <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>February 2011<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> resignation, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s ambassador to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>United States<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/><tag name="PERSON" value="start"/> Sameh Shoukry<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> reported that his personal sources said <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> "is possibly in somewhat of bad health", while several <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> and a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Saudi Arabian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> newspapers reported that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was near death and in a coma. On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>12 April 2011<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, it was reported that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> had been hospitalized after suffering a heart attack during questioning over possible corruption charges.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>June 2011<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s lawyer <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Farid el-Deeb<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> disclosed that his client "has stomach cancer, and the cancer is growing." <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> had undergone sugery for the condition in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Germany<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> the year prior and also suffers from circulatory problems with an irregular heart beat. On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>13 July 2011<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, unconfirmed reports sprang up that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> had slipped into a coma at his residence after giving his final speech, and four days later, on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>17 July<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>el-Deep<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> confirmed that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> had slipped into a coma.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>February 2011<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, the media reported on the wealth of the <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> family. <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>ABC News<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> indicated that experts believed the personal wealth of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and his family to be between <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>US<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>$40&#160; billion and $70&#160; billion founded on military contracts made during his time as an air force officer. <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Britain's Guardian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> newspaper also reported that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and his family might be worth up to $70&#160; billion due to corruption, kickbacks and legitimate business activities. The money was said to be spread out in various bank accounts at home and abroad, including <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Switzerland <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Britain<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, and also invested in foreign property. The newspaper admitted, however, that some of the information regarding the family's wealth might be ten years old. According to <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Newsweek<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, these allegations are poorly substantiated and lack credibility. On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>17 March 2011<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> Senator <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>John Kerry<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, head of foreign relations committee of the congress, officially confirmed that the government of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>United States<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> froze assets worth $31&#160; billion belonging to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, including property and bank accounts. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>John Kerry<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> later retracted his statement saying he meant <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Gaddafi<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> not <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>12 February 2011<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, the government of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Switzerland <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>announced that it was freezing the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Swiss<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> bank accounts of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and his family. On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>20 February 2011<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> Prosecutor General ordered the freeze of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s assets and the assets of his wife <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Suzanne<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, his sons <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Alaa<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Gamal Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, and his daughters in law <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Heidi Rasekh<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Khadiga Gamal<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. The Prosecutor General also ordered the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> Foreign Minster to communicate this to other countries where <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and his family could have assets. This order came two days after <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> newspapers reported that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> filed his financial statement. The <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> regulations mandate government officials to submit a financial statement listing his / her total assets and sources of income during governmental work. On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>21 February 2011<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egyptian Military Council<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, which was temporarily given the presidential authorities following the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>25 January 2011<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Revolution<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, declared no objection to a trial of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> on charges of corruption. On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>23 February 2011<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> newspaper <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Eldostor<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> reported that a "knowledgeable source" described the order of the Prosecutor General for freezing <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s assets and the threats of a legal action as nothing but a signal for <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> to leave <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> after a number of attempts were made to encourage him to leave willingly. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>February 2011<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Voice of America<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> reported that <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s top prosecutor has ordered a travel ban and an asset freeze for former President <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hosni Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and his family, as he considers further action.
A monument to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hosni Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was erected in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2007<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Xırdalan<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Azerbaijan<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>). The <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Azerbaijani Musavat party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> called for its demolition in order to avoid idolatry. The monument was then taken down and a statue symbolising <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and ancient <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> culture was erected instead.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> is ranked 20th on <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Parade Magazine<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>'s <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2009<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> World's Worst Dictators list. He, as other presidents had been before him, had frequently been the target of jokes by the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> people for many years before his resignation.
.
 .
1 served as acting President of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> for eight days following <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s assassination.
2 currently acting head of state, as Chairman of ruling <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Supreme Council of the Armed Forces<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, following .
 .
 .
 