<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Shaban Terstena<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Albanian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>: , <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Macedonian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>: , <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Serbo-Croatian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>: , born <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>January 1, 1965<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Skopje<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>SR Macedonia<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Yugoslavia<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>) is a former <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Yugoslavian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> and <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Macedonian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> wrestler with <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Albanian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> origin, who won the gold medal at the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1984<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Olympics<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Los Angeles<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and also won the silver medal at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Seoul Olympics<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1988<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Terstena<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> is the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1984<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>European<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> champion, won the silver medals in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1983<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1985<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1986<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, and the bronze in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1982<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1988<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. He holds the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1982<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>World Wrestling Championships<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> bronze. Whenever he took part in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Mediterranean<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> or <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Balkan Games<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, he was the wrestler to win the first place. He has been pronounced the Best <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Macedonian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> athlete many times and once, in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1984<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2000<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> he has been also pronounced the best <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Albanian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> athlete of the last century. He has won 715 matches out of 741 fights. He participated in 42 tournaments in the world winning 30 gold medals, the remainder being silver and bronze. At the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Atlanta Olympic Games<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1996<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> he won the fifth place.
.
