<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Gad Lerner<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (born <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>7 December 1954<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Beirut<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Lebanon<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>) is an <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Italian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> journalist and writer.
A member of the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Jewish<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> community, he began his news career in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1976<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, writing for the ultra-leftist daily <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>Lotta Continua<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, belonging to the eponymous political entity, becoming its deputy director. He then worked for the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Genoan<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> daily <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Il Lavoro<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, as well as for <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Radio Popolare<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, the communist newspaper <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Il Manifesto<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> and the weekly newsmagazine <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>L'Espresso<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>.
Notoriety and success came when he started working for television broadcasts on <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Rai Tre<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, among which <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Profondo Nord<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Milano<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Italia<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. His reporting coincided with the infamous years of bribery scandals, known as Tangentopoli (Italian for Bribesville), and the ascent of the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Lega Nord<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> separatist political movement - <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lerner<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> successfully portrayed in his shows the deep changes the country was experiencing.
He later served as director deputy director of the national newspaper <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>La Stampa<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> and briefly as director of news broadcasts for <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>TG1<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> and <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Rai Uno<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. He publicly resigned after a selection of pornographic footage was mistakenly aired on prime time during his news broadcast, <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>TG1<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. Along with his resignation, he revealed that a politician from <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>National Alliance<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mario Landolfi<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, who also was the president of the parliamentary commission of vigilance regarding the public TV broadcasting service, asked him to favour an acquaintance of his in the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>TG1<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Gad Lerner<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> is currently host of the news talkshow <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>L'Infedele<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, on <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>La7 TV <tag name="MISC" value="end"/>channel. He is considered left-leaning. He also occasionally collaborates with the weekly <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Vanity Fair Italia<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, and writes books. He maintains his personal blog, where he personally writes to and answers his visitors (www.gadlerner.it).
