<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Jules Henri Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>29 April 1854<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>  <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>17 July 1912<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) (<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>French<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> pronunciation:&#160; ) was a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>French<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> mathematician, theoretical physicist, engineer, and a philosopher of science. He is often described as a polymath, and in mathematics as The Last Universalist, since he excelled in all fields of the discipline as it existed during his lifetime.
As a mathematician and physicist, he made many original fundamental contributions to pure and applied mathematics, mathematical physics, and celestial mechanics. He was responsible for formulating the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Poincaré conjecture<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, one of the most famous unsolved problems in mathematics, until it was solved in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2002<tag name="DATE" value="end"/><tag name="DATE" value="start"/>3<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. In his research on the three-body problem, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> became the first person to discover a chaotic deterministic system which laid the foundations of modern chaos theory. He is also considered to be one of the founders of the field of topology.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> introduced the modern principle of relativity and was the first to present the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Lorentz transformations<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> in their modern symmetrical form. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> discovered the remaining relativistic velocity transformations and recorded them in a letter to <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Dutch<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> physicist <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hendrik Lorentz<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1853<tag name="DATE" value="end"/><tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1928<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1905<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. Thus he obtained perfect invariance of all of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Maxwell's equations<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, an important step in the formulation of the theory of special relativity.
The <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> group used in physics and mathematics was named after him.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was born on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>29 April 1854<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Cité Ducale<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> neighborhood, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Nancy<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Meurthe-et-Moselle<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> into an influential family (<tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Belliver<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>1956<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>). His father <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Leon Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1828<tag name="DATE" value="end"/><tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1892<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) was a professor of medicine at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Nancy<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Sagaret<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1911<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>). His adored younger sister <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Aline<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> married the spiritual philosopher <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Emile Boutroux<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. Another notable member of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Jules<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>' family was his cousin, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Raymond Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, who would become the President of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>France<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1913<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1920<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, and a fellow member of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Académie française<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
During his childhood he was seriously ill for a time with diphtheria and received special instruction from his mother, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Eugénie Launois<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1830<tag name="DATE" value="end"/><tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1897<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>).
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1862<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Henri<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> entered the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Lycée in Nancy<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (now renamed the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Lycée Henri Poincaré<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in his honour, along with the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Nancy<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>). He spent eleven years at the Lycée and during this time he proved to be one of the top students in every topic he studied. He excelled in written composition. His mathematics teacher described him as a "monster of mathematics" and he won first prizes in the concours général, a competition between the top pupils from all the Lycées across <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>France<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. His poorest subjects were music and physical education, where he was described as "average at best" (<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>O'Connor et al.<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2002<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>). However, poor eyesight and a tendency towards absentmindedness may explain these difficulties (<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Carl<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1968<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>). He graduated from the Lycée in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1871<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> with a Bachelor's degree in letters and sciences.
During the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Franco-Prussian War<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> of <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1870<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> he served alongside his father in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Ambulance Corps<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> entered the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>École Polytechnique<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1873<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. There he studied mathematics as a student of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Charles Hermite<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, continuing to excel and publishing his first paper (Démonstration nouvelle des propriétés de l'indicatrice d'une surface) in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1874<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. He graduated in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1875<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> or <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1876<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. He went on to study at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>École des Mines<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, continuing to study mathematics in addition to the mining engineering syllabus and received the degree of ordinary engineer in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>March 1879<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
As a graduate of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>École des Mines<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> he joined the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Corps des Mines<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> as an inspector for the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Vesoul<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> region in northeast <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>France<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. He was on the scene of a mining disaster at <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Magny<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>August 1879<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> in which 18 miners died. He carried out the official investigation into the accident in a characteristically thorough and humane way.
At the same time, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was preparing for his doctorate in sciences in mathematics under the supervision of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Charles Hermite<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. His doctoral thesis was in the field of differential equations. It was named <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Sur les propriétés des fonctions définies par les équations différences<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> devised a new way of studying the properties of these equations. He not only faced the question of determining the integral of such equations, but also was the first person to study their general geometric properties. He realised that they could be used to model the behaviour of multiple bodies in free motion within the solar system. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> graduated from the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Paris<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1879<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
Soon after, he was offered a post as junior lecturer in mathematics at <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Caen University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, but he never fully abandoned his mining career to mathematics. He worked at the Ministry of Public Services as an engineer in charge of northern railway development from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1881<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1885<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. He eventually became chief engineer of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Corps de Mines<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1893<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and inspector general in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1910<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
Beginning in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1881<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and for the rest of his career, he taught at the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>University of Paris<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> (the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Sorbonne<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>). He was initially appointed as the maître de conférences d'analyse (associate professor of analysis) (<tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Sageret<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1911<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>). Eventually, he held the chairs of Physical and Experimental Mechanics, Mathematical Physics and Theory of Probability, and Celestial Mechanics and Astronomy.
Also in that same year, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> married Miss <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poulain d'Andecy<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. Together they had four children: <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Jeanne<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (born <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1887<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>), <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Yvonne<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (born <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1889<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>), <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Henriette<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (born <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1891<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>), and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Léon<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (born <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1893<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>).
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1887<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, at the young age of <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>3<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>2, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was elected to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>French Academy of Sciences<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. He became its president in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1906<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, and was elected to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Académie française<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1909<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1887<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> he won <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Oscar II, King of Sweden<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>'s mathematical competition for a resolution of the three-body problem concerning the free motion of multiple orbiting bodies. (See section below).
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1893<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> joined the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>French Bureau des Longitudes<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, which engaged him in the synchronisation of time around the world. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1897<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> backed an unsuccessful proposal for the decimalisation of circular measure, and hence time and longitude (see <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Galison<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2003<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>). It was this post which led him to consider the question of establishing international time zones and the synchronisation of time between bodies in relative motion. (See section below).
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1899<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, and again more successfully in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1904<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he intervened in the trials of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Alfred Dreyfus<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. He attacked the spurious scientific claims of some of the evidence brought against <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Dreyfus<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, who was a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Jewish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> officer in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>French army<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> charged with treason by fellow colleagues.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1912<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> underwent surgery for a prostate problem and subsequently died from an embolism on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>17 July 1912<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Paris<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. He was 58 years of age. He is buried in the <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> family vault in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Cemetery of Montparnasse<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Paris<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.
A former <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>French<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> Minister of Education, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Claude Allègre<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, has recently (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2004<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) proposed that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> be reburied in the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Panthéon<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Paris<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, which is reserved for <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>French<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> citizens only of the highest honour.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> had two notable doctoral students at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Paris<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Louis Bachelier<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1900<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Dimitrie Pompeiu<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1905<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>).
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> made many contributions to different fields of pure and applied mathematics such as: celestial mechanics, fluid mechanics, optics, electricity, telegraphy, capillarity, elasticity, thermodynamics, potential theory, quantum theory, theory of relativity and physical cosmology.
He was also a populariser of mathematics and physics and wrote several books for the lay public.
Among the specific topics he contributed to are the following:.
The problem of finding the general solution to the motion of more than two orbiting bodies in the solar system had eluded mathematicians since <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Newton<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s time. This was known originally as the three-body problem and later the n-body problem, where n is any number of more than two orbiting bodies. The n-body solution was considered very important and challenging at the close of the nineteenth century. Indeed in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1887<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, in honour of his 60th birthday, <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Oscar II, King of Sweden<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, advised by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Gösta Mittag-Leffler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, established a prize for anyone who could find the solution to the problem. The announcement was quite specific:
In case the problem could not be solved, any other important contribution to classical mechanics would then be considered to be prizeworthy. The prize was finally awarded to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, even though he did not solve the original problem. One of the judges, the distinguished <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Karl Weierstrass<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, said, "This work cannot indeed be considered as furnishing the complete solution of the question proposed, but that it is nevertheless of such importance that its publication will inaugurate a new era in the history of celestial mechanics." (The first version of his contribution even contained a serious error; for details see the article by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Diacu<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>). The version finally printed contained many important ideas which led to the theory of chaos. The problem as stated originally was finally solved by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Karl F. Sundman<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> for n&#160; =&#160; <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>3<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1912<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and was generalised to the case of n&#160; > &#160; <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>3<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> bodies by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Qiudong Wang<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> in the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1990<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>s.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s work at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Bureau des Longitudes<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> on establishing international time zones led him to consider how clocks at rest on the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Earth<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, which would be moving at different speeds relative to absolute space (or the "luminiferous aether"), could be synchronised. At the same time <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Dutch<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> theorist <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hendrik Lorentz<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was developing <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Maxwell's theory<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> into a theory of the motion of charged particles ("electrons" or "ions"), and their interaction with radiation. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1895<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lorentz<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> had introduced an auxiliary quantity (without physical interpretation) called "local time" and introduced the hypothesis of length contraction to explain the failure of optical and electrical experiments to detect motion relative to the aether (see <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>MichelsonMorley experiment<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>). <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was a constant interpreter (and sometimes friendly critic) of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lorentz<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s theory. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> as a philosopher was interested in the "deeper meaning". Thus he interpreted <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lorentz<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s theory and in so doing he came up with many insights that are now associated with special relativity. In <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>The Measure of Time<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1898<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>), <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> said, " A little reflection is sufficient to understand that all these affirmations have by themselves no meaning. They can have one only as the result of a convention." He also argued that scientists have to set the constancy of the speed of light as a postulate to give physical theories the simplest form. Based on these assumptions he discussed in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1900<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lorentz<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s "wonderful invention" of local time and remarked that it arose when moving clocks are synchronised by exchanging light signals assumed to travel with the same speed in both directions in a moving frame.
He discussed the "principle of relative motion" in two papers in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1900<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and named it the principle of relativity in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1904<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, according to which no physical experiment can discriminate between a state of uniform motion and a state of rest. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1905<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> wrote to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lorentz<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> about <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lorentz<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s paper of <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1904<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, which <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> described as a "paper of supreme importance." In this letter he pointed out an error <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lorentz<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> had made when he had applied his transformation to one of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Maxwell's equations<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, that for charge-occupied space, and also questioned the time dilation factor given by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lorentz<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. In a second letter to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lorentz<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> gave his own reason why <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lorentz<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s time dilation factor was indeed correct after all: it was necessary to make the <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lorentz<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> transformation form a group and gave what is now known as the relativistic velocity-addition law. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> later delivered a paper at the meeting of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Academy of Sciences<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Paris<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>5 June 1905<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> in which these issues were addressed. In the published version of that he wrote:
and showed that the arbitrary function must be unity for all (<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lorentz<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> had set by a different argument) to make the transformations form a group. In an enlarged version of the paper that appeared in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1906<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> pointed out that the combination is invariant. He noted that a <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lorentz<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> transformation is merely a rotation in four-dimensional space about the origin by introducing as a fourth imaginary coordinate, and he used an early form of four-vectors. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> expressed a disinterest in a four-dimensional reformulation of his new mechanics in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1907<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, because in his opinion the translation of physics into the language of four-dimensional geometry would entail too much effort for limited profit. So it was <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hermann Minkowski<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> who worked out the consequences of this notion in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1907<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
Like before, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1900<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) discovered a relation between mass and electromagnetic energy. While studying the conflict between the action/reaction principle and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lorentz<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> ether theory, he tried to determine whether the center of gravity still moves with a uniform velocity when electromagnetic fields are included. He noticed that the action/reaction principle does not hold for matter alone, but that the electromagnetic field has its own momentum. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> concluded that the electromagnetic field energy of an electromagnetic wave behaves like a fictitious fluid ("fluide fictif") with a mass density of E/c2. If the center of mass frame is defined by both the mass of matter and the mass of the fictitious fluid, and if the fictitious fluid is indestructibleit's neither created or destroyedthen the motion of the center of mass frame remains uniform. But electromagnetic energy can be converted into other forms of energy. So <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> assumed that there exists a non-electric energy fluid at each point of space, into which electromagnetic energy can be transformed and which also carries a mass proportional to the energy. In this way, the motion of the center of mass remains uniform. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> said that one should not be too surprised by these assumptions, since they are only mathematical fictions.
However, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s resolution led to a paradox when changing frames: if a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Hertzian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> oscillator radiates in a certain direction, it will suffer a recoil from the inertia of the fictitious fluid. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> performed a <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lorentz<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> boost (to order v/c) to the frame of the moving source. He noted that energy conservation holds in both frames, but that the law of conservation of momentum is violated. This would allow perpetual motion, a notion which he abhorred. The laws of nature would have to be different in the frames of reference, and the relativity principle would not hold. Therefore he argued that also in this case there has to be another compensating mechanism in the ether.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> himself came back to this topic in his <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>St. Louis lecture<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1904<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>). This time (and later also in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1908<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) he rejected the possibility that energy carries mass and criticized the ether solution to compensate the above mentioned problems:.
He also discussed two other unexplained effects: (1) non-conservation of mass implied by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lorentz<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s variable mass , <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Abraham<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s theory of variable mass and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Kaufmann<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s experiments on the mass of fast moving electrons and (2) the non-conservation of energy in the radium experiments of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Madame Curie<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
It was <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Albert Einstein<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s concept of massenergy equivalence (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1905<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) that a body losing energy as radiation or heat was losing mass of amount m&#160; =&#160; E/c2 that resolved <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s paradox, without using any compensating mechanism within the ether. The <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Hertzian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> oscillator loses mass in the emission process, and momentum is conserved in any frame. However, concerning <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s solution of the Center of Gravity problem, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Einstein<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> noted that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s formulation and his own from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1906<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> were mathematically equivalent.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Einstein<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s first paper on relativity was published three months after <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s short paper, but before <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s longer version. It relied on the principle of relativity to derive the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Lorentz transformations<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> and used a similar clock synchronisation procedure (<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Einstein<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> synchronisation) that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1900<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) had described, but was remarkable in that it contained no references at all. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> never acknowledged <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Einstein<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s work on special relativity. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Einstein<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> acknowledged <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> in the text of a lecture in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1921<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> called <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Geometrie und Erfahrung<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> in connection with non-<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Euclidean<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> geometry, but not in connection with special relativity. A few years before his death <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Einstein<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> commented on <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> as being one of the pioneers of relativity, saying "<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lorentz<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> had already recognised that the transformation named after him is essential for the analysis of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Maxwell's equations<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> deepened this insight still further....".
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s work in the development of special relativity is well recognised, though most historians stress that despite many similarities with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Einstein<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s work, the two had very different research agendas and interpretations of the work. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> developed a similar physical interpretation of local time and noticed the connection to signal velocity, but contrary to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Einstein<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> he continued to use the ether-concept in his papers and argued that clocks in the ether show the "true" time, and moving clocks show the local time. So <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> tried to keep the relativity principle in accordance with classical concepts, while <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Einstein<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> developed a mathematically equivalent kinematics based on the new physical concepts of the relativity of space and time. While this is the view of most historians, a minority go much further, such as <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>E.T. Whittaker<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, who held that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lorentz<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> were the true discoverers of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Relativity<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s work habits have been compared to a bee flying from flower to flower. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was interested in the way his mind worked; he studied his habits and gave a talk about his observations in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1908<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> at the Institute of General Psychology in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Paris<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. He linked his way of thinking to how he made several discoveries.
The mathematician <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Darboux<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> claimed he was un intuitif (intuitive), arguing that this is demonstrated by the fact that he worked so often by visual representation. He did not care about being rigorous and disliked logic. He believed that logic was not a way to invent but a way to structure ideas and that logic limits ideas.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s mental organisation was not only interesting to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> himself but also to <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Toulouse<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, a psychologist of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Psychology Laboratory<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>School of Higher Studies<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Paris<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Toulouse<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> wrote a book entitled <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Henri<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1910<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>). In it, he discussed <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s regular schedule:.
These abilities were offset to some extent by his shortcomings:.
In addition, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Toulouse<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> stated that most mathematicians worked from principles already established while <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> started from basic principles each time (<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>O'Connor et al.<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2002<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>).
His method of thinking is well summarised as:.
Habitué à négliger les détails et à ne regarder que les cimes, il passait de l'une à l'autre avec une promptitude surprenante et les faits qu'il découvrait se groupant d'eux-mêmes autour de leur centre étaient instantanément et automatiquement classés dans sa mémoire. (Accustomed to neglecting details and to looking only at mountain tops, he went from one peak to another with surprising rapidity, and the facts he discovered, clustering around their center, were instantly and automatically pigeonholed in his memory.).
<tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Belliver<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>1956<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>).
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was dismayed by Georg Cantor's theory of transfinite numbers, and referred to it as a "disease" from which mathematics would eventually be cured. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> said, "There is no actual infinite; the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Cantorian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>s have forgotten this, and that is why they have fallen into contradiction.".
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> saw mathematical work in economics and finance as peripheral. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1900<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> commented on <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Louis Bachelier<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s thesis "<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>The Theory of Speculation<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>", saying: "<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>M. Bachelier<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> has evidenced an original and precise mind [but] the subject is somewhat remote from those our other candidates are in the habit of treating." (<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Bernstein<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1996<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, pp.&#160; 199200) <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bachelier<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s work explained what was then the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>French<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> government's pricing options on <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>French Bonds<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and anticipated many of the pricing theories in financial markets used today.
Awards.
Named after him.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> had philosophical views opposite to those of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bertrand Russell<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Gottlob Frege<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, who believed that mathematics was a branch of logic. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> strongly disagreed, claiming that intuition was the life of mathematics. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> gives an interesting point of view in his book <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Science and Hypothesis<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>:.
For a superficial observer, scientific truth is beyond the possibility of doubt; the logic of science is infallible, and if the scientists are sometimes mistaken, this is only from their mistaking its rule.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> believed that arithmetic is a synthetic science. He argued that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Peano<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s axioms cannot be proven non-circularly with the principle of induction (<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Murzi<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1998<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>), therefore concluding that arithmetic is a priori synthetic and not analytic. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> then went on to say that mathematics cannot be deduced from logic since it is not analytic. His views were similar to those of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Immanuel Kant<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Kolak<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2001<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Folina<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1992<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>). He strongly opposed <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Cantorian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> set theory, objecting to its use of impredicative definitions.
However, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> did not share <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Kantian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> views in all branches of philosophy and mathematics. For example, in geometry, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> believed that the structure of non-<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Euclidean<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> space can be known analytically. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> held that convention plays an important role in physics. His view (and some later, more extreme versions of it) came to be known as "conventionalism". <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> believed that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Newton<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s first law was not empirical but is a conventional framework assumption for mechanics. He also believed that the geometry of physical space is conventional. He considered examples in which either the geometry of the physical fields or gradients of temperature can be changed, either describing a space as non-<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Euclidean<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> measured by rigid rulers, or as a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Euclidean<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> space where the rulers are expanded or shrunk by a variable heat distribution. However, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> thought that we were so accustomed to <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Euclidean<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> geometry that we would prefer to change the physical laws to save <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Euclidean<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> geometry rather than shift to a non-<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Euclidean<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> physical geometry.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s famous lectures before the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Société de Psychologie<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Paris<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> (published as <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Science and Hypothesis<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>The Value of Science<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, and <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Science and Method<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>) were cited by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Jacques Hadamard<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> as the source for the idea that creativity and invention consist of two mental stages, first random combinations of possible solutions to a problem, followed by a critical evaluation.
Although he most often spoke of a deterministic universe, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> said that the subconscious generation of new possibilities involves chance.
It is certain that the combinations which present themselves to the mind in a kind of sudden illumination after a somewhat prolonged period of unconscious work are generally useful and fruitful combinations... all the combinations are formed as a result of the automatic action of the subliminal ego, but those only which are interesting find their way into the field of consciousness... A few only are harmonious, and consequently at once useful and beautiful, and they will be capable of affecting the geometrician's special sensibility I have been speaking of; which, once aroused, will direct our attention upon them, and will thus give them the opportunity of becoming conscious... In the subliminal ego, on the contrary, there reigns what I would call liberty, if one could give this name to the mere absence of discipline and to disorder born of chance.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s two stagesrandom combinations followed by selectionbecame the basis for <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Daniel Dennett<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s two-stage model of free will.
Popular writings on the philosophy of science:.
On algebraic topology:.
On celestial mechanics:.
On the philosophy of mathematics:.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Albert Einstein<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Alfred North Whitehead<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Aristotle<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Auguste Comte<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Averroes<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Berlin Circle<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Carl<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Gustav Hempel<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>C. D. Broad<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Charles Sanders Peirce<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Dominicus Gundissalinus<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Daniel Dennett<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Epicurians<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Francis Bacon<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Friedrich Schelling<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Galileo Galilei<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Henri<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Herbert Spencer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hugh of Saint Victor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Immanuel Kant<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Imre Lakatos<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Isaac Newton<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>John Dewey<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>John Stuart Mill<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Jürgen Habermas<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Karl Pearson<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Karl Popper<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Karl Theodor Jaspers<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Larry Laudan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Otto Neurath<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Paul Haeberlin<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Paul Feyerabend<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Pierre Duhem<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Pierre Gassendi<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Plato<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>R.B. Braithwaite<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>René Descartes<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Robert Kilwardby<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Roger Bacon<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Rudolf Carnap<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Stephen Toulmin<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Stoicism<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Thomas Hobbes<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Thomas Samuel Kuhn<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Vienna Circle<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>W.V.O. Quine<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Wilhelm Windelband<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Wilhelm Wundt<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>William of Ockham<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>William Whewell<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; more...
Analysis&#160; Analytic-synthetic distinction&#160; A priori and a posteriori&#160; Artificial intelligence&#160; Causality&#160; Commensurability&#160; Construct&#160; Demarcation problem&#160; Explanatory power&#160; Fact&#160; Falsifiability&#160; Ignoramus et ignorabimus&#160; Inductive reasoning&#160; Ingenuity&#160; Inquiry&#160; Models of scientific inquiry&#160; Nature&#160; Objectivity&#160; Observation&#160; Paradigm&#160; Problem of induction&#160; Scientific explanation&#160; Scientific law&#160; Scientific method&#160; Scientific revolution&#160; Scientific theory&#160; Testability&#160; Theory choice&#160; .
Confirmation holism&#160; Coherentism&#160; Contextualism&#160; Conventionalism&#160; Deductive-nomological model&#160; Determinism&#160; Empiricism&#160; Fallibilism&#160; Foundationalism&#160; Hypothetico-deductive model&#160; Infinitism&#160; Instrumentalism&#160; Naturalism&#160; Positivism&#160; Pragmatism&#160; Rationalism&#160; Received view of theories&#160; Reductionism&#160; Semantic view of theories&#160; Scientific realism&#160; Scientism&#160; Scientific anti-realism&#160; Skepticism&#160; Uniformitarianism&#160; Vitalism&#160; Metaphysics.
Epistemology&#160; History and philosophy of science&#160; History of science&#160; History of evolutionary thought&#160; Philosophy of biology&#160; Philosophy of chemistry&#160; Philosophy of physics&#160; Philosophy of mind&#160; Philosophy of artificial intelligence&#160; Philosophy of information&#160; Philosophy of perception&#160; Philosophy of space and time&#160; Philosophy of thermal and statistical physics&#160; Philosophy of social sciences&#160; Philosophy of environment&#160; Philosophy of psychology&#160; Philosophy of technology&#160; Philosophy of computer science&#160; Pseudoscience&#160; Relationship between religion and science&#160; Rhetoric of science&#160; Sociology of scientific knowledge&#160; Criticism of science&#160; Alchemy&#160; more...
.
