<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ercument Kalmık<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1909<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>–<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1971<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) -- <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Turkish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> painter.
Graduated from the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Turkish Fine Arts Academy<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Güzel Sanatlar Akademisi<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>) in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1936<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. He taught at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Technical Teachers School for Girls<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> between <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1939<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1941<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, and later at <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Istanbul Technical University's Faculty of Architecture<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. He lectured at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Berlin Architecture Faculty<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> as a guest professor in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1968<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, and held the chair of basic art education at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Turkish Fine Arts Academy<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Güzel Sanatlar Akademisi<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>) in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1969<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. After <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1941<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> he held exhibitions in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Turkey<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Italy<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Germany<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>USA<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ercüment Kalmık<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> wrote two books: "<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Harmony Systems of Colours<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>" and "<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Tissue in Nature and Art<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>".
The <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Ayse and Ercument Kalmik Foundation<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> has a museum in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Istanbul<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, in the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Ayaspasa district<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Sarayarkasi Sok. 33-35<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>) of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Istanbul<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.
.
