<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Princess Fahrelnissa Zeid<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Arabic<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>: ‎) or F<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>akhr un-nisa<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1901<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Büyükada<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>İstanbul<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Turkey<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> – <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>5 September 1991<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Amman<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Jordan<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>) was a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Turkish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> artist whose work blended the elements of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Islamic<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> and <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Byzantine<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> art from the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>East<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> with abstract and other influences from the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>West<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. She worked in a variety of media such as large oil paintings, collages and stained glass panels.
She married into the <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hashemite<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> royal family of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Iraq<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and is the mother of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Prince Ra'ad<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, the present claimant to the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Iraqi throne<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Fahrelnissa<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was born in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Istanbul<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> on the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>island of Büyükada<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, one of the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Princes' Islands<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, (which are part of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Istanbul<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>), in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1901<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> into a prominent <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Ottoman<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> family. Her father was <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Muhammad Şakir Pasha<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Kabaağaçlı<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>), an <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Ottoman<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> diplomat, brigadier, photographer, and historian, and also the brother of Grand Vizier <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Cevat Pasha<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. Her mother was <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sare Ismet Hanim<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> from <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Crete<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. She was the sister of writer <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Cevat Şakir Kabaağaçlı<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (the <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Fisherman of Halicarnassus<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>/<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Halikarnas Balıkçısı<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>) and painter<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/> Aliye Berger<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. She was also the aunt of artist <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Cem Kabaağaç<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and ceramist <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Fureya Koral<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
She was educated at <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Notre Dame de Sion d'Istanbul<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Pansion Bnagiotti<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. She was then one of the first women to attend the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Fine Arts Academy<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Güzel Sanatlar Akademisi<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>) in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Istanbul<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, later studying at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Académie Ranson<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Paris<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> under <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Roger Bissiere<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Stahlbach<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
Her first marriage was to novelist <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Izzet Melih Devrim<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, one of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Servet-i Fünun<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> writers, in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1920<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. This union produced two children: artist <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Nejad Devrim<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and director/actress <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Şirin Devrim<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. In <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Athens<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>November 1933<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, she married <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Prince Zeid bin Huseyin<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, the ambassador of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Iraq<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> to <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Ankara<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and brother of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>King Faisal I<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. With <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Zeid<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> she had only one child, a son, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Prince Ra'ad<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
Her first one-woman show was held in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Istanbul<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1944<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, followed by exhibitions in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>London<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Paris<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. Her <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>New York<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> début came in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1950<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> when she exhibited a series of large abstract canvases at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Hugo Gallery<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. She went on to participate in almost 50 exhibitions in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Europe<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>U.S.A<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. and the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Middle East<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.
Her husband died in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1970<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, and in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1975<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> she moved to <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Amman<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Jordan<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, where her son <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Raad<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> lived, and where she established the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Fahrelnissa Zeid Institute of Fine Arts<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. She died <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>5 September 1991<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and is buried in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Royal Mausoleum<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Raghdan Palace<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Amman<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Jordan<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.
