<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Giovanni Morelli<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>25 February 1816<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>&#160; – <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>28 February 1891<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) was an <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Italian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> art critic and political figure. As an art historian, he developed the "<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Morellian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>" technique of scholarship, identifying the characteristic "hands" of painters through scrutiny of diagnostic minor details that revealed artists' scarcely conscious shorthand and conventions for portraying, for example, ears.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Morelli<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was trained as a doctor. With his return to <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Italy<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> he acted as a conduit for intellectual life of the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>North<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. His fully developed technique was published as <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Die Werke Italienischer Meister<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, ("<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>The work of the Italian masters<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>"); it appeared under the anagrammatic pseudonym "<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ivan Lermolieff<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>".
The <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Morellian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> method is based on clues offered by trifling details rather than identities of composition and subject matter or other broad treatments that are more likely to be seized upon by students, copyists and imitators. Instead, as <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Carlo Ginzburg<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> analyzed the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Morellian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> method, the art historian operates in the manner of a detective, "each discovering, from clues unnoticed by others, the author in one case of a crime, in the other of a painting". These unconscious traces— in the shorthand for rendering the folds of an ear in secondary figures of a composition, for example— are unlikely to be imitated and, once deciphered, serve as fingerprints do at the scene of the crime. The identity of the artist is expressed most reliably in the details that are least attended to. The <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Morellian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> method has its nearest roots in <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Morelli<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s own discipline of medicine, with its identification of disease through numerous symptoms, each of which may be apparently trivial in itself.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Morelli<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s connoisseurship was developed to a high degree by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bernard Berenson<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, who met <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Morelli<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1890<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. The first generation of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Morellian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> scholars also included <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Gustavo Frizzoni<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Jean Paul Richter<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Adolfo Venturi<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Constance Jocelyn Ffoulkes<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Morellian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> scholarship penetrated the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>English<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> field from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1893<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, with the translation of his master work. The <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Morellian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> technique of connoisseurship was extended to the study of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Attic<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> vase-painters by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>J.D. Beazley<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Michael Roaf<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> to the study of the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Persepolis<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> reliefs, with results that further confirmed its validity. <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Morellian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> recognition of "handling" in undocumented fifteenth and sixteenth-century sculpture, in the hands of scholars like <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>John Pope-Hennessy<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, have resulted in a broad corpus of securely attributed work. At the same time, modern examination of Classical <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Greek<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> sculpture, in the wake of pioneering reassessments by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Brunilde Sismondo Ridgway<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, has also turned away from attributions based on broad aspects of subject and style that are reflected in copies and later <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Roman<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> classicizing pastiche.
The complementary field of document-supported art history traces its origins to the somewhat earlier work of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Joseph Archer Crowe<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Giovanni Battista Cavalcaselle<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
The <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Morellian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> method of finding essence and hidden meaning in details had also a much wider cultural influence. There are references to his work in the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Sherlock Holmes<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> novels by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Arthur Conan Doyle<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and in the works of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sigmund Freud<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. Like <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Morelli<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, both <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Freud<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Doyle<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> had a medical background).
<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Morellian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> method was re-examined by R. Wollheim, "<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Giovanni Morelli<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and the origins of scientific connoisseurship", <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>On Art and the Mind: Essays and Lectures<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1973<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
.
