<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1986<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>- 1st Place in painting. "V Salon <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>UNEAC<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>". <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Sancti Spiritus<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Cuba<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. Painting Award at the Provincial Encounter of Landscape. <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Sancti Spiritus<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Cuba<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1998<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>- 2nd Place at the Painting Contest of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Civil Aeronautics Institute of Cuba<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2002<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>- <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>January 2003<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> Digital Color Artist Of The Month. Digital Consciousness Art Database.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Miguel Cerejido<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> is a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Canadian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> artist, born in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Havana<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Cuba<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>February the 26th of 1960.<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>
Graduated of Drawing and Painting from the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Escuela Nacional de Bellas Artes "San Alejandro"<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1980<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. He finished a Master Degree in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Fine Arts at the Instituto Superior de Arte<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>I.S.A<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.) in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1985<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>; he worked as a professor at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Instituto Superior de Diseño Industrial<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>ISDI<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>), among other art schools in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Cuba<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. He also worked as a specialist at the Centro de "Diseño Ambiental" (Interior Design) in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Havana<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.
He was an active member of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>National Union of Writers and Artists of Cuba<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>UNEAC<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>) since <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1995<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, and of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Art Kollectif Media Foundation Inc. in Ottawa, Canada.<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>
Presently he is a member of Arts <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Ottawa<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> East organization, The <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Council for the Arts<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in Ottawa and The <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Ottawa<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> Art Gallery.
His explorations in painting have always been dealing with the possible nexuses between music and painting as well as, in a very particular way, "Images" that this other artistic discipline produces in his subjectivity.
This theme has been always present in his artistic endeavors from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1983<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> -while still a student at <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>ISA<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>-, encompassing all his carrier and evolving in many different forms, according to levels of perception in the artist's sensibility and to what is he focusing in his approach to the musical phenomenon.
"The nexus between Music and Painting and ways of pictorially representing sound and silence, have been the main subjects of my work as an artist since <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1980<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. This exploration has many facets from attempts at a pictorial representation of sound, to the creation of environments (maybe places or landscapes) that result from the sensations, feelings, states of mind and/or visions generated by Music. My work has gone through different stages from attempts to illustration of specific musical work to explorations of aspects of the musical structure itself. This is, of course, purely subjective. The final phase of production in my work is distinguished by a return to painting, almost forgotten in my eagerness in use it as a medium instead of a purpose, and the utilization of all Ive learned through the years about shaping a pictorial  not musical  art work, which held all the spiritual power of music, as an autonomous entity, without moving it away from its musical sources by means of referent codes, which, I hope, made possible the identification of the theme by the viewer. The resolution of this process continues to evolve as I grow as an artist and a person. It remains my principal challenge." <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Miguel Cerejido<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
