<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Baron Sidney Costantino Sonnino<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>11 March 1847<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>&#160; – <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>24 November 1922<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) was an <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Italian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> politician.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sonnino<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was born in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Pisa<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> to an <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Italian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> father of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Jewish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> heritage (<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Isach Sonnino<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, who converted himself to <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Anglicanism<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>) and a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Welsh<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> mother. He was raised as a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Protestant<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1876<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sonnino<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> traveled to <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Sicily<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Leopoldo Franchetti<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> to conduct a private investigation into the state of Sicilian society. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1877<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, the two men published their research on <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Sicily<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in a substantial two-part report for the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Italian Parliament<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. In the first part <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sonnino<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> analysed the lives of the island's landless peasants. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Leopoldo Franchetti<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s half of the report, Political and Administrative Conditions in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Sicily<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, was an analysis of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Mafia<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in the nineteenth century that is still considered authoritative today. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Franchetti<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> would ultimately influence thinking about the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Mafia<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> more than anyone else until <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Giovanni Falcone<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> over a hundred years later. Political and Administrative Conditions in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Sicily<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> is the first convincing explanation of how the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Mafia<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> came to be.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1878<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sonnino<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> started a newspaper (<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>La Rassegna Settimanale<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>), which changed from weekly economical reviews to daily political issues. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1893<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, after working in several governmental positions, he became finance minister of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Italy<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. He worked in the opposition after the fall of his party from power as a result of the lost <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Battle of Adwa<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. He served twice briefly as Prime Minister, in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1906<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and again from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1909<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1910<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>April 16, 1909<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sonnino<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Wilbur Wright<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> went on a flight at <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Centocelle<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> field, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Rome<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, making <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sonnino<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> one of the earliest of statesmen to fly in an airplane.
After the events in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1914<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sonnino<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was initially supportive to the side of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Germany<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Austria-Hungary<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, but after becoming foreign minister in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>November 1914<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he sided with the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Allied<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> forces, and signed the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Treaty of London<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1915<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Italy<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> consequently declared war on <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Austria-Hungary<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>May 23, 1915<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
When his territorial ambitions towards <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Austria-Hungary<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> were shattered during the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Paris Peace Conference<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, his party lost power again, and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sonnino<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> retired from politics.
<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Cavour<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Ricasoli<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Rattazzi<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Farini<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Minghetti<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>La Marmora<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Ricasoli<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Rattazzi<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Menabrea<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Lanza<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Minghetti<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Depretis<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Cairoli<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Depretis<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Cairoli<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Depretis<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Crispi<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Starabba<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>&#160; Giolitti&#160; Crispi&#160; Starabba&#160; Pelloux&#160; Saracco&#160; Zanardelli&#160; Giolitti&#160; Tittoni&#160; Fortis&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sonnino<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; Giolitti&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sonnino<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; Luzzatti&#160; Giolitti&#160; Salandra&#160; Boselli&#160; Orlando&#160; Nitti&#160; Giolitti&#160; Bonomi&#160; Facta&#160; Mussolini&#160; Badoglio&#160; Bonomi&#160; Parri&#160; De Gasperi.
De Gasperi&#160; Pella&#160; Fanfani&#160; Scelba&#160; Segni&#160; Zoli&#160; Fanfani&#160; Segni&#160; Tambroni&#160; Fanfani&#160; Leone&#160; Moro&#160; Leone&#160; Rumor&#160; Colombo&#160; Andreotti&#160; Rumor&#160; Moro&#160; Andreotti&#160; Cossiga&#160; Forlani&#160; Spadolini&#160; Fanfani&#160; Craxi&#160; Fanfani&#160; Goria&#160; De Mita&#160; Andreotti&#160; Amato&#160; Ciampi&#160; Berlusconi&#160; Dini&#160; Prodi&#160; D'Alema&#160; Amato&#160; Berlusconi&#160; Prodi&#160; Berlusconi&#160; Monti.
