<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Osman Digna<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Arabic<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>: ‎)(c. <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1836<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> – <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1926<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) was a follower of the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Mahdi<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Sudan<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, and hailed from the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Hadendoa tribe<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Beja people<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. His birthplace is unknown; <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Suakin<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> was said to be the town where he was born. When he was called <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Osman Ali<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Osman Digna<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> lived in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Alexandria<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, where he dealt in the selling of slaves. After the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>English<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> forced him to quit his business, he took part in the revolt of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ahmed 'Urabi<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. After the failure of that movement at the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Battle of Tel al-Kebir<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>September 13, 1882<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>), he attached himself to the cause of the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Mahdi<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.
About this time he received the name <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Digna<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> because of the fullness of his beard. He maintained himself at the head of a powerful army around <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Suakin<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and inflicted a severe defeat on <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Baker Pasha<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> near <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Tokar<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, southeast of that place, on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>February 4, 1884<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. Immediately after this victory, however, he was defeated by General <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Graham<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> near <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Tokar<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and at <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Tamanieh<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. As the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Mahdi<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>'s ablest general, he was largely responsible for the fate of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Gordon<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and the loss of the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Sudan<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> to <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and the only foreign commander broke the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>British<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> infantry square in <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Battle of Tamai<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, yet he lost the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Battle<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>December, 1888<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he suffered a bloody reverse at the hands of General <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Grenfell<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> at <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Suakin<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, where he lost an arm. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1899<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> he fought in the last campaign of the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Mahdist<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> forces, whose strength had been broken in the previous year at <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Omdurman<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>January 19, 1900<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he was captured near <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Tokar<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and sent as a prisoner to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Rosetta<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. He served in prison for eight years and after his release remained in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> until his death in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1926<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
