<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Robert John Reed<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lord Reed<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>is a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Scottish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>lawyer and has been a Senator of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>College of Justice<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, a judge of the country's supreme courts, since <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1998<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. He sat as the principal judge in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Commercial Court<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> before being promoted to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Inner House of the Court of Session<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2008<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, and has sat as a substitute judge at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>UK Supreme Court<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. He is an authority on human rights law in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Scotland<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, and serves as one of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>UK<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s ad hoc judges at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>European Court of Human Rights<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Reed<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>was educated at the independent <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>George Watson's College<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Edinburgh<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, and studied at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>School of Law<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Edinburgh<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, taking a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>First Class Honours<tag name="MISC" value="end"/><tag name="MISC" value="start"/>LL.B.<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>and winning a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Vans Dunlop Scholarship<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. He then took a D.Phil. at <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Balliol College<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Oxford<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, and was admitted to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Faculty of Advocates<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1983<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Reed<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>served as <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Standing Junior Counsel<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Scottish Education Department<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1988<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1989<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, and to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Scottish Office Home and Health Department<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1989<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1995<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. He was appointed <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Queen's Counsel<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1995<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, and Advocate Depute in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1996<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. He was appointed a Senator of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>College of Justice<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, a judge of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Court of Session<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>High Court of Justiciary<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, the country's <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Supreme Courts<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1998<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, with the judicial title, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lord Reed<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. He sat initially as a Judge of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Outer House<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, becoming Principal Commercial Judge in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2006<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. He is one of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>United Kingdom<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s ad hoc judges at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>European Court of Human Rights<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, and sat in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Grand Chamber<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>judgements on the appeals of the killers of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>James Bulger<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1999<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. Between <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2002<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>and <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2004<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he was an expert advisor to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>EU/Council of Europe Joint Initiative<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>with <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Turkey<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. He was promoted to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Inner House<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>(<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>First Division<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>) in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2008<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, and appointed to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Privy Council<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. He sat on the Bench of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>UK Supreme Court<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>during the illness of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lord Rodger<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Earlsferry<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, along with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lord Clarke<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, and has been cited by legal commentator <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Joshua Rozenberg<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>as a possible candidate to succeed <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lord Rodger<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. The selection committee was established on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>25 July 2011<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
He has been Chairman of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Franco-British Judicial Co-operation Committee<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>since <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2005<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, and was President of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>EU Forum of Judges for the Environment<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2006<tag name="DATE" value="end"/><tag name="DATE" value="start"/>08<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, now serving as Vice-President. He was a member of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Advisory Board<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>British Institute for International and Comparative Law<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2001<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>06<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, and of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>UN Task Force on Access to Justice<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>since <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2006<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. He is Convener of the charity, Children in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Scotland<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>(<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2006<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>), and Chairman of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Edinburgh<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/><tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Centre for Commercial Law<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>(<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2008<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>). He has been an Honorary Professor of Law at <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Glasgow Caledonian University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>since <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2005<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, and the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>School of Law<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Glasgow<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>since <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2006<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
He married <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Jane Mylne<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1988<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, with whom he has two daughters.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lord Eassie<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lord Reed<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; The <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lord Hardie<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lord Bonomy<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lord Emslie<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
