<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Charles Émile Picard FRS<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>French<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> pronunciation:&#160; ; <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>24 July 1856<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>  <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>11 December 1941<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) was a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>French<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> mathematician. He was elected the fifteenth member to occupy seat 1 of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Académie Française<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1924<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. .
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Picard<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s mathematical papers, textbooks, and many popular writings exhibit an extraordinary range of interests, as well as an impressive mastery of the mathematics of his time. Modern students of complex variables are probably familiar with two of his named theorems. His lesser theorem states that every nonconstant entire function takes every value in the complex plane, with perhaps one exception. His greater theorem states that an analytic function with an essential singularity takes every value infinitely often, with perhaps one exception, in any neighborhood of the singularity. He also made important contributions in the theory of differential equations, including work on <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>PicardVessiot theory<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Painlevé<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> transcendents and his introduction of a kind of symmetry group for a linear differential equation, the <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Picard<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> group. In connection with his work on function theory, he was one of the first mathematicians to use the emerging ideas of algebraic topology. In addition to his path-breaking theoretical work, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Picard<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> also made important contributions to applied mathematics, including the theories of telegraphy and elasticity. His collected papers run to four volumes.
Like his contemporary, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Henri Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Picard<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was much concerned with the training of mathematics, physics, and engineering students. He wrote a classic textbook on analysis and one of the first textbooks on the theory of relativity. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Picard<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s popular writings include biographies of many leading <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>French<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> mathematicians, including his father in law, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Charles Hermite<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Pierre Séguier<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (1635)&#160; · .
