<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Victor Llewellyn Child<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1897<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>–<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1960<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) was a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Canadian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> painter, etcher and newspaper illustrator. A senior pen-and-ink commercial artist at the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Toronto Telegram<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> for much of his professional career, in private life he produced landscapes and portraits in watercolours and oils.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Victor Child<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was born in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Palmerston<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Ontario<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, and studied first in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Toronto<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Ontario College of Art<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> under <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>George Agnew Reid<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Charles Macdonald Manley<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Manly<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>) and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>John William Beatty<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, and later in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>London<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> at <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Heatherley<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>'s. While in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>England<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> during the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>First World War<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> he served with the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Royal Flying Corps<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1920<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> he joined the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Canadian Society of Graphic Art<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, exhibiting his etchings and illustration drawings with the society in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1925<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>–<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1927<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1931<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>–<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1933<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Art Gallery of Toronto<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
The prominent <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Toronto<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> printing firm <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Rous and Mann<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> commissioned his work in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1927<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> for its <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Canadian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> Artists' series <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Christmas<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> cards in company with distinguished painters such as <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Casson<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Harris<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Varley<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Victor Child<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was again among these artists when in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1934<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> he donated work for the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>André Lapine Benefit exhibition<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> chaired by Sir <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Wyly Grier<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. During the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1920<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>s and '<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>30<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>s he was on staff at the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Mail &amp; Emp<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>ire an<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>d Star Weekly<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> newspapers in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Toronto<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> as an illustrator. He married portrait painter <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Marjorie Thompson<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1928<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. Later, in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1940<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he joined the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Telegram<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> and worked there until his death.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Child<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was a decidedly conservative artist. He illustrated religious subjects for the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Salvation Army<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Anglican Church of Canada<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and worked on instructional materials for the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Toronto Board of Education<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. For their annual shows in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1946<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1947<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> he exhibited canvases with the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Ontario Society of Artists<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
Perhaps the most significant moment in <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Canadian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> art history that involved <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Child<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s paintings occurred in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1959<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> when his work was featured in the exhibition Points of View, organized by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Clare Bice<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, curator of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Public Library and Art Museum<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>London<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Ontario<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. At this show, visitors saw the work of the traditionalist/realist <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Ontario Institute of Painters<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, of which <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Child<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> was a founding member in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1958<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, hung beside paintings by the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Canadian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> modernist abstract group <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Painters Eleven<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. Crowds of art enthusiasts, especially at <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Hart House<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Toronto<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> were large. As a popularity contest in critical opinion it was perhaps a draw, but the fame of the abstract artists soon far eclipsed that of the realists. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Victor Child<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> died in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Toronto<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>July 12<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> of the following year.
