Chemistry (career).
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Fritz Haber<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Philipp Lenard<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Georg Ludwig Carius<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hermann Kolbe<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Adolf Lieben<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Carl Friedrich Wilhelm Ludwig<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Viktor Meyer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Friedrich Konrad Beilstein<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Henry Enfield Roscoe<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>John Tyndall<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Edward Frankland<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Dmitri Mendeleev<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Thomas Edward Thorpe<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Robert Wilhelm Eberhard Bunsen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>30 March 1811<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> – <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>16 August 1899<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) was a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>German<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> chemist. He investigated emission spectra of heated elements, and discovered caesium (in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1860<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) and rubidium (in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1861<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Gustav Kirchhoff<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bunsen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> developed several gas-analytical methods, was a pioneer in photochemistry, and did early work in the field of organoarsenic chemistry. With his laboratory assistant, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Peter Desaga<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, he developed the <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bunsen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> burner, an improvement on the laboratory burners then in use. The <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Bunsen–Kirchhoff Award<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> for spectroscopy is named after <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bunsen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Kirchhoff<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Robert Bunsen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was born at <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Göttingen<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1811<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> in what is now the state of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Lower Saxony<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Germany<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, but was then the short-lived <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Kingdom of Westphalia<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>; upon the defeat of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Napoleon<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> three years later it became the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Kingdom of Hanover<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Robert<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was the youngest of four sons of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Göttingen<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s chief librarian and professor of modern philology, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Christian Bunsen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1770<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>–<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1837<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>). Sources disagree on <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Robert Bunsen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s exact birth date. His parish register, as well as two curricula vitae, handwritten by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bunsen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> himself, support the claim that <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>30 March 1811<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> is <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bunsen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s true birth date; however, many later sources cite <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>31 March<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> as the date. According to his biographer <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Georg Lockemann<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bunsen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> himself celebrated his birthday on the 31st in his later years. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lockemann<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> nevertheless regarded the 30th as the correct date.
After attending school in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Holzminden<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bunsen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> matriculated at <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Göttingen<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1828<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and studied chemistry with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Friedrich Stromeyer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> as well as mineralogy with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Johann Friedrich Ludwig Hausmann<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and mathematics with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Carl Friedrich Gauss<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. After obtaining a Ph.D. in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1831<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bunsen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> spent <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1832<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1833<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> traveling in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Germany<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>France<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, and <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Austria<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Friedlieb Runge<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (who discovered aniline and in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1819<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> isolated caffeine), <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Justus von Liebig in Gießen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Eilhard Mitscherlich<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Bonn<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> were among the many scientists he met on his journeys.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1833<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bunsen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> became a lecturer at <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Göttingen<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and began experimental studies of the (in)solubility of metal salts of arsenous acid. His discovery of the use of iron oxide hydrate as a precipitating agent is still today the most effective antidote against arsenic poisoning. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1836<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bunsen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> succeeded <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Friedrich Wöhler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Polytechnic School of Kassel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bunsen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> taught there for three years, and then accepted an associate professorship at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Marburg<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, where he continued his studies on cacodyl derivatives. He was promoted to full professorship in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1841<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bunsen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s work brought him quick and wide acclaim, partly because cacodyl, which is extremely toxic and undergoes spontaneous combustion in dry air, is so difficult to work with. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bunsen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> almost died from arsenic poisoning, and an explosion with cacodyl cost him sight in his right eye. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1841<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bunsen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> created the <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bunsen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> cell battery, using a carbon electrode instead of the expensive platinum electrode used in <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>William Robert Grove<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s electrochemical cell. Early in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1851<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> he accepted a professorship at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Breslau<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, where he taught for three semesters.
In late <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1852<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bunsen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> became the successor of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Leopold Gmelin<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Heidelberg<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. There he used electrolysis to produce pure metals, such as chromium, magnesium, aluminium, manganese, sodium, barium, calcium and lithium. A long collaboration with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Henry Enfield Roscoe<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> began in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1852<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, in which they studied the photochemical formation of hydrogen chloride from hydrogen and chlorine. He discontinued his work with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Roscoe<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1859<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and joined <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Gustav Kirchhoff<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> to study emission spectra of heated elements, a research area called spectrum analysis. For this work, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bunsen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and his laboratory assistant, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Peter Desaga<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, had perfected a special gas burner by <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1855<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, influenced by earlier models. The newer design of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bunsen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Desaga<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, which provided a very hot and clean flame, is now called simply the "<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Bunsen burner<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>".
There had been earlier studies of the characteristic colors of heated elements, but nothing systematic. In the summer of <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1859<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Kirchhoff<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> suggested to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bunsen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> that he try to form prismatic spectra of these colors. By <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>October<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> of that year the two scientists had invented an appropriate instrument, a prototype spectroscope. Using it, they were able to identify the characteristic spectra of sodium, lithium, and potassium. After numerous laborious purifications, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bunsen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> proved that highly pure samples gave unique spectra. In the course of this work, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bunsen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> detected previously unknown new blue spectral emission lines in samples of mineral water from <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Dürkheim<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. He guessed that these lines indicated the existence of an undiscovered chemical element. After careful distillation of forty tons of this water, in the spring of <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1860<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> he was able to isolate 17&#160; grams of a new element. He named the element "caesium", after the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Latin<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> word for deep blue. The following year he discovered rubidium, by a similar process.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bunsen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was one of the most universally admired scientists of his generation. He was a master teacher, devoted to his students, and they were equally devoted to him. At a time of vigorous and often caustic scientific debates, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bunsen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> always conducted himself as a perfect gentleman, maintaining his distance from theoretical disputes. He much preferred to work quietly in his laboratory, continuing to enrich his science with useful discoveries. As a matter of principle he never took out a patent. He never married.
When <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bunsen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> retired at the age of 78, he shifted his work solely to geology and mineralogy, an interest which he had pursued throughout his career. He died in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Heidelberg<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, aged 88.
[[File:its the best]]''''Bold text'.
