<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Angelika Helene Anna Nußberger<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (born <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1 June 1963<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Munich<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>) is a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>German<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> jurist and scholar of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Slavonics<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, and has been the judge representing <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Germany<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>European Court of Human Rights<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> since <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1 January 2011<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. She had previously been Prorector of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Cologne<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and Director of its <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Institute of Eastern European Law<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Nußberger<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was born in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Munich<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, the capital of the southern-<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>German<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> state of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Bavaria<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, and studied <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Slavonics<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Munisch<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1982<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1987<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and Law from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1984<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1989<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> at the same university. She passed the first state legal exam in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Munich<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1989<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and the second in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Heidelberg<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1993<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, being awarded a doctorate that year by the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Würzburg<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> for a dissertation on <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Soviet<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> constitutional law during the transition period.
From <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1993<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2001<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Nußberger<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> worked at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Max Planck Society Institute<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> for <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>International and Comparative Social Law<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, including a period spent at <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Harvard University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1994<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1995<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. From <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2001<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2002<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, she worked as a legal adviser at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Council of Europe<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Strasbourg<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2002<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Nußberger<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> achieved her habilitation, the highest academic qualification a scholar can achieve in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Germany<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, with a thesis on public international law. That year, she was appointed Professor at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Faculty of Law<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Cologne<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, and has led the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Institute for Eastern European Law<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> since then. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2009<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, she was appointed Prorector (deputy to the) of the university with the newly-created position of Prorector for <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Academic Careers, Diversity and Internationality<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. She has been a member of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>International Labour Organization<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Committee of Experts on the Application of Conventions and Recommendations<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> since <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2004<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, and a deputy member of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Council of Europe<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Venice Commission<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> sincce <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2006<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2010<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, she was awarded an honorary doctorate by <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Tbilisi State University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Georgia<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.
On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>22 June 2010<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, she was elected by the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Parliamentary Assembly of the Council of Europe<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> to be the judge representing <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Germany<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>European Court of Human Rights<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, succeeding <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Renate Jaeger<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, previously judge of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Federal Constitutional Court of Germany<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, and took up office on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1 January 2011<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Nußberger<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s research interests focus on the states of Central and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Eastern Europe<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, and encompass the development of constitutional law in these states, and particularly in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Russia<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>; the development of jurisdiction of constitutional courts; the influence of public international law on development of domestic law; international social law; and the post-<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Soviet<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> transformation of the countries' social security systems.
