<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Pierre-Henri Teitgen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>29 May 1908<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> – <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>6 April 1997<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) was a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>French<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> lawyer, professor and politician.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Teitgen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was born in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Rennes<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Brittany<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. Made prisoner of war in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1940<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he played a major role in the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>French Resistance<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>.
Member of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>French Parliament<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1945<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1958<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> for <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Ille-et-Vilaine<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, he was president of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Popular Republican Movement<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Christian Democratic Party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>) from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1952<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1956<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. He was Minister of Information in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1944<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> (one of the founders of the daily <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Le Monde<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>), Minister of Justice in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1945<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>–<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1946<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> (in charge of the purges of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Vichy<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> regime followers and collaborators with <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Nazi Germany<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>), Minister of Defence in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1947<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>–<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1948<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> in <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Robert Schuman<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s government at the time of the insurrectional strikes. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>May 1948<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> he attended the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Congress of The Hague<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> and worked closely with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Robert Schuman<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> in <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Schuman Declaration<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> and the start of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>European Community<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> when he was Minister of Information and Civil service in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1949<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>–<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1950<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. He was later Minister of Overseas in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1950<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. He was member of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Constitutional Committee<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1958<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. He was twice deputy prime minister in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1947<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>–<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1948<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1953<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>–<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1954<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. He was member of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Consultative Constitutional Committee<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1958<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> but became a critic of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>De Gaulle<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s policies. He supported the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Socialist Defferre<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in his attempt as candidate for presidency in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1965<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>September 1976<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he was appointed member of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>European Court of Human Rights<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. He had helped to create the court some 27 years earlier, in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1949<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, outlining its powers and the rights it should protect in a report for the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Consultative Assembly<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Council of Europe<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Teitgen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> died in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Paris<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1997<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Teitgen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s father, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Henri Teitgen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1882<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> - <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1965<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>), was a senior politician of the centre-right <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>MRP<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (party).
.
