<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Andrew Holness<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (born <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>July 21, 1972<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) is the current Prime Minister of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Jamaica<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> since <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>October 23, 2011<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Holness<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> is youngest person to become Prime Minister in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Jamaica<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s history, as well as the country's ninth Prime Minister overall. He previously served as the Minister of Education since <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2007<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Andrew Holness<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> is a graduate of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>St. Catherine High School<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and a graduate of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of the West Indies<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> where he pursued a Master of Science in <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Development Studies<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> and a Bachelor of Science in <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Management Studies<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. He is married to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Juliette<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, they have two children.
He served as Executive Director in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Voluntary Organization for Uplifting Children<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1994<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1996<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and then joined the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Premium Group of Companies<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, acting as a special assistant to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Edward Seaga<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1997<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> he became Member of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Parliament for West Central St. Andrew<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and served as <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Opposition Spokesperson<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> on <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Land and Development<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1999<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2002<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2002<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> he switched portfolio to Housing and then Education in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2005<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. He was sworn in as Minister of Education in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>September 2007<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
He succeeded <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bruce Golding<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> as both leader of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Jamaica Labour Party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and Prime Minister on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>23 October 2011<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> making him the ninth person to hold this office. As Prime Minister, he chose to retain the education portfolio.
On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>December 5, 2011<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Holness<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> called the constitutionally <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2012<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> general election for <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>December 29, 2011<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> as election day.
