<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Osman Hamdi Bey<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1842<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>&#160; – <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>24 February 1910<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) was an <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ottoman<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> statesman, intellectual, art expert and also a prominent and pioneering <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Turkish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> painter. He was also an accomplished archaeologist, and is considered as the pioneer of the museum curator's profession in <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Turkey<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. He was the founder of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Istanbul Archaeology Museums<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>İstanbul Academy of Fine Arts<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (Sanayi-i Nefise Mektebi in Turkish), known today as the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Mimar Sinan University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> of Fine Arts.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Osman Hamdi<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was the son of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>İbrahim Edhem Pasha<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> a former Grand Vizier who was a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Greek<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> boy from the island of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Chios<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> orphaned at a very young age following the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1821<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Greek<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> uprising there. He was adopted by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Kaptan-I Derya Husrev Pasha<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and eventually rising to the ranks of the ruling class of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Ottoman Empire<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Osman Hamdi<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> went to primary school in the popular <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Constantinople<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> quarter of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Beşiktaş<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, after which he studied Law, first in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Istanbul<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1856<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>), and then in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Paris<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1860<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>). However, he decided to pursue his interest in painting instead, left the law program, and trained under <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>French<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> orientalist painters <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Jean-Léon Gérôme<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Gustave Boulanger<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. During his nine-year stay in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Paris<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, the international capital of fine arts in that period, he showed a keen interest for the artistic events of his day. He also met many of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Young Turks<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and though exposed to their liberal ideas, as the son of a loyal Ottoman Paşa, did not participate in their activities.
O<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>sman Hamdi<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> also met his first wife <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Maria<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>French<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> woman, in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Paris<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> when he was a student. After receiving his father's blessings, she accompanied him to <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Constantinople<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> when he returned in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1869<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, where the two got married and had two daughters.
His stay in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Paris<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> was also marked with the first visit ever by an <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Ottoman sultan<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> to <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Europe<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> where <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Abdülaziz<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was invited to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Exposition Universelle<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1867<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Emperor Napoleon III<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
Once back in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Turkey<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, he was sent to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Ottoman<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> province of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Baghdad<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, as part of the administrative team of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Midhat Pasa<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, who would later become an important reformer of the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Tanzimat<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1871<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he returned to <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Constantinople<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, as the vice-director of the Protocol Office of the Palace. During the 1870s, he worked on several assignments in the upper echelons of the Ottoman bureaucracy.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Osman Hamdi<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> exhibited three paintings at the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1867<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Paris Exposition Universelle<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. None seem to have survived today, but their titles were Repose of the Gypsies, Black Sea Soldier Lying in Wait, and Death of the Soldier. An important step in his career was his assignment as the director of the Imperial <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Museum<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (Müze-i Hümayun) in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1881<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. He used his position as museum director to develop the museum and rewrite the antiquities laws and to create nationally sponsored archaeological expeditions. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1882<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he instituted and became director of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Academy of Fine Arts<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, which provided <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Ottomans<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> with training in aesthetics and artistic techniques without leaving the empire. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1884<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he oversaw the promulgation of a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Regulation<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> prohibiting historical artifacts from being smuggled abroad (<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Asar-ı Atîka Nizamnamesi<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>), a giant step in constituting a legal framework of preservation of the antiquities. Representatives or middlemen of 19th century <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>European Powers<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> routinely smuggled artifacts with historical value from within the boundaries of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Ottoman Empire<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (which then comprised the geographies of ancient Greek and Mesopotamian civilizations, among others), often resorting to shadily obtained licenses or bribes, to enrich museums in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>European<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> capitals.
He conducted the first scientific based archaeological researches done by a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Turkish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> team. His digs included sites as varied as the Commagene tomb-sanctuary in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Nemrut Dağı<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in southeastern <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Anatolia<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> (a top tourist's venue in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Turkey<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and a <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>UNESCO<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/><tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/><tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> World Heritage Site today, within the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Adıyaman Province<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>), the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Hekate<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> sanctuary in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Lagina<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in southwestern <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Anatolia<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> (also much visited, and within the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Muğla Province<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> today), and <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Sidon<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Lebanon<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. The sarcophagi he discovered in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Sidon<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> (including the one known as the <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Alexander Sarcophagus<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, although this sarcophagus is thought to contain the remains of a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Persian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> noble who was also the governor of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Babylon<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>.) are considered among the worldwide jewels of archaeological findings. To lodge these, he started building what is today the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Istanbul Archaeology Museum<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1881<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. The museum officially opened in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1891<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> under his directorship.
Throughout his professional career as museum and academy director, Osman Hamdi continued to paint in the style of his teachers, Gérôme and Boulanger.
His <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1906<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> painting, "The Tortoise Trainer", recently broke a record in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Turkey<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> by being sold for the amount of 3.5 million dollars in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>December 2004<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. The painting expresses a sarcastic innuendo on the painter's own view of his style of work compared to those of his collaborators and apprentices, and is also a reference to the historical fact of tortoises having been employed for illuminative and decorative purposes, by placing candles on the shell, in evening outings during the <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Tulip Era<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> in the early 18th century. The painting was acquired by the Suna and İnan <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Kıraç Foundation<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and is currently on display at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Pera Museum<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>İstanbul<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, which was established by this foundation.
Modern researchers have identified the animals portrayed are Testudo graeca ibera, a variety of the Spur-thighed Tortoise. A reproduction of the painting appeared on the cover of the Bibliotheca Herpetologica issue in which the paper about the identification was published.
For another painting by Osman Hamdi Bey, see the article on Milas carpet.
"Kaplumbağa Terbiyecisi", Osman Hamdi Bey'in Romanı, Emre Can, Kapı Yayınları, <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2008<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
"L'ammaestratore di Istanbul", Elettra Stamboulis &amp; Gianluca Costantini, Comma 22, <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2008<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
 Media related to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Osman Hamdi Bey<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> at Wikimedia Commons.
