<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Rebecca Harms<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (born 7 December 1956 in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Hambrock<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Uelzen<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Lower Saxony<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>) is a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>German<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> politician and Member of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>European Parliament<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> for <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Alliance '90/The Greens<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, part of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>European Greens<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. In July 2009 she was elected as co-president of the The <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>GreensEuropean Free Alliance<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> group in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>European parliament<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Harms<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> began her career as an apprentice landscape designer. In 1984 <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Undine von Blottnitz<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> employed her as an assistant after being elected to the European Parliament. She has made numerous documentaries. From 1994 to 2004 she was a member of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Parliament of Lower Saxony<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. From 1998 she was leader of her party. She is a member of the Parteirat of her party.
She lives in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Dickfeitzen<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Wendland<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> region. This region became known nationwide for the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Gorleben<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> atomic waste site.
.
