Proof that e is transcendental.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hermitian<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> adjoint.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Charles Hermite<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>French<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> pronunciation:&#160; ) (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>December 24, 1822<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>  <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>January 14, 1901<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) was a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>French<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> mathematician who did research on number theory, quadratic forms, invariant theory, orthogonal polynomials, elliptic functions, and algebra.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hermite<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> polynomials, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hermite<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> interpolation, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hermite<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> normal form, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hermitian<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> operators, and cubic <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hermite<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> splines are named in his honor. One of his students was <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Henri Poincaré<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
He was the first to prove that e, the base of natural logarithms, is a transcendental number. His methods were later used by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ferdinand von Lindemann<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> to prove that À is transcendental.
In a letter to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Thomas Stieltjes<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1893<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, Hermite famously remarked: "I turn with terror and horror from this lamentable scourge of continuous functions with no derivatives.".
Born at <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Dieuze<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Moselle<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>24 December, 1822<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> he was the son of a salt mine engineer, Ferdinand Hermite. His mother was <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Madeleine Lallemand<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. The family moved to run a drapers business in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Nancy<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1828<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and his father also pursued ambitions as an artist. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Charles<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was the sixth of his parents' seven children.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Charles<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> had a defect in his right foot which meant that from boyhood he moved around with difficulty.
He studied at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Collège de Nancy<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and then, in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Paris<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Collège Henri IV<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Lycée Louis-le-Grand<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hermite<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> wanted to study at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>École Polytechnique<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and he took a year preparing for the examinations and was tutored by <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Catalan<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> between <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1841<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1842<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1842<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> he entered the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>École Polytechnique<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, where he remained as a student for a short time. After one year at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>École Polytechnique<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hermite<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was refused the right to continue his studies because of his disability (<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Ecole Polytechnique<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> is to this day a military academy). He had to fight to regain his place which he won but with strict conditions imposed. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hermite<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> found this unacceptable and decided to leave the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>École Polytechnique<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> without graduating.
As a boy he read some of the writings of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Joseph Louis Lagrange<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> on the solution of numerical equations, and of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Carl Gauss<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> on the theory of numbers. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1842<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, his first original contribution to mathematics, in which he gave a simple proof of the proposition of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Niels Abel<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> concerning the impossibility of obtaining an algebraic solution for the equation of the fifth degree, was published in the "<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Nouvelles Annales de Mathématiques<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>".
A correspondence with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Carl Jacobi<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, begun in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1843<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and continued in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1844<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, led to the insertion, in the complete edition of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Jacobi<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s works, of two articles by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hermite<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, one concerning the extension to <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Abelian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> functions of one of the theorems of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Abel<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> on elliptic functions, and the other concerning the transformation of elliptic functions.
After spending five years working privately towards his degree, in which he befriended eminent mathematicians <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Joseph Bertrand<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Carl Gustav Jacob Jacobi<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Joseph Liouville<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, he took and passed the examinations for the baccalauréat, which he was awarded in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1847<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. He married <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Joseph Bertrand<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s sister, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Louise Bertrand<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1848<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1848<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hermite<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> returned to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>École Polytechnique<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> as répétiteur and examinateur d'admission. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1856<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> he contracted smallpox. Through the influence of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Augustin Cauchy<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and of a nun who nursed him, he resumed the practice of his religion. On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>14 July<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, of that year, he was elected to fill the vacancy created by the death of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Jacques Binet<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Académie des Sciences<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1869<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he succeeded <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Jean-Marie Duhamel<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> as professor of mathematics, both at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>École Polytechnique<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, where he remained until <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1876<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, and in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Faculty of Sciences of Paris<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, which was a post he occupied until his death. From <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1862<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1873<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> he was lecturer at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>École Normale Supérieure<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. Upon his seventieth birthday, on the occasion of his jubilee which was celebrated at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Sorbonne<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> under the auspices of an international committee, he was promoted grand officer of the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Légion d'honneur<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>.
He died in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Paris<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>14 January, 1901<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, aged 78.
As a teacher <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hermite<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was inspiring. His correspondence with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Thomas Stieltjes<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> testifies to the great aid he gave those entering scientific life. His efforts in teaching were directed not towards too rigorous minuteness, but towards exciting admiration for things simple and beautiful. His published courses of lectures have exercised a wide influence. His important original contributions to pure mathematics, published in the leading mathematical journals of the world, dealt chiefly with <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Abelian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> and elliptic functions and the theory of numbers. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1858<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> he solved the equation of the fifth degree by elliptic functions; and in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1873<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> he proved e, the base of the natural system of logarithms, to be transcendental. This last was used by Ferdinand von Lindemann to prove in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1882<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> the same for À.
The following is a list of his works.
.
