<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Toivo Mikael Kivimäki<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>5 June 1886<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> – <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>6 May 1968)<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, J.D., was head of the department of civil law at <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Helsinki University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1931<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>–<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1956<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, Prime Minister of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Finland<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1932<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>–<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1936<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Finland<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s ambassador to <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Berlin<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1940<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>–<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1944<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1946<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Kivimäki<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> together with half-a-dozen other leading politicians were put on "war-responsibility trials" that generally were considered a complete miscarriage of justice, executed under pressure from the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Allied<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> victors in <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>World War II<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, and in breach of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Finland<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s constitutional traditions. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Kivimäki<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was sentenced to five years in prison after being found responsible for the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Continuation War<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (which started with a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Soviet<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> air-attack on <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Finnish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> towns on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>June 25, 1941<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>). After <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Finland<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> signed the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Paris Peace Treaties<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1947<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, and the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Finno–Soviet Agreement of Friendship, Cooperation, and Mutual Assistance<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1948<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, the international situation was deemed somewhat stabilized, and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Kivimäki<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was pardoned. He returned to his career in academia.
As with all politicians connected with the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Continuation War<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Kivimäki<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was for decades seen in a somewhat critical light. During the era of finlandization, many prominent <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Finns<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> expressed themselves cautiously on such subjects in order not to disturb sensitive <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Allied<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> victors of the war; a cautiousness that without doubt influenced <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Finland<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s post-war generation's understanding and views.
However, a post-<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Soviet<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> assessment of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Kivimäki<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> can not avoid the conclusion that he was an extraordinarily successful politician:.
Several individuals and factors were critical for <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Finland<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s survival as a sovereign state and, indeed, as a nation during the rough times of the Winter War and the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Continuation War<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Kivimäki<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> without any doubt occupies a prominent position among these.
