<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Cornect<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> previously served as a town councillor and mayor in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Cape St. George<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. He was also formerly a board member of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Le Gaboteur<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, the province's only <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>French<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>-language newspaper. A fluently bilingual <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Franco-Newfoundlander<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Cornect<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was the first Member of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>House of Assembly<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>MHA<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>) in the province ever to take his oath of office in <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>French<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>.
&#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; .
&#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; .
&#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; .
