<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Muhammad Anwar al-Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Arabic<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>: ‎ , <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/><tag name="MISC" value="start"/> Arabic<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> pronunciation:&#160; ; <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>25 December 1918<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>&#160; – <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>6 October 1981<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) was the third President of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, serving from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>15 October 1970<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> until his assassination by fundamentalist army officers on 6&#160; <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>October 1981<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. In his eleven years as president he changed <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s direction, departing from some of the economic and political principles of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Nasserism<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> by re-instituting the multi-party system, and launching the Infitah economic policy.
He was a senior member of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Free Officers<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> group that overthrew the <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Muhammad Ali Dynasty<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> in the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian Revolution<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> of <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1952<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, and a close confidant of President <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Gamal Abdel Nasser<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, whom he succeeded as President in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1970<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. As president he led <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>October War<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> of <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1973<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to liberate <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> territory occupied by <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, making him a hero in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and, for a time, the wider <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Arab World<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. Afterwards he engaged in negotiations with <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, culminating in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>-<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/><tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/> Peace Treaty<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. This won him the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Nobel Peace Prize<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> but also made him unpopular among some <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Arabs<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, resulting in a temporary suspension of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s membership in the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Arab League<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, and eventually his assassination.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Anwar Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was born on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>25 December 1918<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Mit Abu al-Kum<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>al-Minufiyah<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> to a poor family, one of 13 brothers and sisters. His father was <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, and his mother was <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Sudanese<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. He spent his early childhood under the care of his grandmother, who told him stories revolving around resistance to the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>British<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> occupation and drawing on contemporary history.
During <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>’s childhood, he admired and was influenced greatly by four individuals. The first of his childhood heroes was <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Zahran<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, the alleged hero of the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Denshawai<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> incident, who resisted the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>British<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> occupation in a farmer protest. According to the story, a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>British<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> soldier was killed, and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Zahran<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was the first <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> hanged in retribution. Stories like the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Ballad of Zahran<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> introduced <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> to <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> nationalism, a value he held throughout his life.
The second individual was <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Kemal Ataturk<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, who was the leader of contemporary <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Turkey<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> admired his ability to overthrow the foreign influence and his many social reforms. He also idolized <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mahatma Gandhi<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and his belief of nonviolence when facing injustice. As <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> was under the occupation of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>United Kingdom<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was fascinated by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>’s <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Nazi German army<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> for their quick ability to become a strategic threat to <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Britain<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
He graduated from the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Royal Military Academy<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Cairo<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in 1938 and was appointed in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Signal Corps<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. He entered the army as a second lieutenant and was posted in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Sudan<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Sudan<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> were one country at the time). There, he met <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Gamal Abdel Nasser<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, and along with several other junior officers they formed the secret <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Free Officers Movement<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> committed to freeing <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> from <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>British<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> domination and royal corruption.
During the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Second World War<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> he was imprisoned by the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>British<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> for his efforts to obtain help from the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Axis Powers<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in expelling the occupying <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>British<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> forces. Along with his fellow <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Free Officers<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> participated in the military coup that launched the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian Revolution<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> of <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1952<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> which overthrew <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>King Farouk<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> I on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>23 July<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> of that year. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was assigned to announce the news of the revolution to the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> people over the radio networks.
During the presidency of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Gamal Abdel Nasser<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was appointed Minister of State in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1954<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1959<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he assumed the position of Secretary to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>National Union<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was the President of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>National Assembly<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1960<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>–<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1968<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) and then Vice President and member of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Presidential Council<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1964<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. He was reappointed as Vice President again in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>December 1969<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
Some of the major events of the <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s presidency were his Corrective revolution to consolidate power, the break with the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s long-time ally and aid-giver the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>USSR<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1973<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>October War<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> with <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Camp David peace treaty<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> with <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, the "opening up" (or Infitah) of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s economy, and finally his assassination in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1981<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> succeeded <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Nasser<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> as president after the later's death in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1970<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s presidency was widely expected to be short-lived. Viewing him as having been little more than a puppet of the former president, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Nasser<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s supporters in government settled on <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> as someone they could manipulate easily. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> surprised everyone with a series of astute political moves by which he was able to retain the presidency and emerge as a leader in his own right. On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>15 May 1971<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> announced his <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Corrective Revolution<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, purging the government, political and security establishments of the most ardent <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Nasserists<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> encouraged the emergence of an <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Islamist<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> movement which had been suppressed by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Nasser<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. Believing <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Islamist<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>s to be socially conservative he gave them" considerable cultural and ideological autonomy" in exchange for political support.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1971<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, three years into the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>War of Attrition<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> in the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Suez Canal<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> zone, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> endorsed in a letter the peace proposals of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>UN<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> negotiator <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Gunnar Jarring<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> which seemed to lead to a full peace with <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> on the basis of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s withdrawal to its pre-war borders. This peace initiative failed as neither <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> nor the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>United States of America<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> accepted the terms as discussed then.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> likely perceived that <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s desire to negotiate was directly correlated to how much of a military threat they perceived from <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, which, after the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Six-Day War<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> of <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1967<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, was at an all time low. <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> also viewed the most substantial part of the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> threat as the presence of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Soviet<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> equipment and personnel (in the thousands at this time). It was for those reasons that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> expelled the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Soviet<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> military advisers from <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and proceeded to whip his army into shape for a renewed confrontation with <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. During this time, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> was suffering greatly from economic problems caused by the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Six-Day War<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> and the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Soviet<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> relationship also declined due to their unreliability and refusal of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>’s requests for more military support.
On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>6 October 1973<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, in conjunction with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hafez al-Assad<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Syria<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> launched the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>October War<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, also known as the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Yom Kippur War<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (and less commonly as the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Ramadan War<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>), a surprise attack against the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Israeli<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> forces occupying the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/><tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/> Sinai Peninsula<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Syria<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>n Golan Heights in an attempt to retake the territory captured by <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> six years earlier. The <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Syria<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>n performance in the initial stages of the war (Operation Badr, also known as The Crossing) astonished both <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Arab World<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. The most striking achievement was the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> military's advance approximately 15&#160; km into the occupied <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Sinai Peninsula<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> after penetrating and largely destroying the Bar Lev Line. This line was popularly thought to have been an impregnable defensive chain.
As the war progressed, three divisions of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>i army (IDF) led by General Ariel Sharon had crossed the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Suez Canal<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, trying to encircle first the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> Second Army and when it failed, the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> Third Army. Prompted by an agreement between the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>United States of America<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Soviet<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> allies, the United Nations Security Council passed Resolution 338 on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>22 October 1973<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, calling for an immediate ceasefire. Although agreed upon, the ceasefire was immediately broken. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Alexei Kosygin<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, the Chairman of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>USSR<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> Council of Ministers, cancelled an official meeting with Danish Prime Minister Anker Jørgensen to travel to <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> where he tried to persuade <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> to sign a peace treaty. During Kosygin's two-day long stay it's unknown if he and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> ever met in person. The <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>IDF<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> then continued their drive to encircle the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> army. The encirclement was completed on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>25 October<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, three days after the ceasefire was broken. This development prompted superpower tension, but a second ceasefire was imposed cooperatively on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>October 25<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to end the war. At the conclusion of hostilities, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>i forces were 40 kilometres (25&#160; mi) from Damascus and 101 kilometres (63&#160; mi) from <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Cairo<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.
The initial <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Syria<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>n victories in the war restored popular morale throughout <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Arab World<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and, for many years after, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was known as the "Hero of the Crossing". <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> recognized <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> as a formidable foe, and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s renewed political significance eventually led to regaining and reopening the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Suez Canal<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> through the peace process. His new peace policy led to the conclusion of two agreements on disengagement of forces with the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>i government. The first of these agreements was signed on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>18 January 1974<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, and the second on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>September 4, 1975<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
One major aspect of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s peace policy was to gain some religious support for his efforts. Already during his visit to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>US<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>October<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>–<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>November 1975<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he invited <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Evangelical<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> pastor <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Billy Graham<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> for an official visit, which was held few days following <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s visit. In addition to cultivating relations with <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Evangelical<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> Christians in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>US<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, he also built some cooperation with the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Vatican<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>8 April 1976<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he visited for the first time at the Vatican, and got a message of support from <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Pope Paul VI<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> regarding achieving peace with <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, to include a just solution to the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Palestinian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> issue. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, on his part, extended to the Pope a public invitation to visit <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Cairo<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> also used the media to promote his purposes. In an interview he gave to the Lebanese paper El Hawadeth in early <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>February 1976<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he claimed he had secret commitment from the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>US<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> government to put pressure on the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>i government for a major withdrawal in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Sinai<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Golan Heights<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. This statement caused some concern to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>i government, but <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Kissinger<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> denied such a promise was ever made.
On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>November 20, 1977<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> became the first <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Arab<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> leader to visit <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> officially when he met with <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>i Prime Minister <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Menachem Begin<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, and spoke before the <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Knesset<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Jerusalem<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> about his views on how to achieve a comprehensive peace to the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Arab<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>-<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>i conflict, which included the full implementation of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>UN<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> Resolutions 242 and 338. He said during his visit that he hopes "that we can keep the momentum in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Geneva<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, and may <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>God<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> guide the steps of Premier Begin and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Knesset<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, because there is a great need for hard and drastic decision.".
The <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>–<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>i <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Peace Treaty<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> was signed by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Anwar Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>i Prime Minister <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Menachem Begin<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Washington, DC<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>United States<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>26 March 1979<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, following the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Camp David Accords<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1978<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>), a series of meetings between <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> facilitated by <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>US<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> President <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Jimmy Carter<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. Both <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and Begin were awarded the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Nobel Peace Prize<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> for creating the treaty. In his acceptance speech, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> referred to the long awaited peace desired by both <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Arabs<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>is.
“Let us put an end to wars, let us reshape life on the solid basis of equity and truth. And it is this call, which reflected the will of the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> people, of the great majority of the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Arab<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>i peoples, and indeed of millions of men, women, and children around the world that you are today honoring. And these hundreds of millions will judge to what extent every responsible leader in the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Middle East<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> has responded to the hopes of mankind”.
The main features of the agreement were the mutual recognition of each country by the other, the cessation of the state of war that had existed since the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1948<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Arab<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>-<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>i War, and the complete withdrawal by <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> of its armed forces and civilians from the rest of the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Sinai Peninsula<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> which <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> had captured during the 1967 <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Six-Day War<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>.
The agreement also provided for the free passage of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>i ships through the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Suez Canal<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and recognition of the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Strait of Tiran<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Gulf of Aqaba<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> as international waterways. The agreement notably made <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> the first <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Arab<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> country to officially recognize <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. The peace agreement between <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> has remained in effect since the treaty was signed.
The treaty, which gained wide support among <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>s, was extremely unpopular in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Arab World<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and the wider <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Muslim World<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. His predecessor <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Nasser<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> had made <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> an icon of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Arab<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> nationalism, an ideology that appeared to be sidelined by an <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> orientation following the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1973<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> war (see <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>). By signing the accords, many non-<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/><tag name="MISC" value="start"/> Arabs<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> believed <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> had put <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s interests ahead of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Arab<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> unity, betraying <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Nasser<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s pan-<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Arab<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>ism, and destroyed the vision of a united "<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Arab<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> front" and elimination of the "Zionist Entity". However, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> realized early on that peace is the solution. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s shift towards a strategic relationship with the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>US<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> was also seen as a betrayal by many <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Arabs<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. In the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>United States<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> his peace moves gained him popularity among some <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Evangelical<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> circles. He was awarded the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Prince of Peace Award<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Pat Robertson<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1979<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Arab League<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> expelled <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in the wake of the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>–<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> peace agreement, and the League moved its headquarters from <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Cairo<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> to <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Tunis<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Arab League<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> member states believed in the elimination of the "Zionist Entity" and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> at that time. It was not until <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1989<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> that the League re-admitted <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> as a member and returned its headquarters to <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Cairo<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. As part of the peace deal, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> withdrew from the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Sinai peninsula<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in phases, returning the entire area to <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>25 April 1982<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
Before the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Islamic revolution<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Iran<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1979<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, the relationship between <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Cairo<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Tehran<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> was so friendly that the Shah of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Iran<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mohammad Reza Pahlavi<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, called <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> his "dear brother". The Shah's first wife was <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Princess Fawzia<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. She was the eldest daughter of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sultan Fuad I<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Sudan<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> (later <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>King Fuad I<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>) and his second wife <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Nazli Sabri<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
After his overthrow, the deposed Shah spent the last days of his life in exile in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. When the Shah died, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> ordered that he be given a state funeral and be interred at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Al-Rifa'i Mosque<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Cairo<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, the resting place of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Khedive Isma'il Pasha<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, his mother <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Khushyar Hanim<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, and numerous other members of the royal family of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Sudan<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.
The last years of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s presidency were marked by turmoil and there were several allegations of corruption against him and his family. It has been said that he was assassinated "at the peak" of his unpopularity. In January <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1977<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, a series of '<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Bread Riots<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>' protested <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s economic liberalization and specifically a government decree lifting price controls on basic necessities like bread. The riots lasted for two days and included hundreds of thousands in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Cairo<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. 120 buses and hundreds of buildings were destroyed in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Cairo<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> alone. The riots ended with the deployment of the army and the re-institution of the subsidies/price controls.
Earlier in his reign <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Islamists<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> had benefited from the `rectification revolution` and the release from prison of activists jailed under <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Nasser<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> but <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Sinai treaty<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> with <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> enraged <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Islamists<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, particularly the radical <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/><tag name="MISC" value="start"/> Islamic Jihad<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. According to interviews and information gathered by journalist <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lawrence Wright<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, the group was recruiting military officers and accumulating weapons, waiting for the right moment to launch "a complete overthrow of the existing order" in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. Chief strategist of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>El-Jihad<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> was <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Abbud al-Zumar<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, a colonel in the military intelligence whose "plan was to kill the main leaders of the country, capture the headquarters of the army and State Security, the telephone exchange building, and of course the radio and television building, where news of the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Islamic revolution<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> would then be broadcast, unleashing - he expected - a popular uprising against secular authority all over the country.".
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>February 1981<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> authorities were alerted to <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>El-Jihad<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s plan by the arrest of an operative carrying crucial information. In September, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> ordered a highly unpopular roundup of more than 1500 people, including many Jihad members, but also the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Coptic<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> Pope and other <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Coptic<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> clergy, intellectuals and activists of all ideological stripes. All non-government press was banned as well. The round up missed a Jihad cell in the military led by Lieutenant <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Khalid Islambouli<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, who succeeded in assassinating <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Anwar Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> that October.
According to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Tala'at Qasim<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, ex-head of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Gama'a Islamiyya<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> interviewed in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Middle East<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> Report, it was not <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Islamic Jihad<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> but the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Islamic Group<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>al-Gama'a al-Islamiyya<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>) that organized the assassination and recruited the assassin (<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Islambouli<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>). Members of the Group's '<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Maglis el-Shura<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>' ('<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Consultative Council<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>') – headed by the famed 'blind shaykh' – were arrested two weeks before the killing, but they did not disclose the existing plans and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Islambouli<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> succeeded in assassinating <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>6 October 1981<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was assassinated during the annual victory parade held in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Cairo<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> to celebrate <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s crossing of the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Suez Canal<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. In addition to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, eleven others were killed, including the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Cuban<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> ambassador, an <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Omani<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> general, and a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Coptic<tag name="MISC" value="end"/><tag name="MISC" value="start"/> Orthodox<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> bishop. Twenty-eight were wounded, including Vice President <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hosni Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Irish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> Defence Minister <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>James Tully<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, and four <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>US<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> military liaison officers.
The assassination squad was led by Lieutenant <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Khalid Islambouli<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> after a fatwā approving the assassination had been obtained from <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Omar Abdel-Rahman<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Islambouli<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was tried, found guilty, sentenced to death, and executed in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>April 1982<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was succeeded by his vice president <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hosni Mubarak<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, whose hand was injured during the attack. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s funeral was attended by a record number of dignitaries from around the world, including a rare simultaneous attendance by three former <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>US<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> presidents: Gerald Ford, Jimmy Carter and Richard Nixon. <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Sudan<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>'s President <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Gaafar Nimeiry<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was the only <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Arab<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> head of state to attend the funeral. Only 3 of 24 states in the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Arab League<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> – <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Oman<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Somalia<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Sudan<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> – sent representatives at all. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was buried in the unknown soldier memorial in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Cairo<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, across the street from the stand where he was assassinated.
Over three hundred <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Islamic<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> radicals were indicted in the trial of assassin <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Khalid Islambouli<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, including <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ayman al-Zawahiri<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Omar Abdel-Rahman<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Abd al-Hamid Kishk<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. The trial was covered by the international press and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Zawahiri<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s knowledge of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>English<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> made him the de facto spokesman for the defendants. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Zawahiri<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was released from prison in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1984<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. His brother <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mohammed al-Zawahri<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was imprisoned from 2000 until <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>17 March 2011<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, and then re-arrested on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>20 March 2011<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Abboud al-Zomor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Tareq al-Zomor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, two <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Islamic Jihad<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> leaders imprisoned in connected with the assassination, were released on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>11 March 2011<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
Despite these facts, the nephew of the late president, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Talaat al-Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, claimed that the assassination was an international conspiracy. On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>31 October 2006<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he was sentenced to a year in prison for defaming <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s armed forces, less than a month after he gave the interview accusing <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> generals of masterminding his uncle's assassination. In an interview with a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Saudi<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> television channel, he also claimed both the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>United States<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> were involved: "No one from the special personal protection group of the late president fired a single shot during the killing, and not one of them has been put on trial, " he said.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was married twice. He was first married to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ehsan Madi<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> at age 22, and divorced her several years later, just 17 days after the birth of their third daughter, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Camelia<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. He then married <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Jehan Raouf<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (later known as <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Jehan Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>), who was only 15 years and 9 months at the time, on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>29 May 1949<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. They had one son, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Gamal<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, and three daughters: <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lobna<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Noha<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Jehan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (named after her mother). It was <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Gamal<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> who represented his father when he was presented, posthumously, with the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Presidential Medal of Freedom<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1984<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> by <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>U.S.<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> President <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ronald Reagan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Jehan Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2001<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> recipient of the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Pearl S. Buck Award<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Anwar Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s autobiography, In Search of Identity, was published in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>US<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1977<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. Currently, Mrs. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> is an Associate Resident Scholar at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Maryland<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> where The <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Anwar Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Chair for Development and Peace<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> was established and fully endowed in 1997 to honor her husband's legacy. A nephew, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Talaat Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, was imprisoned in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>October 2006<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> for accusing the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> military of complicity in his uncle's assassination.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1983<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, a miniseries based on the life of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Anwar Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, aired on <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>US<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> television with <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Oscar<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>-winning actor <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Louis Gossett<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, Jr. in the title role. The film was promptly banned by the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> government, as were all other movies produced and distributed by <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Columbia Pictures<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, over allegations of historical inaccuracies. A civil lawsuit was brought by <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s artists' and film unions against <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Columbia Pictures<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and the film's directors, producers and scriptwriters before a court in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Cairo<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, but was dismissed; the court held that "the distortions and the slanders found in the film took place outside the country, " so that "the crimes were not within the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> courts' jurisdiction.".
Western authors attributed the film's poor reception to racism — <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Gossett<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> being <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>African<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>American<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> — in the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> government or <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in general. Either way, one Western source wrote that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s portrayal by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Gossett<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> "bothered race-conscious <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptians<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> and wouldn't have pleased [the deceased] <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>." – The two-part series earned <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Gossett<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> an <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Emmy<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> nomination in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>United States<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. The first <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> depiction of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s life came in 2001, when <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Ayyam El Sadat<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>English<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>: <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Days of Sadat<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>) was released in <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> cinemas. This movie, by contrast, was a major success in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, and was hailed as <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ahmad Zaki<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s greatest performance to date.
The <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>BBC<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> also produced a film on <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> called "<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Why Was Cairo Calm?<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>". Film director and blogger <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Adam Curtis<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> summarizes the documentary: "It tells the story of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s presidency - and how the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>American<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> TV networks created a fantasy vision of him as a wise democratic leader who had opened up the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> economy to the free market, and was loved by his people for making peace for <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. As the film shows - this was a complete illusion.".
 .
 .
1 served as acting President of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egypt<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> for eight days following <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadat<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s assassination.
2 currently acting head of state, as Chairman of ruling <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Supreme Council of the Armed Forces<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, following .
&#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; .
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Jimmy Carter<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (1976)&#160; ·