<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Aimo Kaarlo Cajander<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>4 April 1879<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Uusikaupunki<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>  <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>21 January 1943<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Helsinki<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>) was, outside of botany, best known as Prime Minister of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Finland<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> up to the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Winter War<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>.
He was a professor of Forestry <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1911<tag name="DATE" value="end"/><tag name="DATE" value="start"/>34<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>; director-general for <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Finland<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Forest and Park Service<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1934<tag name="DATE" value="end"/><tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1943<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>; prime minister in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1922<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1924<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, and <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1937<tag name="DATE" value="end"/><tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1939<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>; chairman of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>National Progressive Party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1933<tag name="DATE" value="end"/><tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1943<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>; and Member of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Parliament<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
Forest researcher <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Cajander<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> came to politics in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1922<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> when president <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ståhlberg<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> asked him to take office of prime minister. He had not earlier participated actively in politics. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ståhlberg<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> invited him as prime minister second time in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>January 1924<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Cajander<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s short-lived cabinets were merely caretakers before parliamentary elections.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Cajander<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> joined in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1927<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>National Progressive Party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1928<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> he was chose as minister of defence. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Cajander<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was elected to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Parliament<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1929<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. When <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Kyösti Kallio<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was elected President in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1937<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Cajander<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was asked as the chairman of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>National Progressive Party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> to form majority government. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Cajander<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> formed a coalition government of the two largest party in the parliament - <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Social Democrats<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Agrarian League<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Cajander<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was idealist who did not believe yet in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>August 1939<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> that <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Soviet Union<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> would attack <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Finland<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. Partly for this reason the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Finnish Army<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> was forced to the fight inadequately equipped.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Cajander<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s name is remembered for "Model <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Cajander<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>", the fashion of many <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Finnish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> soldiers in <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Winter War<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>: the army was poorly equipped, so conscripts were given a utility belt, an emblem to be attached to the hat  to comply with the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Hague Conventions<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>  and, hopefully, a rifle. Otherwise, they had to use their own clothes and equipment.
