<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Adolf Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>German<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>: &#160; ; <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>20 April 1889<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> – <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>30 April 1945<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) was an <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Austrian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>-born <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>German<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> politician and the leader of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>National Socialist German Workers Party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>German<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>: (<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>NSDAP<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>), commonly referred to as the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Nazi Party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>). He was from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1933<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1945<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, and head of state (as Führer und Reichskanzler) from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1934<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1945<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> is most commonly associated with the rise of fascism in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Europe<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>World War II<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, and the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Holocaust<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>.
A decorated veteran of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>World War I<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> joined the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>German Workers' Party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, precursor of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Nazi Party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1919<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, and became leader of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>NSDAP<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1921<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1923<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> attempted a coup d'état, known as the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Beer Hall Putsch<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, at the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Bürgerbräukeller<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> beer hall in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Munich<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. The failed coup resulted in <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s imprisonment, during which time he wrote his memoir, <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Mein Kampf<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>My Struggle<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>). After his release in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1924<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> gained support by promoting <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Pan-Germanism<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, antisemitism, and anti-communism with charismatic oratory and propaganda. He was appointed chancellor in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1933<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and transformed the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Weimar Republic<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> into the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Third Reich<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, a single-party dictatorship based on the totalitarian and autocratic ideology of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Nazism<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s avowed aim was to establish a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>New Order<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> of absolute <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Nazi German<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> hegemony in continental <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Europe<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. His foreign and domestic policies had the goal of seizing <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Lebensraum<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (living space) for the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Germanic<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> people. He oversaw the rearmament of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Germany<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and the invasion of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Poland<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> by the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Wehrmacht<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>September 1939<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, which led to the outbreak of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>World War II<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Europe<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
Under <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s direction, <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>German<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> forces and their <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>European<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> allies at one point occupied most of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Europe<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>North Africa<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. These gains were reversed in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1945<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> when the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Allied<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> armies defeated the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>German<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> army. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s policies resulted in the systematic annihilation of as many as 17&#160; million civilians, including an estimated six million <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Jews<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> targeted in the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Holocaust<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> and between 500, 000 and 1, 500, 000 <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Roma<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
In the final days of the war, during the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Battle of Berlin<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1945<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> married <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Eva Braun<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, his long-time mistress. To avoid capture by the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Red Army<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, the two committed suicide less than two days later on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>30 April 1945<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and their corpses were burned.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s father, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Alois Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, was an illegitimate child of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Maria Anna Schicklgruber<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. The name of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Alois<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>' father was not listed on <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Alois<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>' birth certificate, and he bore his mother's surname. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1842<tag name="DATE" value="end"/><tag name="PERSON" value="start"/> Johann Georg Hiedler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> married <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Maria<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, and in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1876<tag name="DATE" value="end"/><tag name="PERSON" value="start"/> Johann<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> testified before a notary and three witnesses that he was the father of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Alois<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. Despite his testimony, the question of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Alois<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>' paternity remained unresolved. For example, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hans Frank<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> suggested the existence of letters claiming that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Alois<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>' mother was employed as a housekeeper for a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Jewish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> family in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Graz<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and that the family's 19-year-old son, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Leopold Frankenberger<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, had fathered <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Alois<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. This claim remained unsupported, however, and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Frank<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> himself did not believe that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> had <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Jewish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> ancestry. The suggestion that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Alois<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>' father was <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Jewish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> was also doubted by historians in the 1990s, and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ian Kershaw<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> dismisses the <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Frankenberger<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> story as a "smear" by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s adversaries. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Kershaw<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> noted that there was no evidence for a family named <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Frankenberger<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> living in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Graz<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> at the time. All <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Jews<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> had been expelled from <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Graz<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>15th century<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and were not allowed to return until the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1860<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>s, well after <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Alois<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>' birth.
At age 39 <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Alois<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> assumed the surname <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, also spelled as <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hiedler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hüttler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, or <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Huettler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>; the name was probably regularized to its final spelling by a clerk. The origin of the name is either "one who lives in a hut" (Standard <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>German<tag name="MISC" value="end"/><tag name="PERSON" value="start"/> Hütte<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>), "shepherd" (Standard <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>German<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> hüten "to guard", <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>English<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> heed), or is from the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Slavic<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> words <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hidlar<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hidlarcek<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Adolf Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was born on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>20 April 1889<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> at around 6:30&#160; pm at the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Gasthof zum Pommer<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, an inn in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Ranshofen<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, a village annexed in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1938<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to the municipality of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Braunau am Inn<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Upper Austria<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. He was the third of five children to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Alois Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Klara Pölzl<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Adolf<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s older siblings&#160; – <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Gustav<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ida<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; – died in infancy.
At the age of three, his family moved to <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Kapuzinerstrasse 5<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Passau<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Germany<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. There, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> would acquire a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Bavarian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> dialect of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Austro-Bavarian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> rather than an <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Austrian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> dialect.[page&#160; needed] In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1894<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, the family relocated to <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Leonding<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> near <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Linz<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, and in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>June 1895<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Alois<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> retired to a small landholding at <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Hafeld<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> near <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Lambach<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, where he tried his hand at farming and beekeeping. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Adolf<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> attended school in nearby <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Fischlham<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, and in his free time, he played "<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Cowboys and Indians<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>". <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> became fixated on warfare after finding a picture book about the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Franco-Prussian War<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> among his father's belongings.[page&#160; needed].
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Alois Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s farming efforts at <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Hafeld<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> ended in failure, and in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1897<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> the family moved to <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Lambach<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> attended a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Catholic<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> school in an <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>11th-century<tag name="DATE" value="end"/><tag name="MISC" value="start"/> Benedictine<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> cloister, the walls of which bore engravings and crests that contained the symbol of the swastika. In <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Lambach<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> the eight-year-old <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> sang in the church choir, took singing lessons, and even entertained thoughts of one day becoming a priest. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1898<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, the family returned permanently to <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Leonding<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.
On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2 February 1900<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s younger brother, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Edmund<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, died of measles, deeply affecting <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. He changed from being confident and outgoing and an excellent student, to a morose, detached, and sullen boy who constantly fought his father and his teachers.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was attached to his mother, but he had a troubled relationship with his father, who frequently beat him, especially in the years after <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Alois<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>' retirement and failed farming efforts. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Alois<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was an <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Austrian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> customs official and wanted his son to follow in his footsteps, which caused much conflict between them.[page&#160; needed] Ignoring his son's desire to attend a classical high school and become an artist, in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>September 1900<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> his father sent <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Adolf<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Realschule<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Linz<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, a technical high school of about 300 students. (This was the same high school that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Adolf Eichmann<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> would attend some 17 years later.) <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> rebelled against this decision, and in <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Mein Kampf<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> revealed that he did poorly in school, hoping that once his father saw "what little progress I was making at the technical school he would let me devote myself to my dream.".
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> became obsessed with <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>German Nationalism<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> as a way to rebel against his father who proudly served the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Austrian Government<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. While many <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Austrians<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> —still considered themselves "<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Germans<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>"— they remained loyal to <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Austria<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. Whereas <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> only expressed his loyalty to <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Germany<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and his friends used the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>German<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> greeting "Heil", and sang the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>German<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> anthem "Deutschland Über Alles" instead of the.[page&#160; needed].
After <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Alois<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>' sudden death on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>3 January 1903<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s behaviour at the technical school became even more disruptive, and he was asked to leave in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1904<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. He enrolled at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Realschule<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Steyr<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>September 1904<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, but upon completing his second year, he and his friends went out for a night of celebration and drinking. While drunk, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> tore up his school certificate and used the pieces as toilet paper. The stained certificate was brought to the attention of the school's principal, who "... gave him such a dressing-down that the boy was reduced to shivering jelly. It was probably the most painful and humiliating experience of his life." <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was expelled, never to return to school again.
At age15, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> took part in his <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>First Communion<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> on <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Whitsunday<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>22 May 1904<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Linz Cathedral<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. His sponsor was <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Emanuel Lugert<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, a friend of his late father.
From <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1905<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> lived a bohemian life in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Vienna<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> with financial support from orphan's benefits and his mother. He was rejected twice by the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Academy of Fine Arts Vienna<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1907<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>–<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1908<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>), because of his "unfitness for painting", and was recommended to study architecture. However, he lacked the academic credentials required for architecture school:.
In a few days I myself knew that I should some day become an architect. To be sure, it was an incredibly hard road; for the studies I had neglected out of spite at the <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Realschule<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> were sorely needed. One could not attend the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Academy<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s architectural school without having attended the building school at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Technik<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, and the latter required a high-school degree. I had none of all this. The fulfillment of my artistic dream seemed physically impossible.
On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>21 December 1907<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s mother died of breast cancer at age 47; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was devastated, and carried the grief from her death with him for the rest of his life. Ordered by a court in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Linz<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> gave his share of the orphan's benefits to his sister <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Paula<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, and at the age of 21, he inherited money from an aunt. He struggled as a painter in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Vienna<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, copying scenes from postcards and selling his paintings to merchants and tourists. After being rejected a second time by the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Academy of Arts<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> ran out of money. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1909<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he lived in a shelter for the homeless, and by <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1910<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he had settled into a house for poor working men on <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Meldemannstraße<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. Another resident of the shelter, Reinhold Hanisch, sold <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s paintings, until the two men had a bitter falling-out.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> stated that he first became an antisemite in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Vienna<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, which had a large <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Jewish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> community, including <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Orthodox<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Jews<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> who had fled the pogroms in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Russia<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s account has been questioned by his childhood friend, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>August Kubizek<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, who suggested that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was already a "confirmed antisemite" before he left <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Linz<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> for <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Vienna<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. This prompted <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Brigitte Hamann<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> to write that "of all those early witnesses who can be taken seriously <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Kubizek<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> is the only one to portray young <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> as an anti-Semite and precisely in this respect he is not trustworthy." <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Vienna<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> at the time of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s residence was a hotbed of traditional religious prejudice and 19th-century racism. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> may have been influenced by the occult writings of the antisemite <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lanz von Liebenfels<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> in his magazine <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Ostara<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>; he probably read the publication, although it is uncertain to what degree he was influenced by von <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Liebenfels<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>' writings.
There were few <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Jews<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Linz<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. In the course of centuries their outward appearance had become <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Europeanised<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> and had taken on a human look; in fact, I even took them for <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Germans<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. The absurdity of this idea did not dawn on me because I saw no distinguishing feature but the strange religion. The fact that they had, as I believed, been persecuted on this account sometimes almost turned my distaste at unfavorable remarks about them into horror. Thus far I did not so much as suspect the existence of an organized opposition to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Jews<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. Then I came to <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Vienna<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. Once, as I was strolling through the Inner City, I suddenly encountered an apparition in a black caftan and black hair locks. Is this a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Jew<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>? was my first thought. For, to be sure, they had not looked like that in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Linz<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. I observed the man furtively and cautiously, but the longer I stared at this foreign face, scrutinizing feature for feature, the more my first question assumed a new form: Is this a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>German<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>?.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Martin Luther<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>On the Jews and Their Lies<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> may have also shaped <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s views. In <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Mein Kampf<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, he refers to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Martin Luther<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> as a great warrior, a true statesman, and a great reformer, alongside <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Richard Wagner<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Frederick the Great<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Wilhelm Röpke<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> concluded that "without any question, <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Lutheranism<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> influenced the political, spiritual and social history of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Germany<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in a way that, after careful consideration of everything, can be described only as fateful.".
At the time, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> apparently did not act on his views. He was a frequent dinner guest in a wealthy <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Jewish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> house, and he interacted well with <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Jewish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> merchants who tried to sell his paintings.[page&#160; needed].
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> received the final part of his father's estate in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>May 1913<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and moved to <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Munich<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. He wrote in <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Mein Kampf<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> that he had always longed to live in a "real" <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>German<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> city. In <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Munich<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, he further pursued his interest in architecture and studied the political writings of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Houston Stewart Chamberlain<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. Moving to <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Munich<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> helped <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> avoid military service in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Austria<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, but the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Munich<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> police—in cooperation with the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Austrian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> authorities—eventually arrested him for dodging the draft. After a physical exam and a contrite plea, he was deemed unfit for service and allowed to return to <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Munich<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. When <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Germany<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> entered <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>World War I<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>August 1914<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he successfully petitioned <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>King Ludwig III<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Bavaria<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> for permission to serve in a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Bavarian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> regiment, and enlisted in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Bavarian army<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> served as a runner on the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Western Front<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>France<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Belgium<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Bavarian Reserve Infantry Regiment<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> 16. He experienced major combat, including the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>First Battle of Ypres<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Battle of the Somme<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Battle of Arras<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, and the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Battle of Passchendaele<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was twice decorated for bravery, receiving the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Iron Cross<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, Second Class, in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1914<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Iron Cross<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, First Class on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>4 August 1918<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. He also received the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Wound Badge<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s First Class <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Iron Cross<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> was recommended by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hugo Gutmann<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, and although the latter decoration was rarely awarded to a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Gefreiter<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, it may be explained by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s post at regimental headquarters, where he had more frequent interactions with senior officers than other soldiers of similar rank. The regimental staff, however, thought <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> lacked leadership skills, and he was never promoted.
While serving at regimental headquarters <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> pursued his artwork, drawing cartoons and instructions for an army newspaper. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>October 1916<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> he was wounded either in the groin area or the left thigh when a shell exploded in the dispatch runners' dugout during the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Battle of the Somme<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> spent almost two months in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Red Cross<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> hospital at <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Beelitz<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. He returned to his regiment on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>5 March 1917<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>15 October 1918<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and several comrades were temporarily blinded by a mustard gas attack. It has been suggested that he may have suffered from conversion disorder, then known as "hysteria".[page&#160; needed] He was hospitalized in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Pasewalk<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> became embittered over the collapse of the war effort. It was during this time that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s ideological development began to firmly take shape. Some scholars, notably <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lucy Dawidowicz<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, argue that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s intention to exterminate <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Europe<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Jews<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> was fully formed at this time.[page&#160; needed].
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> described the war as "the greatest of all experiences" and he was praised by his commanding officers for his bravery. The experience made <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> a passionate <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>German<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> patriot, and he was shocked by <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Germany<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s capitulation in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>November 1918<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. Like many other <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>German<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> nationalists, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> believed in the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Dolchstoßlegende<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (Stab-in-the-back legend), which claimed that the army, "undefeated in the field, " had been "stabbed in the back" on the home front by civilian leaders and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Marxists<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, later dubbed the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>November Criminals<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
The <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Treaty of Versailles<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> stipulated that <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Germany<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> must relinquish several of its territories and demilitarise the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Rhineland<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. The treaty imposed economic sanctions and levied reparations on the country. Many <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Germans<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> perceived the treaty—especially Article 231, which declared <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Germany<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> responsible for the war—as a humiliation. The economic, social, and political conditions effected in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Germany<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> were later exploited by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
After <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>World War I<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> remained in the army and returned to <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Munich<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, where he attended the funeral march for the murdered <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Bavarian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> prime minister <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Kurt Eisner<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. After the suppression of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Bavarian Soviet Republic<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, he took part in "national thinking" courses organized by the Education and Propaganda Department of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Bavarian Reichswehr<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> under Captain <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Karl Mayr<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>July 1919<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was appointed <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Verbindungsmann<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (intelligence agent) of an <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Aufklärungskommando<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (reconnaissance commando) of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Reichswehr<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, both to influence other soldiers and to infiltrate the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>German<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Workers' Party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>DAP<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>). While he studied the activities of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>DAP<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> became impressed with founder <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Anton Drexler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s antisemitic, nationalist, anti-capitalist and anti-Marxist ideas. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Drexler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> favoured a strong active government, a "non-<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Jewish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>" version of socialism, and solidarity among all members of society. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Drexler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was impressed with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s oratory skills and invited him to join the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>DAP<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> accepted on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>12 September 1919<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, becoming the party's 55th member.
At the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>DAP<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> met <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Dietrich Eckart<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, one of its early founders and a member of the occult <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Thule Society<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Eckart<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> became <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s mentor, exchanging ideas with him and introducing <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> to a wide range of people in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Munich<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> society. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> thanked <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Eckart<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and paid tribute to him in the second volume of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Mein Kampf<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. To increase the party's appeal, the party changed its name to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Nationalsozialistische Deutsche Arbeiterpartei<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>National Socialist German Workers Party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> – <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>NSDAP<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>). <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> designed the party's banner of a swastika in a white circle on a red background.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was discharged from the army in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>March 1920<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, and he began working full time for the party. By early <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1921<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> had become highly effective at speaking to large audiences. In February <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1921<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> spoke to a crowd of over six thousand in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Munich<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. To publicize the meeting, two truckloads of party supporters drove around town waving swastika flags and throwing leaflets. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> soon gained notoriety for his rowdy, polemic speeches against the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Treaty of Versailles<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, rival politicians, and especially against <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Marxists<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Jews<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. At the time, the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>NSDAP<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> was centred in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Munich<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, a major hotbed of anti-government <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>German<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> nationalists determined to crush <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Marxism<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> and undermine the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Weimar Republic<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>June 1921<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, while <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Eckart<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> were on a fundraising trip to <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Berlin<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, a mutiny broke out within the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>DAP<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Munich<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. Members of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>DAP<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s executive committee, some of whom considered <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> to be too overbearing, wanted to merge with the rival <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>German<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Socialist Party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>DSP<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>). <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> returned to <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Munich<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>11 July 1921<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and angrily tendered his resignation from the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>DAP<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. The committee members then realized that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s resignation would mean the end of the party. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> announced he would rejoin on the condition that he would replace <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Drexler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> as party chairman, and that the party headquarters would remain in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Munich<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. The committee agreed to his demands; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> rejoined the party as member 3, 680. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> still faced some opposition within the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>DAP<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>: <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hermann Esser<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and his allies printed 3, 000 copies of a pamphlet attacking <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> as a traitor to the party. In the following days, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> spoke to several packed houses and defended himself to thunderous applause. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s strategy proved successful: at a general <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>DAP<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> membership meeting, he was granted absolute powers as party chairman, with only one nay vote cast.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s vitriolic beer hall speeches began attracting regular audiences. Early followers included <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Rudolf Hess<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, the former air force pilot <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hermann Göring<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, and the army captain <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ernst Röhm<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. The latter became head of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Nazis<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>' paramilitary organization, the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Sturmabteilung<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>SA<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, "Storm Division"), which protected meetings and frequently attacked political opponents. A critical influence on his thinking during this period was the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Aufbau Vereinigung<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, [page&#160; needed] a conspiratorial group formed of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>White Russian<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> exiles and early <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>National Socialists<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. The group, financed with funds channeled from wealthy industrialists like <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Henry Ford<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, introduced him to the idea of a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Jewish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> conspiracy, linking international finance with Bolshevism. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> attracted the attention of local business interests. He was accepted into influential circles of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Munich<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> society and became associated with wartime General <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Erich Ludendorff<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
Encouraged by his new support, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> recruited <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ludendorff<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> for an attempted coup known as the "Beer Hall Putsch" (also known as the "<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> Putsch" or "<tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Munich<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> Putsch"). The <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Nazi Party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> had used <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Italy<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s fascists as an example for its appearance and policies, and in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1923<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> wanted to emulate <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Benito Mussolini<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s "March on <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Rome<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>" by staging his own "Campaign in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Berlin<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>". <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ludendorff<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> sought support of Staatskommissar (state commissioner) <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Gustav von Kahr<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Bavaria<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>'s de facto ruler. However, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Kahr<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> along with Police Chief <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hans Ritter von Seisser<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (Seißer) and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Reichswehr<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> General <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Otto von Lossow<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> wanted to install a nationalist dictatorship without <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> wanted to seize a critical moment for successful popular agitation and support. So on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>8 November 1923<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>SA<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> stormed a public meeting of 3, 000 people, organized by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Kahr<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> in the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Bürgerbräukeller<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, a large beer hall in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Munich<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> interrupted <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Kahr<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s speech and announced that the national revolution had begun, declaring the formation of a new government with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ludendorff<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. With his hand gun drawn, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> demanded the support of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Kahr<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Seisser<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lossow<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s forces initially succeeded at occupying the local <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Reichswehr<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and police headquarters; however, neither the army nor the state police joined forces with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Kahr<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and his consorts quickly withdrew their support and fled to join the opposition to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. The following day, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and his followers marched from the beer hall to the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Bavarian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> War Ministry to overthrow the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Bavarian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> government on their "March on <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Berlin<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>", but the police dispersed them. and four police officers were killed in the failed coup.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> fled to the home of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ernst Hanfstaengl<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, and by some accounts contemplated suicide, but this state of mind has been disputed by others. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was depressed but calm when he was found and arrested by the police on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>11 November 1923<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. He was tried for high treason before the special People's Court in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Munich<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, and Alfred Rosenberg became temporary leader of the NS<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>DAP<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. During his trial, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was given almost unlimited time to speak, and his popularity soared as he voiced nationalistic sentiments in his defence speech. His trial began on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>26 February 1924<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1 April 1924<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was sentenced to five years' imprisonment at Landsberg Prison. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> received friendly treatment from the guards and received a lot of mail from supporters. The <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Bavarian Supreme Court<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> soon issued a pardon and he was released from jail on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>20 December 1924<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, against the state prosecutor's objections. Including time on remand, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> had been imprisoned for just over one year for the attempted coup.

