<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Dermot Christopher Ahern<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (born <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>20 April 1955<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) is a former <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Irish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/><tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/> Fianna Fáil<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> politician. He was a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Teachta Dála<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>TD<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>) for the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Louth constituency<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1987<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2011<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. He also served as Minister for <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Social, Community and Family Affairs<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1997<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>–<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2002<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>), <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Minister for Communications<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Marine and Natural Resources<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2002–04<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>), <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Minister for Foreign Affairs<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2004–08<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Minister for Justice and Law Reform<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2008–11<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>).
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Dermot Ahern<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was born in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Dundalk<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>County Louth<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>1955<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. He was educated at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Marist College<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Dundalk<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and later attended <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University College Dublin<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. Afterwards he studied at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Law Society of Ireland<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and was admitted as a solicitor. He then started a successful career as a solicitor.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ahern<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> currently lives in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Blackrock<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> near <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Dundalk<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> with his wife and their two children. His pastimes include playing golf and windsurfing. He is a former <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Ulster<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> windsurfing champion. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ahern<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> is a former chairman of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Rock Celtic soccer club<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and was also treasurer of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Dundalk F.C. Supporter's Club<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ahern<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was born into a family that had no association with party politics. He became involved in politics at a young age and became a member of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Louth County Council<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1979<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> as a <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Fianna Fáil<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> representative. He served on that authority until <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1991<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ahern<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was elected to <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Dáil Éireann<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> at the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1987<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> general election and has retained his seat ever since. The following year he was appointed assistant government chief whip by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taoiseach Charles Haughey<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
Three years later in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1991<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Minister for Finance<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Albert Reynolds<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, failed in his attempt to oust <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Haughey<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> as leader. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ahern<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, who supported <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Haughey<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, was rewarded with the post of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Minister of State<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Department of the Taoiseach<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> with special responsibility as <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Government Chief Whip<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Minister of State at the Department of Defence<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>February 1992<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Haughey<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was forced to resign and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Albert Reynolds<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> became party leader and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taoiseach<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ahern<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> became a backbencher for the entire duration of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Fianna Fáil-Labour Party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> government.
In late <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1994<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bertie Ahern<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (no relation) succeeded <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Albert Reynolds<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> as leader of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Fianna Fáil<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ahern<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> once again returned to the senior ranks of the party becoming chief whip. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1997<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> he was sent to <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>London<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> to check out rumours that another senior party member, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ray Burke<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, had received a payment from Joseph Murphy. The claim was denied and Burke was appointed Minister for Foreign Affairs two days later following the return to power of Fianna Fáil. Burke later served a jail sentence for corruption including the Murphy bribe. Ahern has since taken a stance on the issue of political corruption in Ireland publicly calling for an outright ban of corporate and trade union donations to political parties.
In more recent times <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ahern<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s religious beliefs have been questioned especially in the way that his religious ideology may influence his political standpoint.
Following the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1997<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> general election a <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Fianna Fáil-Progressive Democrats<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> came to power and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ahern<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was appointed <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Minister for Community, Social and Family Affairs<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. As <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Social Affairs Minister<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ahern<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> also introduced the largest social welfare and pension increases in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Irish<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> history. He also achieved pension rights for Irish people who had emigrated from <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Ireland<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> prior to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1953<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
Following the return of the government at the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2002<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> general election <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ahern<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was appointed <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Minister for Communications, Marine and Natural Resources<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. In this post he was critical of the main telecommunications provider <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Eircom<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. His Department introduced a system of Policy Directions to the telecoms regulator mandating, amongst other things, <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Flat Rate Internet Access<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. It also devised the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Republic of Ireland<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>'s Br<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>oadband Action Plan<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> which entailed the government building an alternative fibre infractructure and co-location facilities. He sanctioned a reform package for public service broadcasting in Ireland and introduced a Charter for <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Ireland<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>'s national broadcaster <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>RTÉ<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. His Department introduced a programme to provide free broadband internet access to schools. He secured <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>EU<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> recognition and protection of the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Irish Box<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, an area of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Irish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> territorial waters out of bounds to <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Spanish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> and <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Portuguese<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> fishermen.
Following a cabinet reshuffle in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2004<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ahern<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> became <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Minister for Foreign Affairs<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, the first Louth TD to hold that position since <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Frank Aiken<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> in the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1960<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>s. Shortly into his tenure in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>April 2005<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ahern<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was appointed one of four special envoys for <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>United Nations<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> reform by the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>UN Secretary General<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Kofi Annan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ahern<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> spoke of the 'Third Phase' in <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Irish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> foreign policy which he calls "Active Neutrality". This is a vision of non-aligned Ireland taking up its international responsibilities by acting as a bridge between the developed and developing world, and by acting as a world leader in conflict and disasters. In this regard he took an extremely outspoken line on the crisis in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Darfur<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, calling on the international community to 'wake up to the reality of rape, murder and destruction in the region. More recently <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Ahern<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> has announced the establishment of an <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Irish Volunteer Corps<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and a <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Rapid Response Corps<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> which would harness existing expertise amongst the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Irish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> public to assist in the developing world. He has stated that, in foreign policy terms, 'the single greatest, economic, environmental, geopolitical issue now facing us is climate change.'.
As <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Foreign Minister<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ahern<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was heavily involved in the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Northern Ireland<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> peace process. Like many others in his party he describes himself as a republican and stated at the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2006<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Seán Moylan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> commemoration in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Cork<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> that "as an <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Irish Republican<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> my main personal and political goal is to live to see the unity of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Ireland<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.".
As <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Foreign Minister<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> he led a campaign to secure a path to permanent residency for the 25, 000 to 50, 000 undocumented <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Irish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> citizens resident in the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>United States<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. He also introduced free passports for <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Irish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> senior citizens and had called for a comprehensive ban on the use of cluster munitions. Ahern was the first government Minister to call for a constitutional referendum on the issues arising from the supreme court decision on statutory rape, five months before it became government policy.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ahern<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was appointed <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> on the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>7 May 2008<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> by the new <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taoiseach Brian Cowen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>29 April 2009<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, Ahern proposed a controversial amendment to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Defamation Bill<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> adding the crime of blasphemy to the statute books.
The amendment was passed in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Dáil<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> on the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>9 July 2009<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> with only an hour of the debate set aside for the bill, and was then narrowly passed by the Seanad the next day by walk-through vote, after being defeated in the initial electronic vote. This amendment has been criticized by many within the public sphere, free speech campaigners and some ministers of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>European Union<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> member states. As of <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2010<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, the law is in effect.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ahern<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> is responsible for the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Civil Partnership Bill<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2009<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> published on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>26 June 2009<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
He received the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Murphy Report<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> into child sexual abuse in the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Dublin<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> Diocese in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>June 2009<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. Most of the report was published on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>26 November 2009<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> of that year, though parts were not, due to names that were undergoing prosecution.
As part of a reshuffle in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>March 2010<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, the Equality affairs section of the department was moved to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Department of Community, Equality and Gaeltacht Affairs<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ahern<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> said that in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>March 2010<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> he will propose to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Cabinet<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> a constitutional amendment deleting the constitutional prohibition on blasphemy when the children's rights amendment comes up. The children's rights amendment is set to be put to referendum in the Autumn <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2010<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ahern<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was opposed to a stand-alone referendum that would have cost €3 or €4 million, his spokesman added. At the time, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ahern<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> wrote in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>The Irish Times<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>: “My intention is to remove the possibility of prison sentences and private prosecutions for blasphemy, currently provided for in <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Irish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> law. The only credible alternative to this move is a blasphemy referendum, which I consider, in the current circumstances, a costly and unwarranted diversion.”.
On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>15 November 2010<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he described as 'fiction' the speculation that <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Ireland<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> was about to seek financial aid from the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>European Union<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. He told RTÉ's <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>The Week in Politics<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> that 'nothing is going on at the direction of Government in relation to this.' On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>21 November 2010<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, the <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taoiseach Brian Cowen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> confirmed that <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Ireland<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> had formally requested financial support from the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>European Union<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>European Financial Stability Facility<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>International Monetary Fund<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>30 November 2010<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he announced he will not contest his <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Dáil<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> seat at the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2011<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> general election, as he has rheumatoid arthritis, and said it was a "painful medical condition necessitating heavy medication". He retires to a combined annual ministerial and TD's pension of €128, 300. He resigned as <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Minister for Justice and Law Reform<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>19 January 2011<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
During the debate on decriminalisation of Homosexuality in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Dáil<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1993<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he agreed with a statement by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Fine Gael TD<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Brendan McGahon<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> which reads: "Homosexuality is a departure from normality and while homosexuals deserve our compassion they do not deserve our tolerance" and who described homosexuals as being "like lefthand drivers driving on the right-hand side of the road.".
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ahern<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> himself added: "Will we eventually see the day in this country when, as has happened in the USA, homosexuals will seek the right to adopt children? We should think seriously about this possibility". Following his appointment as Minister responsible for equality, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ahern<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> has refused to be drawn on this matter and has not given an answer as to whether he still holds those opinions.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ahern<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was responsible for introducing legislation recognising civil partnerships for same-sex couples. He declared the legislation (<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Civil Partnership and Certain Rights and Obligations of Cohabitants Act<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2010<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>), which passed into law in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>July 2010<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> as "one of the most important pieces of civil rights legislation to be enacted since independence." .
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Dermot Ahern<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> denied claims that he had made representations to former Minister for <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Justice Michael McDowell<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> on behalf of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Michael McKevitt<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, who has been convicted of directing terrorism. He said that had merely forwarded an email from <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McKevitts<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>' wife, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bernadette Sands McKevitt<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, who was a constituent in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2004<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Dermot Ahern<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>David Andrews<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ray Burke<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Brian Cowen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Noel Dempsey<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Síle de Valera<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Frank Fahey<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mary Harney<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Charlie McCreevy<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Jim McDaid<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Micheál Martin<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>John O'Donoghue<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mary O'Rourke<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Michael Smith<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Joe Walsh<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Michael Woods<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Dermot Ahern<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Séamus Brennan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Brian Cowen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mary Coughlan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Martin Cullen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Noel Dempsey<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mary Hanafin<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mary Harney<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Charlie McCreevy<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Michael McDowell<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Micheál Martin<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Éamon Ó Cuív<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>John O'Donoghue<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Willie O'Dea<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Dick Roche<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Michael Smith<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Joe Walsh<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Dermot Ahern<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Séamus Brennan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Brian Cowen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mary Coughlan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Martin Cullen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Noel Dempsey<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>John Gormley<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mary Hanafin<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mary Harney<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Brian Lenihan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Micheál Martin<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Éamon Ó Cuív<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Willie O'Dea<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Eamon Ryan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Dermot Ahern<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Pat Carey<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mary Coughlan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Martin Cullen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Noel Dempsey<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>John Gormley<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mary Hanafin<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mary Harney<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Tony Killeen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Brian Lenihan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Micheál Martin<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Éamon Ó Cuív<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Willie O'Dea<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Batt O'Keeffe<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Eamon Ryan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Brendan Smith<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
