Dr. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Horace Chang<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> is the current Minister of Water, Environment and Housing in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Jamaica<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. Dr. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Chang<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> is married with two children and was born on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>10 November 1952<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. He attended <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>New Roads All-age School<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Cornwall College<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, where he served as head boy and 6th Form Association President, and the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of the West Indies<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
He has served as Vice President for <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Young Jamaica<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, Deputy General Secretary for the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Jamaica Labour Party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Parliamentary Secretary<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in the Ministry of Health, Chairman and Deputy Leader for <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Area Council Four<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, Member of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Parliament-North West St. James<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and Opposition Spokesman on Housing and Innercity Development.
As a private doctor and part of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Doctor's Hospital Group<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Horace<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> has developed a large and successful prepayment Health Plan for low Income Workers.
.
