<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Karl Ferdinand Herzfeld<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>February 24, 1892<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Vienna<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Austria<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>  <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>June 3, 1978<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Washington, DC<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>U.S<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.) was an <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Austrian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>-<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>American<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> physicist.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Herzfeld<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was born in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Vienna<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> during the reign of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Habsburgs<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> over the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Austro-Hungarian Empire<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. His father was a physician and ordinarius professor of obstetrics and gynecology at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Vienna<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. His mother, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Camilla<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> née <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Herzog<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, was the daughter of a newspaper publisher and sister of the organic chemist <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>R. O. Herzog<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1902<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, when <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Herzfeld<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was 10 years old, he was enrolled in the private <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Gymnasium Schottengymnasium<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, which was run by the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Benedictine Order<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Roman Catholic Church<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and had its name derived from the fact that the founders came from <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Scotland<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. He attended this school until <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1910<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, when he began attending the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Vienna<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> to study physics and chemistry. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1912<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he took courses at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Zurich<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Eidgenössische Technische Hochschule Zürich<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>ETH<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>). It was in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Zurich<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> he met <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Otto Stern<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, who was at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>ETH<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Herzfeld<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> later credited conversations with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Stern<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> for his deeper understanding of thermodynamics. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1913<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he went to study at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Göttingen<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, after which <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Herzfeld<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> returned to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Vienna<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, and was granted his doctorate in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1914<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, under <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Friedrich Hasenöhrl<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, who had become Director of the Institute for Theoretical Physics, upon the suicide of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ludwig Boltzmann<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1906<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Herzfeld<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>s doctoral thesis applied statistical mechanics to a gas of free electrons as a model for a theory of metals. By the time he received his doctorate, he already had published six scientific papers. In one of them, he attempted to derive a model of the hydrogen atom. This paper was published in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1912<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, shortly before <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Niels Bohr<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> submitted his first paper on the <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bohr<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> model of the hydrogen atom.
Upon receipt of his doctorate, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Herzfeld<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> volunteered for service in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Austro-Hungarian Army<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>World War I<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> broke out shortly thereafter and he served until <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1918<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, rising to the rank of first lieutenant. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Herzfeld<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>s thesis advisor <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hasenöhrl<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was called to serve during <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>World War I<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> and was killed at the front. During his tenure in the military, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Herzfeld<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> published six papers on statistical mechanics applied to problems in physics and chemistry, especially to the structure of matter  gases, liquids, and solids.
After the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>War<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Herzfeld<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> returned to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Vienna<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, however, the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> was in such dire financial straits that he moved to <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Munich<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1919<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, with the intent of studying analytical chemistry and getting a job in the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>German<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> chemical industry, which had a highly respected reputation. First, he was an assistant at the physico-chemical laboratory of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Kasimir Fajans<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> at <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Ludwig Maximilians University of Munich<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>LMU<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>). However, once there, he found the challenge of theoretical physics more to his liking. He became Privatdozent for theoretical physics and physical chemistry at <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>LMU<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, and therefore was much more associated with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Arnold Sommerfeld<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, who was ordinarius professor for theoretical physics and Director of the Institute for Theoretical Physics  a prominent organization for the study of atomic and molecular structure. From <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1925<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, until he left <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>LMU<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1926<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he was extraordinarius professor of theoretical physics. During this time, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Linus Pauling<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> did postdoctoral studies with him, and he was the thesis advisor for <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Walter Heitler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, who got his doctorate in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1926<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1925<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Herzfeld<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> published his book on kinetic theory and statistical mechanics, which became a graduate-level textbook in <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>German<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>-speaking universities.
It was in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1926<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Herzfeld<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> took a visiting professorship at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Johns Hopkins University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Baltimore<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Maryland<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, which developed into a regular faculty position. During <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1930<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1932<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he was a lecturer at <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Cooper Union<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Fordham University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>New York City<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.
While at <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Johns Hopkins<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Herzfeld<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> did considerable research with the chemist <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Francis O. Rice<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, who joined the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> as an associate professor the same year <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Herzfeld<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> arrived. Their <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1928<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> paper considered the role of molecular vibrations in the transfer of energy between ultrasonic waves and gas molecules. At <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Johns Hopkins<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Herzfeld<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> worked with other <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>European<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> colleagues on the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>s physics faculty, namely <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>James Franck<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Maria Goeppert-Mayer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, who were awarded <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Nobel Prizes<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> in Physics in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1925<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1963<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, respectively. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Franck<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> came to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Johns Hopkins<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> after he left <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Germany<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1933<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, where he had been ordinarius professor of experimental physics and Director of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Second Institute for Experimental Physics<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Göttingen<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and a close colleague of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Max Born<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, who was Director of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Institute of Theoretical Physics<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> at <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Göttingen<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Goeppert-Mayer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was a student of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Born<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, and she joined the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Johns Hopkins faculty<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1931<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Goeppert-Mayer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Herzfeld<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> published articles on states of aggregation and nuclear fusion reactions. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Herzfeld<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> coauthored articles with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Franck<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> on photosynthesis, one being after they had both left <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Johns Hopkins<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>John Archibald Wheeler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, who became a prominent physicist, took his PhD under <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Herzfeld<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1933<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1936<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Herzfeld<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> moved to <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>The Catholic University of America<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Washington, DC<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, where he remained until his death in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1978<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. He received emeritus status in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1969<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and stayed active for the rest of his life.
Reasons for <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Herzfeld<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> leaving <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Johns Hopkins<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> were described in a letter to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Arnold Sommerfeld<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. A main reason was the dire financial situation at <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Johns Hopkins<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. However, there were other reasons as well. One being his relationship with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>R. W. Wood<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, a professor of experimental physics and chairman of the physics department, had deteriorated. Also, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>J. A. Bearden<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, another experimentalist, thought there was too much emphasis on theoretical physics and the number of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>German<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> physicists in the small department was out of balance. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bearden<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> also suspected that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Herzfeld<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> had brought <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Franck<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> to <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Johns Hopkins<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> to further <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Herzfeld<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>s ambitions to be department chairman. Finally too, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bearden<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> thought <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Herzfeld<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> had caused dissension in the department over his strong support to promote <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Göppert-Mayer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> from research associate in physics to a regular faculty appointment. While <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Herzfeld<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> did receive offers from both <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Fordham University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Catholic University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, neither was appealing as they did not have strong research departments. While talking the situation over with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Isaiah Bowman<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, president of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Johns Hopkins<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, it became clear that the financial difficulties at <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Johns Hopkins<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> might require downsizing the physics faculty. With this in mind, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Herzfeld<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> accepted the offer from <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Catholic University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Herzfeld<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>s teaching responsibilities and salary at <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Catholic University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> were about the same as that at <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Johns Hopkins<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, but there were additional administrative duties, as he was also chairman of the physics department.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1938<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Herzfeld<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> married <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Regina Flannery<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, who was an instructor at <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Catholic University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>; by the time she retired in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1970<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, she had risen to professor and head of that department.
In the late <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1940<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>s, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Herzfeld<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> increased the attention at <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Catholic University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> to quantum-mechanical calculations on the electronic structure of polyatomic molecules, thus establishing a respected position for the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in this field.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1959<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Herzfeld<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and Theodore A. Litovitz collaborated on a book, in part, summarizing <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Herzfeld<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>s thinking on ultrasonics over the 30 plus years since his article with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>F. O. Rice<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1966<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Herzfeld<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> published a review article summarizing 50 years of developments in physical ultrasonics.
