<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Anita Lonsbrough MBE<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (born <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>10 August 1941<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>York<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>) is a former swimmer from <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Great Britain<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> who won a gold medal at the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1960<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Summer Olympics<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
At the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1958<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>British Empire and Commonwealth Games<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Cardiff<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> she won gold in the 220&#160; yards breaststroke and the medley relay.
At the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1960<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Summer Olympics<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Rome<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>27 August 1960<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, at the age of 19, she won gold in the 200&#160; m breaststroke in 2:49.5 ahead of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>West Germany<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Wiltrud Urselmann<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (2:50.0), setting a new world record time. She was one of only two <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>GB<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> gold medallists that year, the other being <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Don Thompson<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> in the 50&#160; kilometre walk.
She would also be the last <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>British<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> woman to win <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Olympic gold<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> in swimming until <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Rebecca Adlington<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> gained the gold in the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2008<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Summer Olympics<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, 48 years later.
At the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1962<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>British Empire and Commonwealth Games<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Perth<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> she won three golds: 110&#160; yards breaststroke; 220&#160; yards breaststroke; and 440&#160; yards individual medley.
At the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1964<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Summer Olympics<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Tokyo<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> she came seventh in the 400&#160; m individual medley.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lonsbrough<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was a <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Treasurer's Office<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> clerk employed at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Huddersfield Town Hall<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. She won her first gold medal for swimming in the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1958<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>British Empire and Commonwealth Games<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Cardiff<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. Five world records and seven gold medals followed until her retirement in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1964<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. At one time she held the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Olympic<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Empire<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> and <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>European<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> titles at the same time.
She currently is a sports commentator and journalist for <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>The Daily Telegraph<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, under the name <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Anita Lonsbrough-Porter<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. She is married to cycling commentator and former leading <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>British<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> professional track cyclist <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hugh Porter<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>; they met travelling to <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Tokyo<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> for the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1964<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Summer Olympics<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and married in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1965<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Anita Lonsbrough<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was the first female flag bearer for <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Great Britain<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Summer Games<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> when she carried the flag in the opening ceremony of the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1964<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Summer Olympics<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. She was the first woman winner of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>BBC Sports Personality of the Year<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1962<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
She was awarded an <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>MBE<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1963<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> for services to swimming.
