<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ahti Kalle Samuli Karjalainen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>(<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>10 February 1923<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Hirvensalmi<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>7 September 1990<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Helsinki<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>) was a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Finnish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>politician. He was a member of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Agrarian League<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>(later known as <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Keskusta<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Centre Party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>) and was Prime Minister of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Finland<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>for two terms. <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Karjalainen<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>is considered one of the most influential people in post-war <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Finnish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>politics and economy.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Karjalainen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>served as second Minister of Treasury, Minister of Foreign Affairs and Minister of Trade and Industry from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1957<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, until he formed his first government on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>13 April 1962<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, which was in session for 615 days until <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>18 December 1963<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. After that, the government was disbanded because <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>SAK<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>-sympathetic ministers had resigned because of economy-political disagreements. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Karjalainen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s second government was in session <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>15 July 1970<tag name="DATE" value="end"/><tag name="DATE" value="start"/>29 October 1971<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Karjalainen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s ministrial career continued with only minor breaks to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>May, 1977<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, when he had spent 5772 days as a political minister. In the history of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Finnish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>politics, this is second only to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Johannes Virolainen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Karjalainen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>was nominated as a candidate for the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Parliament of Finland<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1966<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>and served as Member of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Parliament<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>for 13 years.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Urho Kekkonen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>took <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Karjalainen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>as his secretary in his first government in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1950<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. This was the start of co-operation between <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Kekkonen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Karjalainen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, which continued as good and tight for over 20 years. The co-operation was broken up when <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Kekkonen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> disbanded <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Karjalainen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s, who was seen as his future successor, second government in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1971<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Karjalainen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> sought to be the presidential candidate for the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Centre Party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1981<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, but lost to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Johannes Virolainen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>January 1982<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mauno Koivisto<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was elected as President of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Finland<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> after <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Kekkonen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> resigned.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Karjalainen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> had a great career in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Bank of Finland<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. He served as director of its research facility from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1953<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1957<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and was elected to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Board of Management<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1958<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Karjalainen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> served as deputy Managing Director of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Bank of Finland<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1979<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, acting Chairman of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Board<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1979<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1982<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and as Managing Director from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1982<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1983<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Karjalainen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was a Doctor of Political Science. His thesis was entitled "The relationships between the monetary politics of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Bank of Finland<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and the state economy from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1811<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1953<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> mainly regarding liquidity analysis".
Especially the latter part of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Karjalainen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s political career was influenced by alcoholism (at one stage after he had left the Prime Ministry, there was a national scandal when he was arrested for drunk driving). <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Karjalainen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s use of alcoholic beverages and his rather personal pronunciation of the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>English<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> language gave him a popular nickname "<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Tankero<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>". In <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Finland<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, "<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Tankero jokes<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>" have almost become national heritage.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1989<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Karjalainen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> published letters which showed how <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Paavo Výyrynen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> had worked with <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>KGB<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> spy <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Viktor Vladimirov<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Karjalainen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> died of pancreatic cancer in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>September 1990<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
