As player.
As manager.
As owner.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>James Robert "Loafer" McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>July 10, 1864<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>&#160; – <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>April 29, 1931<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) was an <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>American<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> center fielder, manager, and stockholder in <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Major League Baseball<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> who assisted in establishing the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>American League<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. He spent most of his 13-season playing career with the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Cleveland Spiders<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, and went on to manage the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Cleveland Blues<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>St. Louis Browns<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, and W<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>ashington Senators<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. Shortly before his retirement, he became a major shareholder in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Boston Red Sox<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
His career ended abruptly. During his brief tenure as co-owner of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Red Sox<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> quarreled with longtime friend and colleague <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ban Johnson<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, president of the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>American League<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. In the wake of this disagreement, he sold off his shares in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Red Sox<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and broke off his relationship with <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Major League Baseball<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s rift with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Johnson<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, along with his sudden retirement, damaged his professional reputation, and he received little recognition for his contributions to baseball. Today, he is most often remembered for initiating the customary request that the President of the <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>United States<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> throw out the first ball of the season.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was born in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Youngstown<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Ohio<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, an industrial center located near the border of western <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Pennsylvania<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. His father, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Owen McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, died at a young age, leaving <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s mother, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mary<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, to support three children. The family lived on the city's west side, where the <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> children were raised to value the concept of formal education. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> attended local public schools and graduated from <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Rayen High School<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. In later years, all three of the <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> brothers moved on to successful careers, and the oldest, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Owen McAleer, Jr.<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, served for a time as mayor of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Los Angeles<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>California<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.
A "strapping six-foot 175-pound outfielder, " <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> won early recognition for his physical speed. He became involved with a <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Youngstown<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> minor league baseball club in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1882<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, remaining with the team until <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1884<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1885<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> joined another minor league organization in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Charleston<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>South Carolina<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>; and in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1887<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he played for a team based in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Memphis<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Tennessee<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. His skill as a center fielder was recognized in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1888<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, while he was playing for a club in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Milwaukee<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Wisconsin<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.
Although his primary focus was organized sports, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was also drawn to the field of entertainment. During one season of his minor league career, he became part-owner of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>DeHaven Comedy Company<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, a theatrical road troupe that was organized in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Youngstown<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. His interest in show business remained a constant, and in later years <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> developed a strong friendship with <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Broadway<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> composer and performer <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>George M. Cohan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>April 24, 1889<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> broke into the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Major Leagues<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Cleveland<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Ohio<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, where he established a reputation as a graceful outfielder. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1891<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, when <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Patsy Tebeau<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> became manager of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Cleveland Spiders<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, the club became known for its aggressive tactics. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Tebeau<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> encouraged players to block and hold runners, while he himself openly challenged and harassed officials. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1896<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Cleveland<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> manager was jailed for attacking an umpire who "decided it was too dark to continue a game". On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>June 27, 1896<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was among several <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Cleveland<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> players to be fined by a <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Louisville<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Kentucky<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>) judge for their role in the incident. Later that year, the club's notoriety prompted other <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>National League<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> teams to propose a boycott of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Cleveland<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, "until the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Spiders<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> mended their ways." <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s periodic displays of temper were in keeping with this rowdy environment. During an <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>August 18, 1891<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> game with the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Cincinnati Reds<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Reds<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> player <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Arlie Latham<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> tripped <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> as he rounded third base; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> responded by chasing <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Latham<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> around the field, while brandishing his bat.
At the same time, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> proved a strong performer. A later newspaper account described him as an outstanding outfielder who was "blessed with excellent speed". The article noted that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s skills as a sprinter helped him steal 51 bases in one year and 41 in another. According to some accounts, he was "the first centerfielder to take his eyes off a fly ball, run to the spot where it fell to earth, and catch it". Less proficient as a hitter, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> accumulated a lifetime batting average of.253. During his career, the league's batting (pitchers removed) average for players with the same home field was.284. On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>April 24, 1894<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he assisted in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Cleveland<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s 1–0 victory over <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Cincinnati<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> with a single in the ninth that drove home <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Buck Ewing<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, who had doubled. Along with teammates <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Cy Young<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Jesse Burkett<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>John Clarkson<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Charles Zimmer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> also participated in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Spiders<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>' victory over the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Baltimore Orioles<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1895<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Temple Cup<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, a post-season series between first and second-place teams of the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>National League<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. The <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Spiders<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> placed second to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Orioles<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> at the close of both the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1895<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1896<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> seasons. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s performance came in spite of a serious injury he received during a game held in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Philadelphia<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>August 24, 1895<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, when he collided with a fence. Furthermore, he balanced his achievements in sports with a foray into politics in his hometown of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Youngstown<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. During the summer of <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1895<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was promoted in the local media as a mayoral candidate, first as a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Republican<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, and then as an independent. Further research is required to determine the depth of his involvement in politics.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1898<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, when the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Spiders<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>' owners purchased the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>St. Louis Browns franchise<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> opted to stay in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Cleveland<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, taking a brief hiatus from baseball until the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Cleveland Blues<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> franchise joined the newly formed <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>American League<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>AL<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>). During his two-year absence, the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Spiders<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> lost many of their more experienced players. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1899<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, the team won 20 games and lost 134, which is still percentage-wise the worst season record in <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Major League<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> history. As baseball historian <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bill James<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> noted, the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Spiders<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> were forced to cancel home games due to poor attendance and "turned the last two months of the season into a long road trip". After a full year out of baseball in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1899<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was back in a <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Cleveland<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> uniform in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1900<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, in a new league, as player-manager of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Cleveland Lake Shores<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> of the fledgling <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>American League<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, then a minor league. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s subsequent career as a major league manager (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1901<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>–<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1911<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) overlapped with his playing career (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1882<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>–<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1907<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>). Although he did not play professionally between <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1903<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1906<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> played in his last <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Major League<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> game on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>July 8, 1907<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1900<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> became player-manager of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Cleveland Lake Shores<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (a predecessor of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Cleveland Indians<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>) and continued with the franchise in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1901<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, when the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>American League<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> became a major league and the club was renamed as the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Blues<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, a name borrowed from a team that had participated in the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>National League<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> during the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1870<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>s and <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1880<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>s. The <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Blues<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> made their major league debut on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>April 24, 1901<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, with an 8–2 loss to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Chicago White Sox<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. Two other league games were canceled due to inclement weather, and the contest between the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Blues<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>White Sox<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> served as the inaugural game of the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>AL<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>July<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> of that year, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> presided over the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Blues<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>' upset 6–1 loss to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Detroit Tigers<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. Although the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Tigers<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>' manager, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Tommy Burns<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, agreed to forfeit the game for fear that the umpire, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Joe Cantillon<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, would be injured by an angry crowd, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> agreed to play the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Tigers<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> using a reserve umpire. The <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Blues<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> eventually closed the season with a 54–82 record, placing seventh in the eight-team <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>American League<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, however, contributed little to this outcome. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1901<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he played in only three games with the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Blues<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. The <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>AL<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, established in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1900<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ban Johnson<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, former president of the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Western League<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, was by this time in direct competition with the well-established <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>National League<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>NL<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>). <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, a close friend of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Johnson<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and his associate, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Charles Comiskey<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, played a significant role in the new league's development, recruiting scores of experienced players from the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>NL<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>.
As manager of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Browns<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> lured players such as <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Hall of Famers<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Jesse Burkett<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bobby Wallace<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1902<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Browns<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> took second place in the league, with a record of 78 wins and 58 losses. Between <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1903<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1907<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, however, the team never ranked higher than fifth or sixth place in the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>AL<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. Then, in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1908<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, the club rebounded, finishing just six-and-a-half games out of first place, with a record of 83 wins and 69 losses, landing at fourth in the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>AL<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. The <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Browns<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> ended the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1909<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> season, however, with a record of 61–89, earning seventh place. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was fired at the close of the season. <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Browns<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> owner <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Robert L. Hedges<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, a <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Cincinnati<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> carriage maker, replaced the "affable" <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> with the "crustier" <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Jack O'Connor<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, who was expelled from the league in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1910<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> for seeking to influence the outcome of the annual batting championship.
On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>September 22, 1909<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> went on to manage the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Washington Senators<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (popularly known as the "<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Nationals<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>"), a team that had ceased to be competitive since the death of star hitter <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ed Delahanty<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> six years earlier. The team fared little better under <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s management, finishing with a lackluster 66–85 record (seventh place) at the close of the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1910<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> season. The high point of the season was a game in which <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> initiated what became a baseball tradition. On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>April 14, 1910<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he asked visiting President <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>William Howard Taft<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> to throw out the first ball of a season opener. President <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Taft<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, an ardent fan of the game, readily agreed. Baseball historians <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Donald Dewey<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Nicholas Acocella<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> noted that the game "almost put an end to the career" of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>U.S.<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> Vice President <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>James S. Sherman<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, who "took a foul ball off the bat of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Frank Baker<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> directly in the head". This contest also featured a one-hit performance by pitcher <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Walter Johnson<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, who led the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Senators<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> to a 3–0 victory over the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Philadelphia Athletics<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
Toward the close of the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1911<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> season, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> announced his resignation as manager of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Senators<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1912<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he became a major stockholder in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Boston Red Sox<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, purchasing a half-interest in the team. That year, the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Red Sox<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> "cruised to the pennant with 105 victories".
By the time the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Red Sox<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> entered the sixth game of the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>1912 World Series<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, the team had secured a 3–1 lead over the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>New York Giants<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. (The second game of the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Series<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> ended in a tie.) Then, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> pressured the team's manager, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Jake Stahl<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, to hand the ball to unseasoned pitcher <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Buck O'Brien<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> for the "clincher". <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s recommendation was apparently part of a strategy to ensure that the seventh game of the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Series<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> would be played at <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Boston<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>'s new <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Fenway Park<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. Although the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Red Sox<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s loss to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Giants<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (at 5–2) guaranteed that the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Series<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> would conclude in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Boston<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, the incident created conflict between <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Stahl<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. Subsequent press releases suggesting that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Stahl<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> would replace <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> as club president exacerbated these tensions.
In the seventh game of the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Series<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Red Sox<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> opened <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Fenway Park<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> with a 7–6 victory over the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Giants<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. The team suffered a public relations fiasco, however, when a <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Red Sox<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> shareholder sold seats at the stadium that had been reserved for the club's most ardent fans, the "<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Royal Rooters<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>". Finding themselves without seats, the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Royal Rooters<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, led by <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Boston<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> Mayor <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>John "Honey Fitz" Fitzgerald<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, marched around the stadium in protest. A riot ensued, and in the aftermath of the disturbance, only 17, 000 <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Boston<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> residents showed up for the final game. Nevertheless, the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Red Sox<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> emerged as victors, with a final score of 4–3 and one tied game.
Following the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Series<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> victory over the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Giants<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> returned to his hometown to celebrate the event. A brass band met him at <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Youngstown<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>'s train depot, and a parade and fireworks display were held in his honor. The <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Youngstown Daily Vindicator<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> reported: "As the auto bearing Mr. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> turned into <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>West Federal Street<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, hundreds of sticks of red fire were burning at <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Central Square<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, while the quiet atmosphere was occasionally punctured by the explosion of a bomb". This was the last time he would publicly greet residents of his hometown as a figure in professional baseball.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s tenure as part-owner of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Red Sox<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> came to a swift end. On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>July 15, 1913<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> became involved in a dispute with the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>AL<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> president, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ban Johnson<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, when <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> forced the resignation of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Red Sox<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> manager <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Jake Stahl<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, one of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Johnson<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s closest friends. While <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> claimed that he released <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Stahl<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> because of a foot injury preventing <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Stahl<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> from serving as a player-manager, rumors suggested that the two men had strong personal differences. Following a bitter quarrel with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Johnson<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> sold his holdings in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Red Sox<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. His feud with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Johnson<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> turned out to be a lifelong affair, despite efforts taken by their mutual friend, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Charles Comiskey<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, to smooth over the rift. While <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> never publicly discussed the disagreement that spurred his retirement, he supposedly relayed his version of events to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Frank B. Ward<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, a sports reporter with The <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Youngstown Daily Vindicator<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, with the understanding that the details remain confidential until <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s death.
Although other sources tell a different story, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ward<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> wrote that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> termed his "break" with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Johnson<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> as the result of a "betrayal" of trust. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> indicated that his controlling interest in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Red Sox<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> entitled him to make all major decisions regarding the organization, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ward<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> wrote. This view of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s powers, however, was not shared by the club's manager, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Stahl<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, the article added. To further complicate matters, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Stahl<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s father-in-law, a <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Chicago<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>-based banker, was reportedly a shareholder in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Red Sox<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. After one particularly heated exchange between <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Stahl<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> at the close of the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1912<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> season, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Stahl<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> went to <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Chicago<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> to confer with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Johnson<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. The article indicated that, after this meeting, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Johnson<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> sent <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> a "sternly worded" letter, which may have been designed to preserve his relationship with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Stahl<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Stahl<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s father-in-law. According to the article, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Johnson<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> later confided to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> that he owed <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Stahl<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s father-in-law money and therefore felt obliged to take <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Stahl<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s side in the dispute. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, however, took the admonition from <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Johnson<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> as a betrayal of their friendship, refused to accept <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Johnson<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s explanations, and promptly retired, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ward<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> wrote. This version of events is largely corroborated by the early research of baseball historian <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>David Fleitz<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
Baseball historians <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Dewey<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Acocella<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, however, described a markedly different scenario in which <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Johnson<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> secretly sold off <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s shares while <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was away on a <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1913<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> world tour with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Comiskey<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>New York Giants<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> manager <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>John McGraw<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, and members of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Red Sox<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> team. According to this account, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s conflict with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Stahl<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was followed up by his involvement in a feud between two pairs of players – <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Tris Speaker<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Joe "Smoky Joe" Wood<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, on one side, and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Heinie Wagner<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bill Carrigan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, on the other. The conflict had a "religious dimension" and was described in the press as "pitting Masons against members of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Knights of Columbus<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>". <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> evidently supported <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Wagner<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Carrigan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Catholic<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> players in the dispute. These back-to-back incidents involving individuals associated with the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Red Sox<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> team "reinforced <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Johnson<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s belief that the club president was the source of all the trouble", <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Dewey<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Acocella<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> wrote. In his recent book, <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>The Irish in Baseball<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>David Fleitz<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> observed that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s abrupt dismissal was typical of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Johnson<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, "who had a history of ending relationships when they no longer benefited him personally".
Relatively little is known about <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s private life. Research suggests that he was married three times, with his first marriage (to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hannah McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>) taking place in the early <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>20th century<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. At some point, he married the former <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Anna Durbin<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, a native of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Trenton<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>New Jersey<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. The couple had no children. According to her obituary, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Anna McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was her husband's "constant companion" during his "active career as a baseball magnate". When the couple settled in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Youngstown<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1913<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, she participated in charity work and joined the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Altar and Rosary Society<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> at <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>St. Columba's Church<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, where she attended religious services. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1930<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Anna McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> died suddenly at an apartment the couple shared on the north side of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Youngstown<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>James McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, who discovered his wife's body after returning from a walk, was "overcome". <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> had recently been released from a local hospital following an appendicectomy; he was quickly readmitted following his wife's death.
A few months later, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> married a <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Youngstown<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> woman, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Georgianna Rudge<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, a graduate of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Juilliard School of Music<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> who was almost 23 years her husband's junior. Ultimately, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Georgianna McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> survived her husband by more than five decades. By the time of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>James McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s second marriage, his health was in decline. He was hospitalized within a few months of the wedding.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> returned to <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Youngstown<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, where he spent his last years. Active in the community, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> served on the city's original draft board, which had been authorized under <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Ohio<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> Governor <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>James M. Cox<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> during <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>World War I<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. In retirement, the former baseball manager maintained friendships with celebrities including <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>George M. Cohan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>King Alfonso XIII<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Spain<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> became acquainted with the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Spanish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> monarch during a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>European<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> tour with the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Red Sox<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in the winter of <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1912<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>–<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1913<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
His final years were marked by poor health. Several weeks before his death, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was admitted to a local hospital, where his health reportedly improved. This account, however, differs from that of baseball historian <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>David Fleitz<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, who suggested that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> had been diagnosed with cancer in the early <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1930<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>s. In any event, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> died suddenly on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>April 29, 1931<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, shortly after being released from the hospital. He was 66 years old. After private funeral services at <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Orr<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s funeral home, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s remains were interred at <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Oak Hill Cemetery<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, on <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Youngstown<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>'s near south side. Apart from his widow, he left behind two brothers, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>J.C. McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Austintown<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Ohio<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Owen McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Los Angeles<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. Other survivors included two nephews, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Captain Charlies McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, an officer in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>U.S. Army<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>James McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Los Angeles<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.
Rumors persist that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s death was the result of a self-inflicted gunshot wound to the head. While his name is included on some lists of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Major League Baseball<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> players who committed suicide, contemporary newspaper accounts indicated that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> died of natural causes.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s hometown newspaper, The <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Youngstown Daily Vindicator<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, eulogized the ex-Major Leaguer in the following terms: "Forceful and resourceful, but always retiring when there was talk of his share in the development of baseball, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>James R. McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> died within a matter of weeks after the passing of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Byron Bancroft Johnson<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, his chief partner in the forming of the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>American League<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, and the man with whom he 'broke', which break brought about his retirement".
The article praised <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> for assisting the careers of other baseball figures. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1905<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, during his tenure as manager of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>St. Louis Browns<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> helped future <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Hall of Fame<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> umpire <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Billy Evans<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> secure a position with the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>American League<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, writing a personal letter to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Johnson<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> on <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Evans<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>' behalf. Meanwhile, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> served as a contact for another <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Youngstown<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> resident, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>John "Bonesetter" Reese<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, the Welsh-born "baseball doctor" who worked with players such as <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Cy Young<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, Ty Cobb, Rogers Hornsby, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Walter Johnson<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>John McGraw<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s contributions to the game failed to win him a place in the Baseball Hall of Fame, however. In 1936, during the first elections to the Baseball Hall of Fame, he received just one vote in the balloting for 19th-century figures. Nevertheless, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> received an unofficial endorsement from Hall of Fame second baseman Nap Lajoie, who described <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> as "one of the best ever". <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s obituary in The New York Times suggested that he was "one of the fastest outfielders the major leagues ever produced". In 2003, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bill James<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> described <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McAleer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> as "the best defensive outfielder of the 1890s". More recently, baseball historian <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>David Fleitz<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> observed, "this brilliant defensive outfielder was a smart, clever, and ambitious man who helped to create two of the original eight franchises of the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>American League<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>".
Birmingham • Fohl • Speaker • McCallister • Peckinpaugh • <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Johnson<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> • O'Neill • Vitt • Boudreau • Lopez • Farrell • Bragan • Gordon • Dykes • Harder • McGaha • Harder • Tebbetts • Strickland • Adcock • Dark • Lipon • Aspromonte • Robinson • Torborg • Garcia • Ferraro • Corrales • Edwards • Hart • McNamara • Hargrove • Manuel • Skinner • Wedge • Acta.
