<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Jonathan Edward Schell<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (born <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1943<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) is an author and visiting fellow at <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Yale University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, whose work primarily deals with nuclear weapons.
His work has appeared in <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>The Nation<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>The New Yorker<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, and <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>TomDispatch<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>The Fate of the Earth<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> received the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Los Angeles Times<tag name="MISC" value="end"/><tag name="MISC" value="start"/> Book Prize<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, among other awards, and was nominated for the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Pulitzer Prize<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>National Book Award<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, and the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>National Critics Award<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. He was most recently a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Distinguished Fellow<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Yale Center<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> for the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Study of Globalization<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>.
In the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1980<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>s, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Schell<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> wrote a series of articles in <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>The New Yorker<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (subsequently published as <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>The Fate of the Earth<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>), which were instrumental in raising public awareness about the dangers of the nuclear arms race. He has been a persistent advocate for disarmament, and a world free of nuclear weapons.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2002<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2003<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Schell<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was a persistent critic of the invasion of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Iraq<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. He has since commented, "There doesn't seem to be a rush to find the people who were right about <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Iraq<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and install them in the mainstream media.".
During his heyday at <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>The New Yorker<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Spy<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> magazine noted that his colleagues referred to him as "the incredibly boring <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Jonathan Schell<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>".
He is the younger brother of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Orville Schell<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, former dean of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of California<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Berkeley Graduate School<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> of Journalism. and current <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Arthur Ross<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> Director of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Center on U.S.-China Relations<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> at <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Asia Society<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>New York<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. He is a graduate of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>The Putney School<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Putney<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Vermont<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.
.
