<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Veselin Vujović<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (born <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>January 18, 1961<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Cetinje<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Montenegro<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>FPR Yugoslavia<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>) is a former <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Yugoslav<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> handball player who competed in the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1984<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Summer Olympics<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and in the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1988<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Summer Olympics<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. During his career he played for <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>RK Metaloplastika Šabac<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Barcelona<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Granollers<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. With <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>RK Metaloplastika<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> he won two handball champions league (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1985<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1986<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) and one with <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>FC Barcelona Handbol<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1991<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>). He was first player to receive title of the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>IHF World Player of the Year<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1984<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> he was a member of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Yugoslav handball team<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> which won the gold medal. He played all six matches and scored 28 goals. Four years later he was part of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Yugoslav team<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> which won the bronze medal. He played all six matches again and scored 29 goals.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1986<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> he is named as.
He is the manager of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>HC Vardar PRO<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, a handball club in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Skopje<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Macedonia<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.
.
