<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Forshaw Day<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1837<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>–<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1903<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) was a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Canadian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> artist known for his landscapes.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Forshaw Day<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was born in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>London<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>England<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1837<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. He studied architecture and design at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Royal Dublin Society<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Dublin<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Ireland<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1857<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. He studied architecture and design at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>South Kensington School of Art<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>London<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>England<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Forshaw Day<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> emigrated to <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Halifax<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Nova Scotia<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> at age 25 in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1862<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
He painted pictures and taught painting at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Technological Institute<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Halifax<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Nova Scotia<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1862<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>-<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1879<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. He prepared sets for <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Garrison theatre productions<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Halifax<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Nova Scotia<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1876<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Day<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> supplied a panorama, "From <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Paris<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> to <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>London<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, " for a professional theatre company. .
He worked as a draftsman at the in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>H.M. Naval Yard<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1862<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>-<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>79<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Halifax<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Nova Scotia<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. He moved to <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Kingston<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Ontario<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> where he taught freehand drawing at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Royal Military College of Canada<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1879<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>-<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1897<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Day<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> painted in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>England<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Ireland<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Switzerland<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. In <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Canada<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Day<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> painted in the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Maritimes<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Ontario<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>British Columbia<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Northwest Territories<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Forshaw Day<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> worked in the late 19th Century, after the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Civil War<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>United States<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Day<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was elected a member of the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Ontario<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> Society of Artists on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>August 14, 1879<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. He exhibited his works at the shows of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Royal Canadian Academy of Arts<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1901<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, members of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Royal Military College of Canada Club<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> raised the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Forshaw Day Painting Fund<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in aid of Prof. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Forshaw Day<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>R.C.A.<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, "in consideration of the friendly relations that always existed between him and the <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Cadets<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> in attendance at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>College<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, and in view of the fact that his circumstances were such as to appeal to the feelings of all those who had met him at <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Kingston<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>." A number of his Paintings were bought by club members and an oil painting was donated to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>College<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. He died in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Kingston<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Ontario<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1903<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Forshaw Day<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s work involved a combination of easel painting, printmaking and graphics. He worked with etching and oil paint. His preferred subjects included landscapes and marine seascapes.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Forshaw Day<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s work is found in various museums and private collections.
.
<tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Forshaw Island<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>St Joseph Channel<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Algoma<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Ontario<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Canada<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> was named in honour of late Professor <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Forshaw Day<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, Esq., <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>R.C.A<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> sometime Professor of Drawing at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Royal Military College, Kingston<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> c. <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1879<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
&#160; .
