<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Nehemiah Ford<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was an <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Canadian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> politician and painter. He was mayor of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Hamilton<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Ontario<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1852<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
Little is known of the life of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Nehemiah Ford<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. His presence in <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hamilton<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> is recorded in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1839<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, when he was a member of the executive of the first Mechanics' <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Institute of Wentworth County<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. He served as its recording secretary for several years, and was made an honorary member on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>February 25, 1848<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> as a reward for his services. A painter by trade, as well as a freemason, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Ford<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> was also a member of both Barton Lodge and the Church of St. Thomas.
He married Keziah Beasley in 1835, the daughter of one of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hamilton<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s earliest settlers, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Richard Beasley<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. They had at least two sons together. The date of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Ford<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s death is not certain, but is believed to be between <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1858<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1862<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ford<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was elected mayor in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1852<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, and his term of office was unusual. Problems arose when <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ford<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> agreed to allow <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>John Gamble Geddes<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> to use the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>James Street<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> council chambers for a meeting of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Gore and Wellington Church Society<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. Unfortunately, the time chosen coincided with a scheduled council meeting, and, when <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ford<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> agreed to change the time of the municipal meeting, he caused considerable friction. The council criticized his conduct but agreed to vote him the £100 salary for his year's services as mayor. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ford<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> refused to accept the salary with censure and brought the affair to public attention. Although the matter was later smoothed over, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ford<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> refused to run for a second term.
.
