<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Stephen Mandel<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (born <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>July 18, 1945<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Windsor<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Ontario<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>) is a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Canadian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> politician and the current mayor of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Edmonton<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Alberta<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mandel<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> received an Associate of Arts Degree from <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Lincoln College<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Lincoln<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Illinois<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, a Bachelor of Science in Business Administration from Miami University, and his Masters in Political Science from <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Windsor<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
He moved to <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Edmonton<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1972<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> from <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Windsor<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Ontario<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. He was first elected to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Edmonton City Council<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2001<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> as a Councillor for Ward 1. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2004<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he won an upset victory by defeating <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Edmonton<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s three-term mayor, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bill Smith<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mandel<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> is active with promoting the city's arts and festival scene. He is also an active volunteer with the city's local Heart and Stroke Foundation and with several local Jewish organizations.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mandel<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> is married to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lynn Mandel<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. They have two children, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Rachel<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Adam<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2006<tag name="DATE" value="end"/><tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2011<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> the city administration has been criticized by some members of the local press on issues relating to infrastructure maintenance.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>September 2007<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mandel<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> ordered the removal from city property of work by <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Edmonton<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> sculptor <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ryan McCourt<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, after receiving a 700-name petition that alleged <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>McCourt<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s sculptures had "hurt <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Hindu<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> religious sensibilities".
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mandel<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> created the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Mayor's Evening for the Arts<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, modifying what was formerly a luncheon event to a festive evening at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Francis Winspear Centre for Music<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> featuring awards to local businesses and artists.
On <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Thursday, March 4, 2010<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mandel<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> announced that he would seek a third term as mayor. He was re-elected for his third term on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>Monday, October 18, 2010<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. 55% of all votes cast for the mayoral election were for <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mandel<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
Mayor: <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Stephen Mandel<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
.
