<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Dragutin Šurbek<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (born <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>August 8, 1946<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Zagreb<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>SR Croatia<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>SFR Yugoslavia<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>) is a legendary former table tennis player from <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Croatia<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. He is one of the most successful <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Croatian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> table tennis players ever.
One of the most extraordinary <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>European<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> players ever, he won hundreds of tournaments during the peak of his table tennis career (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1964<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>–<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1986<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>), from <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Tokyo<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Novi Sad<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> to <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Beijing<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Zagreb<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. His partner in doubles was the almost equally powerful player <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Antun Stipančić-Tova<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Šurbek<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> competed with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Zoran Primorac<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> at the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1992<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Summer Olympics<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> for <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Croatia<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> when he was 46 year old.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Dragutin Šurbek<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s biggest successes were two <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>World Championship<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> titles in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Men's Doubles event<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. He won gold medals in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1979<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> (with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Stipančić<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>) and in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1983<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> (with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Zoran Kalinić<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>). In the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Men's Singles event<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, he won the bronze medal three times (in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1971<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1973<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1981<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>). He was the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>European<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> champion in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Men's Singles<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1968<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Men's Doubles<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1970<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1982<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1984<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. With the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>SFR Yugoslavia<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> national team, he was <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>European<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> champion in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1976<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
He received the award for the best athlete of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Yugoslavia<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1983<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Šurbek<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> is currently a table tennis coach in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Zagreb<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.
