<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lucio Malan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (born <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>30 July 1960<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) is an <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Italian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> politician.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Malan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was born in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Luserna San Giovanni<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Turin<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. He earned his BA in Literature at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Turin<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, then he obtained a master's degree in history at <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Nevada Las Vegas<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, where <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lucio Malan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was also tutor-assistant.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lucio Malan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> is member of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>People of Freedom Party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. From <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1994<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1996<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> he was a deputy. Since <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2001<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> he has been senator and secretary of the presidency of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Italian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> Senate. He is also a member of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>NATO Parliamentary Assembly<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lucio Malan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> is a member of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Waldensian Evangelical Church<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
From <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1990<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1998<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> he was guest speaker of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Italian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> History and Culture at University Studies Abroad Consortium in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Turin<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Italy<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
From <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1998<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2008<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> he has been the director of communications of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Forza Italia Party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
Some <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Italian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> newspapers have reported that Senator <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Malan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> took his wife as a secretary using public funds of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Senate<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
.
