<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Danutė Jočienė<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (maiden name <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sadauskaitė<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, born <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>November 10, 1970<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Tučiai<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Mažeikiai<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Lithuania<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>) is a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Lithuanian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> lawyer. She is the second representative of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Lithuania<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>European Court of Human Rights<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> to date and the youngest judge in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Court<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s history (at the time of her election in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>May 2004<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> she was 33 years old).
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Danutė Jočienė<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> graduated from the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Law Faculty<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Vilnius University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and worked as a lecturer in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Department of the International and European Union Law<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Faculty<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
She was agent of the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Lithuanian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> government for the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>European Court of Human Rights<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2003<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>November 2004<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Danutė Jočienė<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s professional work has been in the field of human rights law, and she was appointed as a judge and reporter from <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Lithuania<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> to the second section of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>European Court of Human Rights<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2004<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
