<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Jasna `ekari<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>(<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Cyrillic<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>: 0A=0 (5:0@8[, nýe <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Brajkovi<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>(@0X:>28[) (born <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>December 17, 1965<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Belgrade<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Serbia<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>is a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Serbian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>sport shooter. She has won a total of five <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Olympic<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>medals: one gold, three silvers and one bronze. She has also won three <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>World Championships<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>gold medals in the 10 m air pistol. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1992<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, she lost the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Olympic<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>gold despite having the same score as winner <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Marina Logvinenko<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. She is one of only twenty-two shooters (by <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2010<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) to compete at at least six <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Olympic Games<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
She grew up in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Osijek<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Croatia<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, where she began to practice shooting. In the school section, first competed with a rifle and had a nice placed at regional competitions. A little later began to use a gun. <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1990<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>again came to <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Belgrade<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>and then following a successful year in sports and private level. She is married and has two children, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lea<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>(50) and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Luka<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>(C:0).
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>`ekari<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>was elected world's best shooter of the year thrice (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1990<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1994<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>and <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2005<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>), and the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>International Shooting Sport Federation<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>awarded her the title of Shooter of the Millennium in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2000<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. Furthermore she was a three-time world champion (<tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Budapest<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/><tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1987<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Sarajevo<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/><tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1989<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, and <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Milan<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/><tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1994<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>). Apart from that, she was a four-time <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>European<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> champion in the individual competitions (<tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Espoo<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1986<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>; <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Manchester<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1991<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Budapest<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1992<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Budapest<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1996<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, and <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Belgrade<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2005<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>).
`<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>ekari<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> triumphed six times in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>World Cup Finals<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and won six <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Crystal Globes<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>  one in the sport pistol (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1988<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) and five in the air pistol (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1990<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1996<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1997<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, and <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2005<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>). In the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1996<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>World Cup Finals<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> she first equalled the world record with 392, and then bettered it to 492.7. She won a total number of 90 medals in major competitions: <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Olympic Games<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>European<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>World Championships<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>World Cups<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Mediterranean Games<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. In the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2008<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> games, she will be the country's flag bearer at the opening ceremonies. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Jasna<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> is also in the golden book of the sport shooting as the only shooter participating at five OG and made final in all five!.
Despite never having changed nationality, `<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>ekari<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> has competed under four flags at her six <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Olympics<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. She competed for <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Yugoslavia<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> at the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1988<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Olympics<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1992<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, since <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Yugoslavia<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> was under <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>UN<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> sanctions, she (and fifty other <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Serbians<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Montenegrins<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Macedonians<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>) competed as Independent Olympic Participants. Her next three <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Olympics<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> were under the flag of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Serbia<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Montenegro<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and she finally competed for <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Serbia<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2008<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. Another athlete to compete under four different flags is <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Serbian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>-<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>American<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> table tennis player <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ilija Lupulesku<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, but he changed nationality in the process.
