<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sheila Finestone<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>PC<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>January 28, 1927<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> – June 8, 2009) was a Canadian Member of Parliament and Senator.
Born in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Montreal<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Quebec<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, the daughter of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Minnie Cummings Abbey<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Monroe Abbey<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, her father was a president of the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Canadian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Jewish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> Congress. Finestone received a Bachelor of Science degree from <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>McGill University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1947<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. The same year, she married <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Alan Finestone<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1923<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>–<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1997<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>). They had four sons: <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>David<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (born <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1950<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>), <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Peter<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (born <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1951<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>), <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Maxwell<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (born <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1953<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Stephen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (born <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1956<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>).
From <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1977<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1980<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, she was president of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Fédération des femmes du Québec<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1984<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> she was elected as a <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Liberal Member of Parliament for the Montreal<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> riding of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Mount Royal<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. She was re-elected in the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1988<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1993<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1997<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> elections.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Finestone<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was sworn to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Privy Council<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>November 1993<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> as Secretary of State (Multiculturalism and Status of Women). <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Finestone<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was appointed to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Senate of Canada<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>August 1999<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. She completed her term in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Senate<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2002<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> when she reached the mandatory retirement age of 75.
She was a member of the board of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Canadian Landmine Foundation<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2008<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Finestone<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was the recipient of the Distinguished <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Service Award<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Canadian Association of Former Parliamentarians<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, "presented annually to a former parliamentarian who has made an outstanding contribution to the country and its democratic institutions." The award was accepted on her behalf by her son <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Peter<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, due to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Finestone<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s inability to attend, following health challenges.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sheila Finestone<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> died on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>June 8, 2009<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, aged 82, in Ottawa following a battle with cancer.
.
