<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ernest Vessiot<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>March 8, 1865<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>  <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>October 17, 1952<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) was a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>French<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> mathematician. He was born in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Marseille<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>France<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and died in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>La Bauche<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Savoie<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>France<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. He entered the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>École Normale Supérieure<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1884<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
He was <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Maître de Conférences<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> at <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Lille University of Science and Technology<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1892<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>-<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1893<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, then moved at <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Toulouse<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Lyon<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.
After <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1910<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he was a professor of analytical mechanics and celestial mechanics at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Paris<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. He presided over entrance examinations at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>École Polytechnique<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. As director of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>École Normale Supérieure<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> until <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1935<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he overviewed the construction of its new physics, chemistry and geology buildings of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>24, Rue Lhomond<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.
He was elected a member of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Académie des Sciences<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1943<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Vessiot<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s work on <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>PicardVessiot theory<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> dealt with the integrability of ordinary differential equations.
.
