<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sandy Collins<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> is a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Canadian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> politician from <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Newfoundland and Labrador<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Canada<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. He represents the riding of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Terra Nova<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Newfoundland and Labrador House of Assembly<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, as a member of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Progressive Conservative Party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. Before entering politics <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Collins<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> worked as executive assistant to Cabinet Minister <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Paul Oram<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>When Oram<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> retired from provincial politics in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2009<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Collins<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> succeeded him as the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Member of the House of Assembly for Terra Nova<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
Upon finishing high school in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1996<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Collins<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> attended <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Memorial University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. He graducated in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2001<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> with a Bachelor of Arts degree with a double major in Political Science and History. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Collins<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> then accepted a one-year teaching position in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>South Korea<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and as a result of that experience he returned to university and received a Bachelor of Education degree in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2003<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. He returned to <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>South Korea<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> after completing his third degree and in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2004<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Collins<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> returned to Newfoundland and Labrador to work as Constituency Assistant to Paul Oram.
Collins is a member of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Progressive Conservative Party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and won his seat in a by-election on N<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>ovember 26, 2009<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> for the district of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Terra Nova<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. In the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2011<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> provincial election <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Collns<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was easily elected, winning over 63% of the popular vote. Following his re-election Premier Dunderdale appointed him as the Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister of Health and Community Services.
&#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; .
&#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; .
&#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; .
