<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Alice Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (12 September 1859&#160; – 1885) was an <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>English<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> nursemaid honoured for her bravery in rescuing the children in her care from a house fire. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was a household assistant and nursemaid to the family of her brother-in-law and sister, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Henry<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mary Ann Chandler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. The <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Chandlers<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> owned an oil and paint shop in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Union Street<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Southwark<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, then just south of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>London<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> lived with the family above the shop. In 1885 fire broke out in the shop, and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> rescued three of her nieces from the burning building, before falling from a window and suffering fatal injury.
<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Britain<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, in the wake of the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Industrial Revolution<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, experienced a period of great social change in which the rapidly growing news media paid increasing attention to the activities of the poorer classes. The manner of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>' death caused great public interest, with large numbers of people attending her funeral and contributing to the funding of a memorial. Shortly after her death, she underwent what has been described as a "secular canonisation", being widely depicted in popular culture and, although very little was known about her life, widely cited as a role model. Various social and political movements promoted <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> as an example of the values held by their particular movement. The circumstances of her death were distorted to give the impression that she was an employee willing to die for the sake of her employer's family, rather than for children to whom she was closely related. In 1902 her name was added to the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Memorial to Heroic Self Sacrifice<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> and in 1936 a street near the scene of the fire was renamed <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Ayres Street<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in her honour.
The case of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Alice Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> came to renewed public notice with the release of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Patrick Marber<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s 1997 play <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Closer<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, and the 2004 film based on it. An important element of the plot revolves around a central character who fabricates her identity based on the description of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> on the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Memorial to Heroic Self Sacrifice<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, with some of the film's key scenes shot around the memorial.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Alice Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was born into a large family in 1859, the seventh of ten children of a labourer, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>John Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. In December 1877, her sister <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mary Ann<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (older than <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Alice<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> by eleven years) married an oil and paint dealer, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Henry Chandler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Chandler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> owned a shop at 194 <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Union Street<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Southwark<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, about 400 yards (370&#160; m) south of the present-day <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Tate Modern<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
In 1881 <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> worked as a household assistant to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Edward Woakes<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, a doctor specialising in ear and throat disorders. By 1885 she had become a household assistant and nursemaid to the <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Chandlers<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, living with the family. After her death, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was described by a local resident as "not one of your fast sort—gentle and quiet-spoke, and always busy about her work". Another neighbour told the press that "no merry making, no excursion, no family festivity could tempt her from her self-imposed duties. The children must be bathed and put to bed, the clothes must be mended, the rooms must be 'tidied up', the cloth must be laid, the supper carefully prepared, before <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Alice<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> would dream of setting forth on her own pleasures".
The <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Chandler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s shop at <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Union Street<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, as depicted in a contemporary newspaper illustration, occupied the corner premises of a building of three storeys. The family lived above the shop, with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Henry<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mary Ann Chandler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> sleeping in one bedroom with their six-year-old son <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Henry<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> sharing a room on the second floor with her nieces, five-year-old <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Edith<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, four-year-old <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ellen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, and three-year-old <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Elizabeth<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. On the night of 1885, fire broke out in the oil and paint shop, trapping the family upstairs. Gunpowder and casks of oil were stored in the lower floors of the building, causing the flames to spread rapidly. Although the shop was near the headquarters of the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>London<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Fire Brigade<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and the emergency services were quickly on scene, by the time the fire engine arrived intense flames were coming from the lower windows, making it impossible for the fire brigade to position ladders. Meanwhile <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, wearing only a nightdress, had tried to reach her sister but was unable to get to her through the smoke. The crowd that had gathered outside the building were shouting to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> to jump. Instead she returned to the room she shared with the three young girls and threw a mattress out of the window, carefully dropping <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Edith<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> onto it. Despite further calls from below to jump and save herself, she left the window and returned carrying <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ellen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ellen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> clung to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and refused to be dropped, but <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> threw her out of the building, and the child was caught by a member of the crowd. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> went back into the smoke a third time and returned carrying badly injured <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Elizabeth<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, whom she dropped safely onto the mattress.
After rescuing the three girls, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> tried to jump herself, but overcome by smoke inhalation, fell limply from the window, striking the projecting shop sign. She missed the mattress and the crowd below and fell onto the pavement, suffering spinal injuries. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was rushed to nearby <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Guy's Hospital<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> where, because of the public interest that her story excited, hourly bulletins were issued about her health and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Queen Victoria<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> sent a lady-in-waiting to enquire after her condition.
The oil and paint stored in the shop caused the fire to burn out of control, and when the fire services were eventually able to enter the premises the rest of the family were found dead. The body of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Henry Chandler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was found on the staircase, still clutching a locked strongbox filled with the shop's takings, while the badly burnt remains of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mary Ann Chandler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> were found lying next to a first floor window, the body of six-year-old <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Henry<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> by her side. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s condition deteriorated and she died in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Guy's Hospital<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> on 1885. Her last words were reported as "I tried my best and could try no more". <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Elizabeth<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, the last of the children to be rescued, had suffered severe burns to her legs and died shortly after <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s body was not taken to <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Guy's Hospital<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s mortuary, but was laid in a room set aside for her. The estimated value of the floral tributes came to over £1, 000 (about £80, 000 as of 2011). <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was posthumously recognised by the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Metropolitan Board of Works<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>-controlled <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Royal Society for the Protection of Life from Fire<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (today the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Society for the Protection of Life from Fire<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>), who awarded her father <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>John Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> a sum of 10 guineas (about £840 as of 2011) in her honour. A memorial service for <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> at <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>St Saviour's Church<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (now <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Southwark Cathedral<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>) attracted such a large crowd that mourners were turned away due to lack of standing room, while a collection taken at the memorial service comprised 951 coins, totalling over £7. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was given a large public funeral, attended by over 10, 000 mourners. Her coffin was carried from her parents' house to her grave in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Isleworth Cemetery<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> by a team of 16 firemen, relieving each other in sets of four. The church service was attended by a group of 20 girls, dressed in white, from the village school that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> had attended. It had been planned that the girls should follow the coffin to the graveside and sing, but a severe hailstorm prevented this.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Henry<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mary Ann Chandler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> were buried in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Lambeth Cemetery<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> along with the two children who had died in the fire. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Edith<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ellen Chandler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> were accepted by the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Orphan Working School<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Kentish Town<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and trained as domestic servants.
Shortly after the fire it was decided to erect a monument to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, to be funded by public subscription, and by August 1885 the fund had raised over £100 (about £8, 000 as of 2011). On 1885 work began on the memorial. The monument was erected above her grave in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Isleworth Cemetery<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, and was of an <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Egyptian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> design inspired by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Cleopatra<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s Needle, which had been raised in central <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>London<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in 1878. It took the form of a 14-foot (4.3&#160; m) solid red granite obelisk, and is still today the tallest grave marker in the cemetery. On the front of the obelisk is inscribed.
The right hand side of the monument lists the ten members of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Alice Ayres Memorial Committee<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, chaired by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Rev H. W. P. Richards<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. The <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Union Street<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> fire and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s rescue of the children caused great public interest from the outset, and the fire, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s death and funeral, and the fundraising for and erection of the memorial were all reported in detail in the local and national press and throughout the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>British Empire<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
The <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>British<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> government had traditionally paid little attention to the poor, but in the wake of the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Industrial Revolution<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> attitudes towards the accomplishments of the lower classes were changing. The growth of the railways, the mechanisation of agriculture and the need for labour in the new inner-city factories had broken the traditional feudal economy and caused the rapid growth of cities, while increasing literacy rates led to a greater interest in the media and current affairs among ordinary workers. In 1856 the first military honour for bravery open to all ranks, the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Victoria Cross<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, had been instituted, while in 1866 the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Albert Medal<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, the first official honour open to civilians of all classes, was introduced. Additionally, a number of private and charitable organisations dedicated to lifesaving, most prominently the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Royal Humane Society<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (1776) and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Royal National Lifeboat Institution<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (1824), were increasing in activity and prominence, and gave awards and medals as a means of publicising their activities and lifesaving advice.
Painter and sculptor <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>George Frederic Watts<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and his second wife, designer and artist <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mary Fraser Tytler<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, had long been advocates of the idea of art as a force for social change, and of the principle that narratives of great deeds would provide guidance to address the serious social problems of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>British<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> cities. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Watts<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> had recently painted a series of portraits of leading figures he considered to be a positive social influence, the "<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Hall of Fame<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>", which was donated to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>National Portrait Gallery<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>; since at least 1866 he had proposed as a companion piece a monument to "unknown worth", celebrating the bravery of ordinary people.
On 5 September 1887, a letter was published in <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>The Times<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> from <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Watts<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, proposing a scheme to commemorate the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Golden Jubilee<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Queen Victoria<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> by means of collecting and commemorating "a complete record of the stories of heroism in every-day life". He cited the death of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Alice Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> as an example of the type of event he proposed to commemorate, and included in his letter a distorted account of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s actions during the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Union Street<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> fire.
The roll would be a long one, but I would cite as an example the name of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Alice Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, the maid of all work at an oilmonger's in Gravel-lane, in April, 1885, who lost her life in saving those of her master's children.
.
The facts, in case your readers have forgotten them, were shortly these:—Roused by the cries of "Fire" and the heat of the fiercely advancing flames the girl is seen at the window of an upper story, and the crowd, holding up some clothes to break her fall, entreat her to jump at once for her life. Instead she goes back, and reappears dragging a feather bed after her, which, with great difficulty, she pushes through the window. The bed caught and stretched, the girl is again at the window, a child of three in her arms, which with great care and skill she throws safely upon the mattress. Twice again with still older children she repeats the heroic feat. When her turn comes to jump, suffocated or too exhausted by her efforts, she cannot save herself. She jumps, but too feebly, falls upon the pavement, and is carried insensibly to <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>St. Thomas's Hospital<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, where she dies.
— <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>George Frederic Watts<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Another Jubilee Suggestion<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, 5 Sep 1887.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Watts<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> had originally proposed that the monument take the form of a colossal bronze figure, but by 1887 was proposing that the memorial take the form of "a kind of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Campo Santo<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>", consisting of a covered way and marble wall inscribed with the names of everyday heroes, to be built in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Hyde Park<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Watts<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s suggestion was not taken up, leading <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Watts<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> to comment that "if I had proposed a race course round <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Hyde Park<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, there would have been plenty of sympathisers". However, his high profile lobbying further raised the already high public awareness of the death of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Alice Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Emilia Aylmer Blake<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> wrote perhaps the first poem about <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, titled <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Alice Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, which she recited at a social gathering in June 1885. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sir Francis Hastings Doyle<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> also wrote a well-received poem in honour of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, as did leading social reformer and women's rights campaigner <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Laura Ormiston Chant<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. By the late 1880s <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was coming to be seen as a model of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>British<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> devotion to duty, and her story was told in collections of heroic and inspirational stories for children, including as the first story in <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>F. J. Cross<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s influential <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Beneath the Banner<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, in which <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Cross<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> remarked that: "She had tried to do her best always. Her loving tenderness to the children committed to her care and her pure gentle life were remarked by those around her before there was any thought of her dying a heroic death. So, when the great trial came, she was prepared; and what seems to us Divine unselfishness appeared to her but simple duty.".
In 1890 a series of painted panels by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Walter Crane<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> were unveiled in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Octavia Hill's Red Cross Hall<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, 550 yards (500&#160; m) from the site of the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Union Street<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> fire. Inspired by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>George Frederic Watts<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s proposals, the panels depicted instances of heroism in everyday life; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Watts<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> himself refused to become involved in the project, as his proposed monument was intended to be a source of inspiration and contemplation as opposed to simply commemoration, and he felt that an artistic work would potentially distract viewers from the most important element of the cases, the heroic sacrifices of the individuals involved.
The first of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Price<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s panels depicted the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Union Street<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> fire. It is an idealised image depicting <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> as the rescued rather than the rescuer, blending religious imagery with traditional 19th-century symbols of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>British<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> heroism, and bears no relationship to actual events. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, in a long and flowing pure white gown, stands at a first floor window, surrounded in flames and holding a small child. A fireman stands on a ladder and reaches out to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and the child; meanwhile, a sailor in full <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Royal Navy<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> uniform holds a second child. Although in reality <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> had been at a much higher level of the building and the heat of the burning oil and gunpowder had made it impossible for the fire brigade to approach the building, by depicting <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> with the fireman and sailor, widely seen as symbols of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>British<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> heroism and <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>British<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> strength, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Price<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s picture further enhanced her growing reputation as a heroic figure. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Price<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s picture in the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Red Cross Hall<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> was itself mentioned in <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Alice Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, a border ballad by <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>National Trust<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> founder <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Canon Hardwicke Rawnsley<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> published in his 1896 <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Ballads of Brave Deeds<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, for which <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>George Frederic Watts<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> wrote the preface.
.
In 1898 <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>George Frederic Watts<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was approached by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Henry Gamble<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, vicar of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>St Botolph's Aldersgate church<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in the City of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>London<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>St Botolph<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s former churchyard had recently been converted, along with two smaller adjoining burial grounds, into <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Postman's Park<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, one of the largest public parks in the City of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>London<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, and the church was engaged in a protracted financial and legal dispute over ownership of part of the park. To provide a public justification for keeping the disputed land as part of the park, and to raise the park's profile and assist in fundraising, the church offered part of the park as a site for his proposed memorial. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Watts<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> agreed, and in 1900 the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Memorial to Heroic Self Sacrifice<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> was unveiled by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Alfred Newton<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, Lord Mayor of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>London<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mandell Creighton<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, Bishop of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>London<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. The Memorial consisted of a 50-foot (15&#160; m) long and 9-foot (2.7&#160; m) tall wooden loggia with a tiled roof, designed by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ernest George<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, sheltering a wall with space for 120 ceramic memorial tablets.
The memorial tablets were hand made and expensive to produce, and at the time of the Memorial's unveiling only four were in place. In 1902 a further nine tablets were unveiled, including the memorial to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Alice Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> for which <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Watts<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> had long lobbied. Made by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>William De Morgan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> in the Arts and Crafts style, the green-and-white tablet reads "<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Alice Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, daughter of a bricklayer's labourer who by intrepid conduct saved 3 children from a burning house in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Union Street<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, Borough, at the cost of her own young life April 24, 1885".
Although the public would have been familiar with the concept of a female national heroic figure following the widespread coverage and public admiration of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Harriet Newell<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Grace Darling<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Florence Nightingale<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, the ongoing coverage of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and her elevation as a national hero was unusual for the period. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was an uneducated working class woman, who after her death underwent what has been described as "a secular canonisation", at a time when, despite the gradual formal recognition of the contributions of the lower classes, national heroes were generally male and engaged in exploration, the military, religion or science and engineering.
This was a period in which political pressures for social reform were growing. The version of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> presented to the public as a woman devoted entirely to duty embodied the idealised <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>British<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> character at the time, while the image of a hard working but uncomplaining woman who set the welfare of others above her own embodied the idealised vision of the working class presented by social reformers, and the ideal selfless and dedicated woman presented by campaigners for women's rights. At the unveiling of the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Memorial to Heroic Self Sacrifice<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> the Lord Mayor, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Alfred Newton<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, had remarked that it was "intended to perpetuate the acts of heroism which belonged to the working classes", while <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>George Frederic Watts<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, although he was opposed in principle to discrimination based on class and saw the Memorial as being theoretically open to all classes, had remarked that "the higher classes do not or ought not to require reminders or inducements". <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Watts<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> saw the purpose of his Memorial not as a commemoration of deeds, but as a tool for the education of the lower classes.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Watts<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s view was shared by others who sought to provide inspirational material on <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>British<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> heroes, and authors writing about <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> systematically altered the fact that the children rescued were members of her family, instead describing them as the children of her employer. Press reports at the time of the fire described <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> variously as a "little nursemaid", "a willing, honest, hard-working servant", and a "poor little domestic". As well as <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Watts<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s 1887 description of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> as "the maid of all work at an oilmonger's", <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Cross<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s chapter on <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> in <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Beneath the Banner<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> is titled "<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Only a Nurse Girl!<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>", while <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Rawnsley<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> called her "the nursemaid in the household". <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Barrington<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, writing five years after the fire at the unveiling of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Price<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s panel, acknowledges in a footnote that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was related to the <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Chandlers<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, but nonetheless describes her as displaying the "typical <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>English<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> virtues—courage, fortitude, and an unquestioning sense of duty".
While <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>George<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mary<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Watts<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and their fellow paternalist social reformers, along with the broadly sympathetic mainstream <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>British<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> press, portrayed <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> as an inspirational selfless servant to her employer, others had a different view. The left-wing <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Reynolds Weekly Newspaper<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> complained that the lack of support for <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s family from the state was symbolic of poor treatment of workers as a whole. The pioneering feminist periodical <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>The Englishwoman's Review<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> described their "righteous pride" at <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s "instinctive motherhood"; on the other hand <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Young England<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, an imperialist children's story paper, said that "there is no sex in self-sacrifice", lauding <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> as a model of devotion to duty.
In 1936 the new Labour administration of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>London County Council<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> renamed <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>White Cross Street<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, near the site of the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Red Cross Hall<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and the scene of the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Union Street<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> fire, to <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Ayres Street<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in tribute to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Alice Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, a name it retains today. The <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Chandlers<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>' house at <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>194 Union Street<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> no longer stands, and the site is occupied by part of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Union House<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> office complex; immediately opposite the site of the fire is the present-day headquarters of the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>London<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Fire Brigade<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Alice Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> came to renewed public notice with the release of the 1997 play <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Closer<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Patrick Marber<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and the 2004 <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>BAFTA Award<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>- and <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Golden Globe<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>-winning film <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Closer<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> based on it starring <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Natalie Portman<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Julia Roberts<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Jude Law<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Clive Owen<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. A key plot element revolves around the memorial tablet to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Postman's Park<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, in which it is revealed that the character <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Jane Jones<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (played by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Portman<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> in the film), who calls herself <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Alice Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> for most of the story, has in fact fabricated her identity based on the tablet on the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Memorial to Heroic Self Sacrifice<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, which she reads at the time of her first meeting with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Dan Woolf<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (played by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Jude Law<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> in the film) at the beginning of the action. The park, and the memorial to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ayres<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, feature prominently in the opening and closing scenes of the film.
