<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Charles Glover Barkla<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>7 June 1877<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>23 October 1944<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) was a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>British<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> physicist, and the winner of the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Nobel Prize<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> in Physics in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1917<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> for his work in X-ray spectroscopy and related areas in the study of X-rays (<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Roentgen<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> rays).
Barkla was born in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Widnes<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>England<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, and he studied at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Liverpool Institute<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and at <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Liverpool University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1899<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Barkla<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> went to <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Trinity College<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Cambridge<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, as an Exhibition Scholar to work in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Cavendish Laboratory<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> under the physicist <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>J. J. Thomson<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. At the end of a year and a half, his love of music led him to move on to <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>King's College<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Cambridge<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, where he joined its chapel choir. He completed his bachelor of arts degree in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1903<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, and then his Master of Arts degree in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1907<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. No information seems to be available about when or where he earned a Doctor of Philosophy (Ph.D.) degree, but it is known that the great physicists J.J. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Thompson<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (the discoverer of the electron) and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Oliver Lodge<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> were his doctoral advisors.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1913<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, after having worked at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Universities of Cambridge<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Liverpool<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>King's College<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>London<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Barkla<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was appointed as a professor of natural philosophy at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Edinburgh<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, a position that he held until his death. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Barkla<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> married <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mary Esther Cowell<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1907<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Barkla<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> made significant progress in developing and refining the laws of X-ray scattering, X-ray spectroscopy, the principles governing the transmission of X-rays through matter, and especially the principles of the excitation of secondary X-rays. For his discovery of the characteristic X-rays of elements, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Barkla<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was awarded the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Nobel Prize<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> in Physics in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1917<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. He was also awarded the Hughes Medal of the British Royal Society that same year.
Little more seems to have been recorded about the life of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Charles Barkla<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
The lunar crater <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Barkla<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was named in the honor of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Charles Barkla<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. Also a commemorative plaque has been installed in the vicinity of the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Canongate<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, near the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Faculty of Education Buildings<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Edinburgh<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. Additionally, a lecture theatre at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Liverpool<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s Physics department is named after him.
