<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Maud de Boer-Buquicchio<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (born <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>December 28, 1944<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) is a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Dutch<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> jurist. She has served as Deputy Secretary General of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Council of Europe<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> since <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2002<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>De Boer-Buquicchio<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was born in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Hoensbroek<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Netherlands<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, and studied <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>French<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> language and literature and later law at <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Leiden University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. She specialized in international relations and labor law, obtaining her degree in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1969<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> with a thesis on the equality of treatment between women and men under <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>European Community<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> law.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>De Boer-Buquicchio<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> joined the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Council of Europe<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1969<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, and joined the legal Secretariat of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>European Commission of Human Rights<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. She later worked in a variety of positions in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Council of Europe<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> system, including in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Private Office of the Secretary General<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Council of Europe<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and as Deputy Registrar of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>European Court of Human Rights<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. She was elected Deputy Secretary General in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2002<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, and reelected in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2007<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>De Boer-Buquicchio<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> is married and has two sons.
