<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>David Alexander Colville<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, (born <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>August 24, 1920<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Toronto<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Ontario<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>) is a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Canadian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> painter.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Colville<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s family moved from <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Toronto<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> to <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Amherst<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Nova Scotia<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1929<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. He attended <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Mount Allison University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1938<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>-<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1942<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, graduating with a Bachelor of Fine Arts. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Colville<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> married <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Rhoda Wright<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> that year and enlisted in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Canadian Army<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> under the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>War Artist Program<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. During his four-year deployment to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>European Theatre<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, he was one of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Canada<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s most prominent war artists, famously painting troops landing at <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Juno Beach<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> on D-Day.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Colville<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> returned to <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>New Brunswick<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> after the war and became a faculty member with the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Fine Arts Department<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> at <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Mount Allison University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> where he taught from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1946<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>-<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1963<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. He left teaching to devote himself to painting and print-making full-time from a studio in his home on <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>York Street<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>; this building is now named <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Colville House<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Alex Colville<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> lived in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>St. Catharines<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Ontario<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, for three years before moving to <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Nova Scotia<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1973<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he moved his family to his wife's hometown of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Wolfville<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Nova Scotia<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> where they lived in the house that her father built and in which she was born. The <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Colvilles<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> have three sons, a daughter, and eight grandchildren. In contrast to many of his contemporaries, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Colville<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> aligned himself with the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Progressive Conservative Party of Canada<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and was a card-carrying party member for many years.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Colville<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> has exhibited extensively across <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Canada<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and internationally including at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Tate Gallery<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>London<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Beijing Exhibition Centre<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Beijing<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1983<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> an international touring retrospective of his work was organized by the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Art Gallery<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Ontario<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Alex Colville<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s work is found in many collections including the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Art Gallery<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Nova Scotia<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Cape Breton University Art Gallery<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Sydney<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Nova Scotia<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Museum of Modern Art<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>New York<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Musée National D'Art Moderne<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Paris<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>National Gallery of Canada<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Ottawa<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Centre National d'Art et de Culture Georges Pompidou<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Paris<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Wallraf-Richartz Museum<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Cologne<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Kestner Gesellschaft<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Hannover<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Germany<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.
This <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1963<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> painting is perhaps his best-known work.
This <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1954<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> work was inspired by two lines from the poet <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Roy Campbell<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>:.
"<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Horse and Train<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>" is a part of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Art Gallery<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hamilton<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s permanent collection; <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Dominion Foundries and Steel, Ltd.<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Dofasco Inc<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>) donated the painting in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1957<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. It appears on the cover of the album <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Night Vision<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bruce Cockburn<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Alex Colville<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and "<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Horse and Train<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>" are mentioned in the introduction (and in the story itself) of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Nova Scotia<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> fiction writer <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Barry Wood<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s short story Nowhere to Go published in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>England<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s Postscripts #14 in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2008<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
His mural in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Tweedie Hall<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> at <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Mount Allison University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, known officially as "<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>The History of Mount Allison<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>" or "<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>The Circuit Rider<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, " features a centrepiece of a large rear end of a horse. This "horse's ass painting, " as it is often known, is viewed by some as brilliant and by some as appalling. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Colville<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> chose not to explain the significance of the work.
His <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1967<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> painting "<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Pacific<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>", showing a man leaning against an open door looking out to sea while a pistol rests on a table in the foreground, inspired one of the definitive scenes in the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1995<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> film <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Heat<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> with actor <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Robert De Niro<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
Painted in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1953<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, its sale at auction for $1.287 million set a record for a work by a living <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Canadian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> artist. Part of the estate of the late <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>G. Hamilton Southam<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1918<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>-<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2008<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>), it was sold at an auction of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Canadian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> post-war and contemporary art by <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Heffel Fine Art Auction House<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>November 25, 2010<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. Expected to get up to $600, 000, the price inflated during a three-way bidding war between two <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Canadian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> phone bidders and a person at the auction.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Colville<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> designed the images on the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Canadian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1867<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>-<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1967<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> centennial commemorative coin set. The set consists of the following designs: Rock dove on 1 cent coin, rabbit on 5 cent coin, mackerel on 10 cent coin, lynx on 25 cent coin, wolf on 50 cent coin and goose on the 1 dollar coin.
