<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Françoise Tulkens<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (born <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>12 September 1942<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) is a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Belgian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> lawyer and expert in criminal and penal law, and Vice-President of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>European Court of Human Rights<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. She has been a member of the Court since 1998, Section President since 2007 and Vice-President since <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>February 2011<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Tulkens<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was born in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Brussels<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, the capital of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Belgium<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. She studied Law, earning a doctorate in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1965<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and practising at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Bar<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> until <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1968<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, when she was appointed <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Research Fellow<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> with the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Belgian National Fund for Scientific Research<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Fonds National de la Recherche Scientifique<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>). She was awarded the agrégation (higher education teaching qualification) in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1976<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and the same year took up a post as Professor of Law in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Université catholique de Louvain<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>French<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>-speaking <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Catholic University of Leuven<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>), where she remained until her appointment as a permanent judge at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>European Court of Human Rights<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Strasbourg<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.
Alongside her post at <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Leuven<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Tulkens<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was Chairwoman of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Scientific Committee of the European Law-making Research Group<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Paris<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>) from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1993<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1998<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and editor-in-chief of the journal, <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Revue internationale de droit pénal<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1994<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1998<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. From <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1996<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1997<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, she was an Expert for the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>European Committee for the Prevention of Torture<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. She has also been a Visiting Professor at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Universities of Geneva<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Ottawa<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Paris I<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Pantheon-Sorbonne<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>) and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Rennes<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1 November 1998<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, she became a Judge of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>European Court of Human Rights<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in respect of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Belgium<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. She was elected a Section President in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2007<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1 February 2011<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> became one of two Vice-Presidents of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Court<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, along with the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>British<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> judge, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sir Nicolas Brazta<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, and under <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>French<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> President <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Jean-Paul Costa<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
