<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Miguel de Bonilla y Laya-Bolívar<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1763<tag name="DATE" value="end"/><tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1826<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) was a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Costa Rican<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Roman<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Catholic<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> priest and politician. He was one of the signatories of the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Costa Rican Declaration of Independence<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bonilla<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was baptized in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Cartago<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Costa Rica<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>September 30, 1763<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. His parents were Sargent Major <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Andrés de Bonilla y Sáenz<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>María Gertrudis de Laya-Bolívar y Miranda<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>José Santiago de Bonilla y Laya-Bolívar<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, president of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Costa Rica<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s governing junta in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1822<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, was his brother.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bonilla<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was ordained as a priest in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Guatemala<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. He was in charge of several parishes in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Costa Rica<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and was the proprietor of valuable ranching property. He was called by the nickname <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Padre Tiricia<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Father Jaundice<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>), apparently because he suffered from the disease.
The ayuntamientos of the town of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Bagaces<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, the city of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Esparza<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, and several indigenous peoples designated <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bonilla<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>October 1821<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> as their representative in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Junta de Legados de los Ayuntamientos<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> that met in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Cartago<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>October 25<tag name="DATE" value="end"/><tag name="DATE" value="start"/>26<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1821<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to discuss <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Costa Rica<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s independence from <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Spain<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>October 29, 1821<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he attended the session of the ayuntamiento of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Cartago<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> en which the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Costa Rican Declaration of Independence<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> was ratified.
He was one of the members of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Costa Rican republican party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> during the era of independence. He was in the neighborhood of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Cartago<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s parish church when the royalist coup of <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>March 29, 1823<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> was announced. One of the supporters of the empire, the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Catalan<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Juan Freses de Ñeco<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, son-in-law of the royalist military commander <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Joaquín de Oreamuno y Muñoz de la Trinidad<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, shouted, "Padre Tiricia returns, because we will kill him!" (¡Ese padre Tiricia que se vuelva, porque lo matamos!), and immediately shot him with a bullet that pierced his cassock. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bonilla<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> walked to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Alajuela<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Rafael Francisco Osejo<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, president of the toppled government, and there they convinced <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Gregorio José Ramírez y Castro<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> to command the republican forces, who defeated the royalists in the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Battle of Ochomogo<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> the following <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>April 5<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bonilla<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> died of a heart attack in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Cartago<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Costa Rica<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>August 1826<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
