<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sophie Pemberton<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1869<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>-<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1959<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) was a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Canadian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> painter.
Born in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Victoria<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>British Columbia<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, she was the daughter of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Teresa Jane Grautoff<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Joseph Despard Pemberton<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1821<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>-<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>93<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>). A successful executive with the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Hudson's Bay Company<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and the first Surveyor-General of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Vancouver Island<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, her father could afford to send her to live and study in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Paris<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Académie Julian<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Pemberton<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> painted at a time when her chosen mediums had been the exclusive domain of men and her <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>European<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> influences can be seen in her work. The painter of both portraits and landscapes, <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Pemberton<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> was the first artist from the province of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>British Columbia<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> to receive international acclaim when her work was exhibited at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Royal Academy<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>London<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, including her award-winning <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1897<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> work seen here titled "Little Boy Blue.".
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1905<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, she married <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Arthur Beanlands<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, an <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Anglican<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> priest. He died in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1917<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and she eventually married <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Horace Deane-Drummond<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. Beyond her work on canvas, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sophie Pemberton<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> taught painting to local female artists. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1909<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> she did the artistic decoration for the non-denominational <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Pemberton Memorial Chapel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> gifted by her family to <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Victoria's Royal Jubilee Hospital<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sophie Pemberton<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> died in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1959<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Victoria<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and was interred there in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Ross Bay Cemetery<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
