No reason has been cited for the Wikify tag on this article.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Joseph Plaskett<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (born <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>12 July 1918<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>New Westminster<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>British<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Columbia<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>), mainly known as <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Joe Plaskett<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, is a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Canadian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> painter. He studied with many prominent <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Canadian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> painters like <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>A.Y. Jackson<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Jack Shadbolt<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lawren Harris<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Jock Macdonald<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Joe Plaskett<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was a pupil of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hans Hofmann<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>New York<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Provincetown<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1947<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1948<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1950<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he arrived in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Paris<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> where he studied with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Fernand Léger<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Jean Lombard<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, etching and engraving with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Stanley William Hayter<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. He taught intermittently in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Canada<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> until <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1957<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. After that date he settled definitely in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Paris<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> where his studio became an informal salon for <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Canadian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> painters, writers, poets and filmmakers, interfacing with artists from other countries.
In the Spring of <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2001<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he received the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Order of Canada<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> for his excellence in the field of visual art.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Joseph Plaskett<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> is considered to be one of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Canada<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>’s most talented and established painters. Since the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1940<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>s, he has had over 65 solo and group exhibitions, with work in major public, private and corporate collections, including the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>National Gallery<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Canada<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Plaskett<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> studied art in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Banff<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>San Francisco<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>New York<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>London<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Paris<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. He has lived in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Paris<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> since <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1951<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, and more recently in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Suffolk<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>England<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. His chosen subjects have always been intimate expressions of everyday life – interiors, still life, and portraits of friends and models. There is a warm humanity to his work, a love of light and form and colour that is evident in every painting he produces. The works are composed with such superb quality of painting that the ensuing results are masterworks of visual delight.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2004<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he set up The <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Joe Plaskett Foundation<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> which makes an annual award to a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Canadian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> artist to enable them to travel to <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Europe<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> to grow and study.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Plaskett<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s 90th birthday occurred in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2008<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. To celebrate, exhibitions were held in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Montreal<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Ottawa<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Toronto<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, and <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Vancouver<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Plaskett<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> continues to paint daily and his work is held in many collections worldwide.
.
