<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ann Power<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (born <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>23 November 1962<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Dublin<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Ireland<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>) is an <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Irish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> lawyer and academic, and since <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>22 January 2008<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> has been the judge in respect of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Ireland<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>European Court of Human Rights<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, the international tribunal tasked with enforcement of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>European Convention on Human Rights<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> amongst the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Council of Europe<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s forty-seven Member States. Her term on the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Court<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> will end in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2014<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Power<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was born on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>23 November 1962<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Dublin<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, the capital of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Ireland<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. She studied <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>English<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> and <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Philosophy<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Mater Dei Institute of Education<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in the city from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1980<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1984<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> (B.Rel.Sc. <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1984<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>), and for a Master of Education degree at <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Trinity College<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Dublin<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, specialising in <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Philosophy<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1984<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1987<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, graduating first class both times. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1986<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, she began working as a secondary school <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>English<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> teacher, and in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1987<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> combined this with lecturing in <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Philosophy<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. From <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1989<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1991<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, whilst still teaching and lecturing, she studied for a Diploma in Legal Studies from the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>King's Inns<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, the institution through which barristers are admitted to legal practice in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Ireland<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, and from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1991<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1993<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> undertook legal training there as a barrister, winning the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>John Brooke Scholarship<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> for first place in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Ireland<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in the final Bar examinations. She later completed a D.Phil. in Jurisprudence and <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Legal Philosophy<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> at <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University College<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Oxford<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Power<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was admitted as a barrister in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1993<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and worked as an advocate before the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Superior Courts of Ireland<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, whilst continuing to lecture in <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Philosophy<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. She developed a practice in <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Constitutional<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Public<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> and <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Medical law<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, as well as Immigration and Asylum law, and from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1998<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2003<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> was a lecturer in Jurisprudence at <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>King's Inns<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2006<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, she was appointed <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Senior Counsel<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (postnominal <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>SC<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>), a similar position to <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Queen's Counsel<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>United Kingdom<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, at one point representing <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Taoiseach<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (Prime Minister) of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Ireland<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bertie Ahern<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>September 2007<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Power<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was nominated under <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Article 22 ECHR<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> along with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Fionnuala Ní Aoláin<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Roger Sweetman<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Parliamentary Assembly<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Council of Europe<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> to be considered for appointment as the judge in respect of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Ireland<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>European Court of Human Rights<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ní Aoláin<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> withdrew her candidacy shortly afterwards for personal reasons, and in her stead was nominated <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>David Keane<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>22 January 2008<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Power<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was elected, achieving 125 votes out of 173 cast. She was elected at the same time as the judges for <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Bulgaria<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Latvia<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Moldova<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Turkey<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, and is a member of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Section III of the Court<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. Her term will expire in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2014<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
Shortly after being appointed to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Court<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>July 2008<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Power<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> withdrew from participating in the case of A, B and C v <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Ireland<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, a case brought by three women challenging <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Ireland<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s controversial abortion laws. She did so under Rule 28 of the Rules of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Court<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, which restricts a judge from participating in consideration of a case where they will or may not be able to be impartial, for example where a family member is involved or they have previousy acted in the matter. She was originally to be replaced in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Grand Chamber<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> hearing by <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>High Court<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> judge Mr <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Justice Nicholas Kearns<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, however he withdrew on being appointed President of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>High Court<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, and she was instead replaced by Mrs <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Justice Mary Finlay Geoghegan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>High Court<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> judge and wife of then <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Supreme Court<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> judge <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hugh Geoghegan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Power<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> lists her interests as including drama, singing, travelling, painting and hillwalking. She speaks <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>English<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Irish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>French<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> and <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Polish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. From <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1988<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2000<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, she was an appointed member of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Academic Council of All Hallows College<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Roman<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Catholic<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> college in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Drumcondra<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Dublin<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, linked to <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Dublin City University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
