<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Gradimir V. Milovanović<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>January 2, 1948<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) is a mathematician from <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Serbia<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> known for his contributions to approximation theory and numerical analysis. He has published over 150 papers and authored twenty books in his area.
Born in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Zorunovac<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, in the <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Knjaževac<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> municipality of mideastern <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Serbia<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, he studied at <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Niš<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, obtaining a B.Sc. in electrical engineering and computer science (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1971<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>), an M.Sc. in mathematics (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1974<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) and a D.Sc. (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1976<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) on the thesis <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>On Some Functional Inequalities<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> advised by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Dragoslav Mitrinović<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. He was with the faculty of electronic engineering and the department of mathematics at the same place as, promoted to professor (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1986<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) and acting as rector (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2004<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>-<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>06<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>), until he joined the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Megatrend University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Belgrade<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2008<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>).
He has been a member of the board of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Mathematical Society of Serbia<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2003<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>-<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>06<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>), president of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Scientific Council of the Mathematical Institute<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> at <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Serbian Academy of Sciences and Arts<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Belgrade<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1997<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>-), vice president of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Scientific Society of Serbia<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2002<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>-) and president of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>National Council for Scientific and Technological Development<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2006<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>-).
