<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Slobodan Ka
ar<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (born <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>September 15, 1957<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) is a retired <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Bosnian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Serb<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> boxer, born in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Peruica<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> near <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Jajce<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Bosnia and Herzegovina<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, then <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>SFR Yugoslavia<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. He won the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Light Heavyweight Gold medal<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> for <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Yugoslavia<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> at the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1980<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Summer Olympics<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. In the same year, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ka
ar<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was named as. He is the younger brother of boxer <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Tadija Ka
ar<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, who won a silver medal at the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1976<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Summer Olympics<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ka
ar<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> turned pro in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1983<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and won his first 21 fights, including a victory over <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Eddie Mustafa Muhammad<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> to capture the vacant <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>IBF Light Heavyweight Title<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ka
ar<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> lost his next fight, a defense against <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bobby Czyz<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1986<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> via 5th round TKO. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ka
ar<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> retired the next year with a record of 2220.
.
