<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Renate Jaeger<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>30 December 1940<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> -) is a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>German<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> lawyer and judge of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>European Court of Human Rights<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. Her term at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Court<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> expired on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>30 December 2010<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Jaeger<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was born in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Darmstadt<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, a city in the state of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Hesse<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Germany<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, and studied Law at <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Cologne<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Munich<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Lausanne<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1968<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, after completing her legal training, she became a judge at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Sozialgericht of Düsseldorf<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>North Rhine-Westphalia<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. The <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Sozialgericht<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> ('social court') is the lowest of three courts dealing with social security matters, the higher courts being the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Landessozialgericht<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (state level) and national <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Bundessozialgericht<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Federal Social Court of Germany<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>).
Between <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1970<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1971<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Jaeger<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was seconded as a research assistant to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Bundessozialgericht<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, and in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1974<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> was promoted to sit on the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Landessozialgericht<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> for <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>North Rhine-Westphalia<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, remaining there until <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1987<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. From <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1976<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1979<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, she was again seconded as a research assistant, this time to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Bundesverfassungsgericht<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Federal Constitutional Court<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Germany<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1986<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, she was promoted to Presiding Judge at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Landessozialgericht<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, and in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1987<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> was called to join the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Bundessozialgericht<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
As well as being a member of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Federal Social Court<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Jaeger<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was appointed in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1988<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to sit on the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>State Constitutional Court<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>North Rhein-Westphalia<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. From <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1991<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1994<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, she took on a lectureship at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Münster<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>24 March 1994<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, she was appointed a judge of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Federal Constitutional Court<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Bundesverfassungsgericht<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>) in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>First Senate<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. She was also appointed Liaison Officer between the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Court<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Council of Europe<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Venice Commission<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>28 April 2004<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Jaeger<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was elected by the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Parliamentary Assembly<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Council of Europe<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> to be a judge on the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>European Court of Human Rights<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, based in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Strasbourg<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>France<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, with effect from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1 November<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> that year. On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>14 October<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, she received an honorary doctorate by the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Münster<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, and that Autumn was awarded the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Grand Cross of the Order of Merit<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Federal Republic of Germany<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Großes Verdienstkreuz mit Stern und Schulterband<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>). She was succeeded at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Federal Constitutional Court<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Reinhard Gaier<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2 July 2009<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, she was elected Vice-President of one of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Court<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s Sections. Her term at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Court<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> ended on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>30 December 2010<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, and she was succeeded by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Angelika Nussberger<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Jaeger<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> is a member of the board of trustees of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Aktion Deutschland Hilft<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, an alliance of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>German<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> emergency aid organisations.
