Politics and government of.
the Republic of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Turkey<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
Other countries&#160; Atlas.
Politics portal.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Köksal Toptan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1943<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>Rize<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) is a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Turkish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> lawyer, politician and a member of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Justice and Development Party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. He earlier served as government minister in three cabinets. He was the speaker of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Grand National Assembly of Turkey<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> between <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>August 2007<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>August 2009<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
He was educated in the Faculty of Law at <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Istanbul University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. He worked as a lawyer following his graduation. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Köksal Toptan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> entered politics first at regional level in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Zonguldak<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. Later, he was elected to the parliament as <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Deputy of Zonguldak<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Bartın<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. He served as Minister of State in the 6th <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Süleyman Demirel<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> cabinet (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>November 12, 1979<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> - <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>September 12, 1980<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>), as Minister of National Education in the 7th <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Demirel<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> cabinet (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>June 23, 1991<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> - <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>June 25, 1993<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) and then as Minister of Culture in the 2nd <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Tansu Çiller<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> cabinet (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>October 5, 1995<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> - <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>October 30, 1995<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>). During the government of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Justice and Development Party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>AK Party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>), he was the chairman of the parliament commission of justice between <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2003<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>-<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2007<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
Elected as deputy of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Zonguldak<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> from the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>AK Party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> again in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2007<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he was nominated by his party for the post of Speaker of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Parliament<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>August 8, 2007<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>August 9, 2007<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Köksal Toptan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was elected 23rd Speaker of the parliament, supported also by the opposition parties.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Köksal Toptan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> is married with three children.
On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>November 12, 1979<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he was appointed as a state minister in the <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Süleyman Demirel<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> government, a post he held until the military coup of <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>September 12, 1980<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. Banned from politics, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Toptan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> started to work as a lawyer and even represented <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Demirel<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, who was also banned from political activity. He became famous winning all the cases in which he defended <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Demirel<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1983<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he took an active role in the establishment of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>True Path Party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>DYP<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>), then led by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hüsamettin Cindoruk<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, and entered <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Parliament<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> for a second time as a <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Zonguldak<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> deputy in the interim elections held on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>September 28, 1986<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. In the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1991<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> elections, he became a deputy from <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Bartın<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and then was appointed minister of education. During his term, he introduced innovative projects such as open high schools and student transfers from the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Turkic republics<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
After <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Demirel<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was elected president in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1993<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he competed with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Tansu Çiller<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> for leadership of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>DYP<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> but was defeated and resigned from his post as education minister. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1995<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he served as culture minister and was re-elected as a <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Bartın<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> deputy in the general elections held in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>December<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> of that year. In the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1999<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> general elections, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Toptan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was unable to enter <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Parliament<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> but began to work as the chairman of a foundation promoting <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Turkey<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
Before the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2002<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> elections, he was invited by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Erdoğan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>AK Party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, was elected as a deputy from <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Zonguldak<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and was appointed chairman of the parliamentary <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Justice Commission<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, where he helped draft the new (<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>TCK<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>). Before <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Gül<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was first nominated for the presidency, his name was frequently mentioned as a possible candidate for that post. He was hospitalized at the hour when <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Gül<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>’s candidacy was announced and it was rumored backstage that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Toptan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>’s illness could be attributed to his disappointment about not being nominated.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Toptan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s wife is a former judge with the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Supreme Court of Appeals<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. During his term as education minister, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Toptan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> conducted appreciable work related to disabilities and encouraged the opening of numerous rehabilitation centers. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Toptan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>’s wife, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Saime Toptan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, is the chairwoman of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Turkish Training and Solidarity Foundation for the Disabled<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
