<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sir Vincent Evans<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>GCMG<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>MBE<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>20 October 1915<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> - <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>18 May 2007<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) was a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>British<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> diplomat and international lawyer, who served as Judge of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>European Court of Human Rights<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in respect of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>United Kingdom<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1980<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1991<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Evans<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was born in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>London<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and educated at <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Merchant Taylors' School<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Northwood<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Wadham College<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Oxford<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, where he obtained a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>1st Class Honours<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> degree in <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Jurisprudence<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1937<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>BCL<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> on a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Cassel Scholarship<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> from <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Lincoln's Inn<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1938<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. He was called to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Bar<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> at <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Lincoln's Inn<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1939<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> but joined the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Army<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> that year on the outbreak of the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Second World War<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, becoming a Lieutenant Colonel and appointed <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>MBE<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1945<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, and was appointed Legal Advisor to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>British Administration<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Cyrenaica<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, the eastern coastal region of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Libya<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
Upon leaving the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Army<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, he was appointed Assistant Legal Adviser to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Foreign Office<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1947<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and was involved in drafting of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>United Nations Universal Declaration of Human Rights<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, and became Legal Counsellor to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>UK Permanent Mission<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>UN<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1954<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. He left this post in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1959<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, at which time he was appointed Companion of the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Order of St Michael and St George<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>CMG<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>), and returned to the Foreign Officer as Legal Counsellor, being promoted to Deputy Legal Adviser in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1960<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and Legal Adviser in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1968<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. He chaired the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Council of Europe<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>European Committee on Legal Cooperation<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1969<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1971<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, and was appointed <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Knight Commander of the Order of St Michael and St George<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (<tag name="MISC" value="start"/><tag name="MISC" value="start"/>KCMG<tag name="MISC" value="end"/><tag name="MISC" value="end"/>) in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1970<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Knight Grand Cross<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>GCMG<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>) in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1976<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, and <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Queen's Counsel<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1973<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
He retired from the Foreign Office in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1975<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> but remained involved in international legal affairs. He served as the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>UK<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s Representative to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Council of Europe Steering Committee on Human Rights<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1976<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1980<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, and chaired the group in his last year there. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1977<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he became a Member of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>United Nations Human Rights Committee<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and was its Vice-Chairman from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1979<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1980<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. He left the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Committee<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1984<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and was succeeded by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Dame Rosalyn Higgins<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, who went on to become the first female member of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>International Court of Justice<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, and its President from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2006<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2009<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. He was also a Member of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Permanent Court of Arbitration<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1987<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1997<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1980<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he was elected the judge in respect of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>United Kingdom<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> at the then non-permanent <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>European Court of Human Rights<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Strasbourg<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, succeeding Sir <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Gerald Fitzmaurice<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, also a former Foreign Office lawyer and judge of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Permanent Court of Arbitration<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. He spent ten years at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Court<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, taking part in a number of significant judgements including <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Dudgeon v United Kingdom<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, and retired in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1991<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
He was Vice-President of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>British Institute of Human Rights<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1992<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2004<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, a member of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Advisory Board of the Centre for International Human Rights Law<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Essex<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1983<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1994<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, and a member of the Council of Management of the British Institute of International and Comparative Law from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1969<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2005<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Evans<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> married <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Joan Mary Symons<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1947<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, with whom he had a son and two daughters. He was a keen gardener and a member of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Athenæum<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. He died on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>18 May 2007<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
