<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Nuala Ahern<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (née <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>MacDowell<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>; born <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>5 February 1949<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Omeath<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>County Louth<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>) is a former <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Irish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Green Party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> member of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>European Parliament<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> representing <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Leinster<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Ireland<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1994<tag name="DATE" value="end"/><tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2004<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. Ahern became active in politics in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1991<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> becoming elected to <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Wicklow County Council<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. She joined the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Green Party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1989<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
Her involvement in politics began through community action in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Wicklow<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> to prevent sewage pollution into the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Irish Sea<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. She is a long-term anti-nuclear campaigner, promoting the use of renewable energy. She grew up in the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Cooley<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> peninsula of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>North County Louth<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> which is close to the plutonium reprocessing plant in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Sellafield<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> on the West coast of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>UK<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. She campaigned against the construction of a nuclear power plant in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Carnsore Point<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>County Wexford<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in the late <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1970<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>s and for the closure of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Sellafield<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> which still operates today. She campaigned against the use of genetically modified food stating concerns of inadequate scientific knowledge. She has also campaigned against animal testing in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>European Union<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
In the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>European Parliament<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ahern<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was vice-president of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Petitions Committee<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, vice-president of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Committee on Industry, External Trade, Research & Energy<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, member of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Culture Committee<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Legal Affairs Committee<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and president of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Intergroup on Complementary and Natural Medicine<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ahern<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> is founding member of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Irish Women's Environment Network and the Wicklow Greens<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
Her father <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Vincent MacDowell<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> from <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Newry<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, is a former councillor and political activist, a former vice chairman of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Northern Ireland Civil Rights Association<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and a representative of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Green Party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Labour Party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
.
.
.
.
.
.
.
.
