<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Stepa Stepanovi OSS OCT GCMG<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Serbian Cyrillic<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>: , pronounced&#160; ; <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>11 March<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> [O.S. <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>28 February<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>] <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1856<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> - <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>April 29, 1929<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) was a field marshal (vojvoda) of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Serbian Army<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> who distinguished himself in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Serbia<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s wars from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1876<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1918<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Stepa Stepanovi<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was born in the village of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Kumodra~<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> outside of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Belgrade<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>11 March<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> [O.S. <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>28 February<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>] <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1856<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. He joined the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Serbian army<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1874<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, as a cadet in the artillery school.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Stepanovi<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> obtained significant achievements in the war against the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Turks<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, especially in the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Battle of Adrianople<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>March 1913<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> during the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>First Balkan War<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>.In the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Second Balkan War<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> his forces were deployed in the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Nia<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> region with an encampment in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Pirot<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.
At the beginning of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>World War I<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> he acted as the representative of then absent chief of staff <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Radomir Putnik<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. He was responsible for mobilization and some war preparations. After <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Putnik<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s return he took command of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Second Army<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. In <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>World War I<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, he led the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Serbian army<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in a great victory in the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Battle of Cer<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, where his <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Second Army<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> completely defeated the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Austrian Fifth Army<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, arriving to the scene after a forced march. This was the first allied victory of the war, and he was promoted to Vojvoda (Field-Marshal). His army achieved successes in the Battle of the Drina and Battle of Kolubara , in addition to the defence of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Serbia<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1915<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1918<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> he was again in command of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Second Army<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> which was a part of the large <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Allied<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> offensive in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Macedonia<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, they achieved a breakthrough on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>September 15<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. The <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Second Army<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> advanced to the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Bulgarian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> border and from there, after <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Bulgarian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> capitulation on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>September 29, 1918<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> turned West towards <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Bosnia<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Adriatic sea.<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>
He was an active officer until the end of <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1919<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, when he retired from service as the commander in chief of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Serbian army<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. During his career he was also serving as the minister of the army on two occasions.
He was decorated with the "Takovski krst sa ukratenim ma
evima" medal for bravery during the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1876<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>-<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1878<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> wars against the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Turks<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. He was also awarded the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Knight Grand Cross<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>GCMG<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>) of The <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Most Distinguished Order of Saint Michael<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> and <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Saint George<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. He died in the town of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>a
ak<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>April 29, 1929<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
.
