<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lothar Bisky<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (born 17 August 1941) is a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>German<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> politician. He was the chairman of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Party of Democratic Socialism<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>PDS<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>), the successor of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>East Germany<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>'s <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Socialist Unity Party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>SED<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>). In June 2007 he became co-chairman of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>The Left<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Die Linke<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>) party, formed by a merger of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>PDS<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and the much smaller <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Labour and Social Justice  The Electoral Alternative<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. From 2007 until 2010 he was the President of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Party of the European Left<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. Also, he is the Publisher of the socialist newspaper <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Neues Deutschland<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bisky<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was born in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Zollbrück<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Germany<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> (now <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Korzybie<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Pomeranian Voivodeship<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Poland<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>). After an impoverished youth in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>northern West Germany<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, he emigrated to the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>GDR<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> at the age of 18, and after facing initial doubts due to his heritage was allowed to join the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Socialist Unity Party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in 1963, but did not rise to leadership positions until shortly after the fall of communism and the resulting purge of hardliners from the party. He was rector of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Film and Television<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Potsdam<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>-<tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Babelsberg<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>) from 1986 to 1990. In 1991 he became a member of the board of directors of regional television channel <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>ORB<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (now part of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>RBB<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>.).
In 1995, it was discovered that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bisky<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was a former informer for the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Stasi<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. The <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Stasi<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> records on his wife referred to his activities as an informant. Subsequent investigations revealed that <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bisky<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was registered with the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Stasi<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> with the code names of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bienert<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> from 1966 and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Klaus Heine<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> from 1987. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lothar Bisky<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was also described in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Stasi<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> records as "zuverlässig" (reliable), the highest level of trust for an informer.
When <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bisky<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was promoted, the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Hauptverwaltung Aufklärung<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Stasi<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> issued a statement where <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bisky<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was described as "a reliable comrade, who strictly follows orders and always is honest with the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Ministry for State Security<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Stasi<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>)" ("ein zuverlässiger Genosse, der sich strikt an die gegebenen Anweisungen hält und gegenüber dem MfS stets ehrlich war").
In 1990 he was a member of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Volkskammer<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and since 1990 he has been a member of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>state parliament<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Brandenburg<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.
He was chairman of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>PDS<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> from 1993 until his resignation in 2000 over a defeat for the executive committee on support for <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>United Nations<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> military intervention. He was re-elected chairman in 2003 after this "left turn" had cost the party its seats in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Bundestag<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in 2002. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bisky<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> is seen to be on the moderate, social democratic wing of the party and he is a long-time close ally of the party's most prominent figure, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Gregor Gysi<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. He is often regarded for his abilities to lead meaningful discussions between parties of completely opposite viewpoints, be it within his own party or in media events with other groups.
The party returned strongly to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Bundestag<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in the 2005 election. <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Bisky<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, one of 54 Left MPs, was nominated by his party to become one of the six vice presidents of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Bundestag<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. When the new <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Bundestag<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> was constituted on 18 October, however, he failed three times to be elected. Several MPs explained this with the fact that he was an informant of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Stasi<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. Later, he failed a fourth time, and subsequently gave up his bid for the vice president position which was given to <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Petra Pau<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> instead.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lothar Bisky<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> is married and the father of three sons. The oldest son, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Jens Bisky<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, is a journalist and writer and the second-oldest, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Norbert Bisky<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, is a painter. The youngest son, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Stephan Bisky<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, died in late 2008 while working towards his neuro-informatics doctorate at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Edinburgh<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
