<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Jean-Paul Costa<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (born <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>3 November 1941<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Tunis<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>) is a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>French<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> jurist and has been President of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>European Court of Human Rights<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> since <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>19 January 2007<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. He was first appointed a judge of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Court<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1 November 1998<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, and in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2009<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> was elected to serve an additional three years as President. His term at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Court<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> will end on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>3 November 2011<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Costa<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was born in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Tunis<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, capital of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Tunisia<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, and educated at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Lycée Carnot<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in the city, but his family left when the country declared independence in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1957<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. He was then educated at the prestigious <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Lycée Henri-IV<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Paris<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, before studying at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Institut d'Études Politiques de Paris<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, better known as <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Sciences Po<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, graduating with an undergraduate diploma in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1961<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, Master of Laws in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1962<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and Diploma of Superior Studies in Public Law in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1964<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. He then studied from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1964<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1966<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>École nationale d'administration<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>National Management School<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>).
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>June 1966<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Costa<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was appointed Auditeur in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Council of State<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, a body of the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>French<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> national government that provides the executive branch with legal advice and acts as the administrative court of last resort. From <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1968<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1973<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he lectured at <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Sciences Po<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, and from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1981<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1984<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> was Director of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Office of the Minister of National Education<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Alain Savary<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. From <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1985<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1986<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he led the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>French<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> delegation negotiating construction of the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Channel Tunnel<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, and from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1985<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1989<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> taught at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>International Institute of Public Administration<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. He was then appointed Visiting Professor at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Orléans<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1989<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>-<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1998<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) and the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Sorbonne<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1992<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>-<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1998<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>).
On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1 January<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he was appointed the judge in respect of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>France<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> at the newly-permanent <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>European Court of Human Rights<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1 May 2000<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he rose to become a Section President and on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1 November 2001<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> Vice-President of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Court<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>19 January 2007<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he succeeded <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Swiss<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Luzius Wildhaber<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> as President of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Court<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. He was re-elected to this post in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2009<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
The <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>British Government<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> is trying to find out if they want to proceed towards giving prisoners the voting right. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Jean-Paul Costa<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> is alreay worried that the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>UK<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> may turn in to what <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Greece<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> looked like under the rule of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Colonels<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
