<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Grigore Constantin Moisil<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Romanian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> pronunciation:&#160; ; <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>10 January 1906<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Tulcea<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Romania<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>  <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>21 May 1973<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Ottawa<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Canada<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>) was a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Romanian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> mathematician, computer pioneer, and member of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Romanian Academy<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. His research was mainly in the fields of mathematical logic, (<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Aukasiewicz-Moisil algebra<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>), <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Algebraic logic<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>MV-algebra<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, algebra and differential equations. He is viewed as the father of computer science in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Romania<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Moisil<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was also a member of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Academy of Sciences<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Bologna<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>International Institute of Philosophy<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1996<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>IEEE Computer Society<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> awarded him posthumously the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Computer Pioneer Award<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Grigore Moisil<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was born in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1906<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Tulcea<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> into an intellectual family. His grandfather, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Grigore Moisil<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1814<tag name="DATE" value="end"/><tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1891<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>), a clergyman, was one of the founders of the first <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Romanian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> high school in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Nsud<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. His father, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Constantin Moisil<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1867<tag name="DATE" value="end"/><tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1958<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>), was a history professor, archaeologist and numismatist; as a member of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Romanian Academy<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, he filled the position of Director of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Numismatics Office of the Academy<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. His mother, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Elena<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1863<tag name="DATE" value="end"/><tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1949<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>), was a teacher in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Tulcea<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, later the director of "<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Maidanul Dulapului<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>" school in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Bucharest<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> (now "<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Enchic Vcrescu<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>" school).
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Grigore Moisil<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> attended primary school in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Bucharest<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, then high school in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Vaslui<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Bucharest<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> (at "<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Spiru Haret" High School<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>) between <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1916<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>-<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1922<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1924<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> he was admitted at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Constructions Faculty of the Polytechnic University of Bucharest<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, and also the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Mathematics Faculty of the University of Bucharest<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. He showed a stronger interest in mathematics, so he quit the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Polytechnic University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1929<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, despite already having passed all the third-year exams. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1929<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> he defended his Ph.D. thesis, <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>La mécanique analytique des systemes continus<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Analytical mechanics of continuous systems<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>), before a commission led by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Gheorghe biceica<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Dimitrie Pompeiu<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Anton Davidoglu<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> as members. The thesis was published the same year by the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Gauthier-Villars<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> publishing house in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Paris<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, and received favourable comments from <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Vito Volterra<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Tullio Levi-Civita<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Paul Lévy<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1930<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Moisil<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> went to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Paris<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> for further study in mathematics, which he finalized the next year with the paper On a class of systems of equations with partial derivatives from mathematical physics. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1931<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> he returned to <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Romania<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, where he was appointed in a teaching position at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Mathematics Faculty of the University of Ia_i<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. Shortly after, he left for a one-year <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Rockefeller Foundation<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> scholarship to study in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Rome<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1932<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> he returned to Ia_i, where he remained for almost 10 years, developing a close relationship with professor <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Alexandru Myller<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. He taught the first modern algebra course in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Romania<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, named <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Logic and theory of proof<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Ia_i<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. During that time, he started writing a series of papers based on the works of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Jan Aukasiewicz<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> in multi-valued logic. His research in mathematical logic laid the foundation for significant work done afterwards in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Romania<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, as well as <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Argentina<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Yugoslavia<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Czechoslovakia<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, and <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Hungary<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. While in Ia_i, he completed research remarkable for the many new ideas and for his way of finding and using new connections between concepts from different areas of mathematics. He was promoted to Full Professor in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>November 1939<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1941<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, a position of professor at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Bucharest<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> opened up, and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Moisil<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> applied for it. However, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Gheorghe Vrânceanu<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Dan Barbilian<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Miron Nicolescu<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> also applied for the position, and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Vrânceanu<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> got it. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Moisil<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> approached the Ministry of Education, arguing that it would be a great opportunity for mathematics in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Romania<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> if all four could be appointed. As a result of his appeal, all four mathematicians were hired. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Moisil<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> moved to <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Bucharest<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, where he became a Professor in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Faculty of Mathematics<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> (later the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Faculty of Mathematics and Computer Science<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>) at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Bucharest<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>December 30, 1941<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
From <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1946<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1948<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Moisil<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> took a leave of absence, being named plenipotentiary envoy to <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Ankara<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. While in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Turkey<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, he gave several series of mathematics lectures at <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Istanbul University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Istanbul Technical University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1948<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he resumed teaching at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Bucharest<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. That same year, he was elected to the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Romanian Academy<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, and a member of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Institute of Mathematics of the Romanian Academy<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. After <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1965<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, one of his outstanding students-- <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>George Georgescu<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> -- worked closely with him on multi-valued logics, and after the emergence of <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Romania<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> from dictatorship in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1989<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he became a Professor of Mathematics and Logic at the same university and department as <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Moisil<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1991<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. His student also published extensive, original work on <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>algebraic logic<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>MV-algebra<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Algebra<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Algebraic topology<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, categories of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>MV-algebras<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>category theory<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> and <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Aukasiewicz-Moisil algebra<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Moisil<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> published papers on mechanics, mathematical analysis, geometry, algebra and mathematical logic. He developed a multi-dimensional extension of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Pompeiu's areolar derivative<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, and studied monogenic functions of one hypercomplex variable with applications to mechanics. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Moisil<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> also introduced some many-valued algebras, which he called <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Aukasiewicz algebras<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> (now also named <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Aukasiewicz-Moisil algebras<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>), and used them in logic and the study of automata theory. He created new methods to analyze finite automata, and had many contributions to the field of automata theory in algebra.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Moisil<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> had important contributions in the creation of the first <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Romanian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> computers. He played a fundamental role in the development of computer science in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Romania<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, and in raising the first generations of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Romanian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> computer scientists. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1996<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he was awarded posthumously the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Computer Pioneer Award<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> by the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers Computer Society<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Aukasiewicz logic<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>.
<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Aukasiewicz-Moisil algebras<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>.
Quantum computers.
<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>MV-algebra<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>.
Mathematical logic.
Categorical logic, Adjoint functors.
