<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Stephen Pollard<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (born ca. <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1965<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) is a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>British<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> author and journalist, currently editor of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>The Jewish Chronicle<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. He is a former Chairman of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>European Institute<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> for the Study of Contemporary <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Antisemitism<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> and a former president of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Centre for the New Europe<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, a free-market think tank based in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Brussels<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. He has written columns for several publications, including <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>The Times<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> and the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Daily Mail<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, and also maintains a blog.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Pollard<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> is an alumnus of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>John Lyon School<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Mansfield College<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Oxford<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.
He is an advocate of market-based public service reforms. He is also a frequent commentator on Israel, and a critic of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Jihadist<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> movements.
Formerly a journalist and leader-writer on the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Daily Express<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Stephen Pollard<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> left that paper in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2001<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> soon after it was taken over by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Richard Desmond<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, a publisher of pornographic magazines, who began implementing radical cutbacks. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Pollard<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s last leader for the paper, on the problems of the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>British<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> farming industry, turned out to contain the words "Fuck you, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Desmond<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>" spelt out with the first letter of each sentence. A standing job offer at <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>The Times<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> was withdrawn as they considered the acrostic in the article to be "unacceptable" and "insulting".
After early articles for the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Fabian Review<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1993<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> (e.g. "More Southern Discomfort", discussing ways by which the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Labour Party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> could reform itself sufficiently to regain power), <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Stephen Pollard<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s career has seen a fair degree of political movement from <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Left<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> to <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Right<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>; he was formerly an advisor to anti-<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>EU<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/><tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/> Labour<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> politician <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Peter Shore<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Pollard<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was one of the signatory founders, in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2005<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Henry Jackson Society<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, which advocates a proactive approach to the spread of liberal democracy across the world.
By <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2006<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Pollard<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> held the view that, in the "battle to save western civilisation", the "<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Left<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, in any recognisable form, is now the enemy". His biography of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Labour Party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> politician <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>David Blunkett<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, with the subject's involvement, was published in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2004<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>November 2008<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Pollard<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> became editor of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>The Jewish Chronicle<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. In his <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2009<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>New York Times<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> review of a book by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Bruce Bawer<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Pollard<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> endorsed the notion that "liberal appeasement" is paving the way for a "replacement" of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>European<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> civilization by radical Islamist ideology. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Pollard<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> has argued that the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Palestine Solidarity Campaign<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> has tipped over to <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>antisemitism<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> and the defence of attacks on <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Jews<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. Writing about the disruption of an appearance by the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israel Philharmonic Orchestra<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1 September 2011<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> at the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>BBC Proms<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> he asserted that the actions of pro-<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Palestinian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> activists had a "chilling air" reminiscent of "the way <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Nazi<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> party members broke up meetings" in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Weimar<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/><tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/> Germany<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.
