<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Avraham "Bren" Adan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (Hebrew: ‚¨}, born <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>October 1926<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) is a former Israeli general who served in the military between <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1947<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1973<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Adan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was born in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Kfar Gileadi<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>British Mandate Palestine<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1926<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. He joined the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Palmach<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1943<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. During the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1948<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Arab-Israeli War<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> he was a company commander in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>8th Battalion of the Negev Brigade<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and participated in <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Operation Uvda<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, in which the brigade captured the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Jordanian outpost of Umm Rashrash<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, now known as <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Eilat<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, at the southernmost tip of the newly-created country. It was he who raised the Ink Flag claiming the territory for <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Israel<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, as depicted in the famous photograph of the event.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Adan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> joined the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Armored Corps<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1949<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and founded the first Sherman tank unit in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>IDF<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. During the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1956<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> Suez War, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lieutenant Colonel Adan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> commanded the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>82nd battalion of the 7th Armored Brigade<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Sinai<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, defeating several Egyptian forces in the region. After the war he became the operations officer of the corps, then the commander of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>7th Brigade<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Armored Corps School<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. During the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>June 1967<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> Six-Day War, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Adan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was the deputy commander of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Armored Corps<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>31st Armored Division<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, fighting again in the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Sinai<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>March 10, 1969<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he became the commander of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Armored Corps<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Major General Adan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was defending the northern portion of the Israeli defense along the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Suez Canal<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> when the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>October 1973<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Yom Kippur War<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> broke out. As the commander of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>162nd Division<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, his division suffered severe losses from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>October 6<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>October 8<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, in to stop the Egyptian attack and push it back across the canal. Later on during the war he led his unit across the canal into Egyptian territory just north of the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Great Bitter Lake<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, during <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Operation Stouthearted Men<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. He then maneuvered his unit southward to <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Suez City<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, where his unit surrounded the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Egyptian Third Army<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
Between <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1974<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1977<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he served as the Armed Forces Attach√© at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Israeli embassy<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Washington, DC<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.
