<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>María Josefa Gabriela Cariño Silang<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>March 19, 1731<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> – <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>September 20, 1763<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) was the wife of the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Ilocano<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> insurgent leader, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Diego Silang<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. Following <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Diego<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>'s assassination in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1763<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, she led the group for four months before she was captured and executed.
Born in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Barangay Caniogan<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Santa<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Ilocos Sur<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Silang<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was a mestiza, of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Spanish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> and <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Ilocano<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> descent. The people of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Abra<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> do claim she was born in what is now <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Pidigan<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Abra<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> (those two places are not far from each other, and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Abra<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> was not incorporated as a province until early in the 20th century). She was adopted by a very wealthy businessman <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Tomás Millan<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, who later married her at the age of 20, but died after three years. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1757<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, she re-married, this time to 27-year-old <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Ilocano<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> insurgent leader, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Diego Silang<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. The groups’ goal was to ensure an independent Ilocos. She became one of his closest advisors, whenever the troops battle, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Gabriela<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> always went with them to give support and help with the battle, a major figure in her husband's collaboration with the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>British<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> and the brief expulsion of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Spanish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> officials from <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Vigan<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Ilocos Sur<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> during the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>British<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> occupation of the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Philippines<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.
Together with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Cariño<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sebatian Andaya<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Manuel Flores<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, there she regrouped her troops, and rallied the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Tingguian community<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> to fight. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Gabriela<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>’s troops of 2000 fighters attacked the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Spanish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Vigan<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>September 10, 1763<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. With a larger number of the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Spanish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> troops, the 6000 men strong <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Spanish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> garrison was ready, with amassing <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Spanish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Tagalog<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, and <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Kapampangan<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> soldiers, and <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Ilocano<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> collaborators recruited from other regions to ambush her and rout her forces. Many were killed. She escaped, alongside <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Cariño<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and seven others, but were caught on <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>September 20, 1763<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. They were summarily hanged.
A list of the closest living descendants of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>María Josefa Gabriela Cariño Silang<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>:.
Belonging to the family of the first <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Galician<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> who arrived in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Candon<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in late 17th century, Ignacio <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Cariño<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Gabriela<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Silang<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, the noted Ilokano revolutionary of the 18th century, was a daughter of Ignacio’s eldest son <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Anselmo<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Tingian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> house servant in the <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Cariño<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> household in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Candon<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. When her husband was executed, she fled to <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Abra<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and took refuge in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Tayum<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, in the house of her uncle Nicolas, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Anselmo<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>’s brother. The names above are the direct descendants of Nicolas and their ancestral home is home also today to the <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Cariño<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> museum "CASA MUSEO CARIÑO". Maintained with loving care by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Rosario<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Cariño<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> one can visit the room occupied by <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Gabriela<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> when she lived there.
The family are still living in the ancestral house and former headquarters of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Gabriela<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Silang<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Tayum<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Abra<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. It is now a <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Museum and Art Gallery<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> that holds one of the most diverse art work and Antique collections in the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Philippines<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> the collection includes Thousands of Antiques from all around the world with some paintings from great painters like <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Pablo Picasso<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Juan Luna<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Fernando Amorsolo<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Domenico Ghirlandaio<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Claude Monet<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Pierre-Auguste Renoir<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, XIX originals collected by the Family over the centuries.
More info will be added soon, as we are getting more info and stories no one else knows about <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Gabriela<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Silang<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> passed down to generation.
