<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Paolo Ferrero<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (born <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>17 November 1960<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Pomaretto<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Piedmont<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>) is an <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Italian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> politician, member of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Communist Refoundation Party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and former <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Italian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> Minister of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Social Solidarity<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Prodi II Cabinet<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ferrero<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was born in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Pomaretto<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, in the province of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Turin<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
A former <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>FIAT<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> worker, he started his political commitment at the age of 17, joining the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Proletarian Democracy party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. Unlike the majority of his party, <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ferrero<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> is religious and is a member of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Waldensian Evangelical Church<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and was the leader of the youth evangelical <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Waldensian federation<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> before fully entering politics in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1987<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. He served as <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Turin<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> city councillor from <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1993<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1997<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. He has two children, aged 18 and 12.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ferrero<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> is relatively new to national politics, as he was first elected as Member of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Parliament<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2006<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>. Prior to his appointment, in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2006<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, to the cabinet of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Prodi<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, he was responsible for the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Communist Refoundation Party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s social, economic and labour department. He is responsible for social policy, national civil service, non-<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>EU<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> immigrants and drug-related policies.
On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>27 July 2008<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ferrero<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was elected secretary of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Communist Refoundation Party<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, winning over the other major candidate <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Nichi Vendola<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Maurizio Acerbo<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Fausto Bertinotti<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Alberto Burgio<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Paolo Cacciari<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Francesco Caruso<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Luigi Cogodi<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Peppe De Cristofaro<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Titti De Simone<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Elettra Deiana<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Daniela Dioguardi<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Donatella Duranti<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Antonio Falomi<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Daniele Farina<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Paolo Ferrero<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Pietro Folena<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Francesco Forgione<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mercedes Frias<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Alfonso Gianni<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Franco Giordano<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Salvatore Iacomino<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Pietro Ingrao<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Angela Lombardi<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Vladimir Luxuria<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ramon Mantovani<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Graziella Mascia<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Gennaro Migliore<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Donatella Mungo<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sergio Olivieri<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Gian Luigi Pegolo<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Maria Cristina Perugia<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Marilde Provera<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Alì Rashid<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Andrea Ricci<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mario Ricci<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Augusto Rocchi<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Franco Russo<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Patrizia Sentinelli<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Sabina Siniscalchi<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Massimiliano Smeriglio<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Maurizio Zipponi<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Martino Albonetti<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Daniela Alfonzi<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Salvatore Allocca<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Maria Luisa Boccia<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Salvatore Bonadonna<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Giovanna Capelli<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Milziade Caprili<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Giovanni Confalonieri<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>José Luiz Del Roio<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Giuseppe Di Lello Finuoli<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Erminia Emprin<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Rina Gagliardi<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Fosco Giannini<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Claudio Grassi<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Heidi Guiliani<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Santo Liotta<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Luigi Malabarba<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Francesco Martone<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Lidia Menapace<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Maria Celeste Nardini<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Anna Maria Palermo<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Giovanni Russo Spena<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Tommaso Sodano<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Raffaele Tecce<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Tiziana Valpiana<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Olimpia Vano<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Stefano Zuccherini<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Vittorio Agnoletto<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Giusto Catania<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Corrado Gabriele<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Luisa Morgantini<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>&#160; <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Roberto Musacchio<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>.
