<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Félix Édouard Justin Émile Borel<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>7 January 1871<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> – <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>3 February 1956<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) was a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>French<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> mathematician and politician.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Borel<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was born in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Saint-Affrique<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Aveyron<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>. Along with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>René-Louis Baire<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> and <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Henri Lebesgue<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, he was among the pioneers of measure theory and its application to probability theory. The concept of a <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Borel<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> set is named in his honor. One of his books on probability introduced the amusing thought experiment that entered popular culture under the name infinite monkey theorem or the like. He also published a series of papers (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1921<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>-<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>27<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) that first defined games of strategy.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1913<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> and <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1914<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> he bridged the gap between hyperbolic geometry and special relativity with expository work.
In the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1920<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>s, <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1930<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>s, and <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1940<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>s he was active in politics. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1922<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> he founded <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>ISUP<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, the oldest <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>French school for Statistics<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. From <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1924<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> to <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1936<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he was a member of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>French National Assembly<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1925<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, he was <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Minister of Marine<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. During the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Second World War<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> he was a member of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>French Resistance<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Borel<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> died in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Paris<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1956<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
Besides the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Centre Émile Borel<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Institut Henri Poincaré<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Paris<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and a crater on the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Moon<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, the following mathematical notions are named after him:.
<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Doctoral studies&#160;<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> : <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>European Doctoral College<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Lille<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Nord-Pas de Calais<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> •.
<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Campus Lille<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> I&#160; : <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Lille University of Science and Technology<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> • <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>École centrale de Lille<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> •.
<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Campus Lille II<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>&#160; : <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Lille University of Health and Law<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> •.
<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Institut Pasteur de Lille<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> •.
<tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Campus Lille III<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>&#160; : <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Lille University Charles de Gaulle for humanities, social sciences, litterature and arts<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>•.
<tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Campus Artois<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>&#160; : <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Artois University • École des Mines de Douai<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> •.
<tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Campus Littoral<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>&#160; : <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of the Littoral Opal Coast<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> •.
 .
 .
 .
 .
 .
 .
