<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Olivia Peguero<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> is a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Dominican<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> contemporary landscape and botanical artist. Painting most of the year in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Dominican Republic<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Florida<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, she is known for producing all of her studies and the majority of her finished pieces en plein air. Unlike many other <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Dominican<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> artist, her works are created in oil using a more traditional <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>European<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> style, many times depicting life as birth, existence and death within her flowers. Two common themes present in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Peguero<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> art are the conservation of old growth <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Dominican<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> forests and pride in <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Dominican<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> heritage. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2005<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, she made news when a private collector requested a commission and was turned down for asking her to paint a beach in the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>DR<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> but label the art as it was from another <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Caribbean<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> country. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2007<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, Mrs. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Peguero<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> enlisted the help of a few important collectors and corporate sponsors to form the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Peguero Arte Libros Foundation<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Art Books for Education<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> Program. Today, a large percentage of the proceeds from the sale of her art are donated to the foundation.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Olivia Peguero<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> was born in the <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Dominican Republic<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, and grew up in the small towns of <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Miches<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> on the east coast, and <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Las Salinas<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in the southwest. She attended the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Mahatma Gandhi secondary school<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Santo Domingo<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and after graduation, moved to <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>New York<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> to join her parents who had immigrated a few years prior. Although she was mostly isolated from the arts as a child, she was strongly influenced by the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Dutch<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> Masters style and it seemed only natural that the same style be applied in a lush, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Caribbean<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> environment. Today, many people associate <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Peguero<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> art as only tropical or island oriented, but much of her work and training focused on mastering traditional architecual, botanical and landscape methods with her early paintings often being completed in and around the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Lake District<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>England<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.
Mrs. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Peguero<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> attended university in <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>New York<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Florida<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and continued to refine her style during the course of her training. She completed a Bachelors Degree of <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Fine Art Studio Painting from Florida Atlantic University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Florida<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, a Bachelors Degree in Management Information Systems from <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Mercy College<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>New York<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and a Master Degree in Business Administration, MBA from <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Nova University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, Florida.
Mrs. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Peguero<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> is the founder of the Peguero <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Arte Libros Foundations<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> US 501(c)(3) and the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Art Books for Education Project<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> that focuses on art education for young <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Dominican<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> children in rural areas. In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2007<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>, the case was presented that even today, many <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Dominican<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> children in rural areas are not exposed to and do not have the opportunity to learn fine arts such as painting, sculpture, poetry and story writing. And for a country so rich in the music and dance arts to not have an emphasis in these areas was a loss for every child. One of the programs currently under implementation by the foundation is to supply rural schools with a set of <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Spanish<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> language art books that cover painting, sculpture, poetry and story writing. These would then be given to the school for their library and as some schools dont have a library, it would be the start of a long term collection to benefit all students. ArteLibros.org.
The <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Mariposa Cocoa<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> Preserve is a private preservation initiative owned and run by the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Peguero<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> family that combines sustainable organic cocoa farming practices and forest management with the protection of wildlife and nature. Located just west of the town of Miches, in the El Seibo province of the Dominican Republic, the preserve is only accessible via footpath and horseback. The countryside within the preserve was a primary landscape subject in many of the earliest Peguero paintings. <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Tours of the Mariposa Cocoa Preserve<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> is by invitation only with an annual artist expedition.
[MariposaCocoa.com].
