<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Ronald Raphael Coifman<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> is the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Phillips<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> Professor of Mathematics at <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Yale University<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Coifman<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> graduated from the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Geneva<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1965<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Coifman<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> is a member of the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>American Academy of Arts and Sciences<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Connecticut Academy of Science and Engineering<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, and the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>National Academy of Sciences<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. He is a recipient of the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1996<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>DARPA Sustained Excellence Award<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1996<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Connecticut Science Medal<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1999<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Pioneer Award of the International Society for Industrial and Applied Science<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>, and the <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1999<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> Nati