<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Hanne Sophie Greve<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> (born <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>14 April 1952<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Tønsberg<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Norway<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>) is a <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Norwegian<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> judge.
She graduated as cand.jur. in (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1976<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) and later (<tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1988<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) dr. juris at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>University of Bergen<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>. She is a former judge at the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>International Court of Justice<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>The Hague<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> and the <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>European Court of Human Rights<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> in <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Strasbourg<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>.
Before she was appointed to the position in the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Hague<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> she was a judge at <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Gulating Court of Appeal<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> and was involved in a number of national and international projects where human rights were in focus.
Her doctoral thesis was about refugees from <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Cambodia<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/>, a subject about which she has shown a particular interest and written about on various occasions.
<tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Greve<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> is currently (as of <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>2007<tag name="DATE" value="end"/>) writing a book on an alleged red herring manoeuver originating with <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Winston Churchill<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/>, concerning an allied invasion in <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1942<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> during <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>World War II<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Greve<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> is of the opinion that this invasion never was anything other than a distraction, a distraction that cost the lives of several hundred <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Norwegians<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>, among which the inhabitants of a fiskevær in the <tag name="LOCATION" value="start"/>Vestlandet<tag name="LOCATION" value="end"/> region of the country. No date has yet been given for the publication of the book.
On <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>April 30, 2007<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> <tag name="PERSON" value="start"/>Greve<tag name="PERSON" value="end"/> stated that <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Norway<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/> has come to be perceived as a haven for international war criminals just like the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>South American<tag name="MISC" value="end"/> countries after <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>World War II<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>. This statement was given in a TV documentary on <tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="start"/>Norway<tag name="ORGANIZATION" value="end"/>'s <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>TV 2<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>.
In <tag name="DATE" value="start"/>1995<tag name="DATE" value="end"/> she was awarded the <tag name="MISC" value="start"/>Fritt Ord Award<tag name="MISC" value="end"/>.
